So how was it going? Did you start?
Yeah, actually, actually hosting I want to know is actually many monks, they asked me
what's the problem about the understanding of dependent origination.
Actually, I asked a winner where I find you at least it's not necessary for me to know.
He thought that maybe I would get confused, but actually simply I don't understand what they're talking about.
I started only the teaching of the non-zero whoever, the timeless creation.
But I think in Zealand most monks, they don't understand that.
They think like a dependent origination process.
And that like two lines, three lines, I don't know.
But what they're talking about, I don't understand.
So it's very difficult for me to explain what the winner and winner thought.
So how do you explain to them?
Well, I don't think you have to start with a premise that they already have a different view.
I don't want to say never wrong view.
But yeah, from a real point of view, that's a wrong view.
Wrong view.
Because they approach a Patitsamapada as an explanation.
I remember Bikubodi.
He was very, very much sharing the traditional view.
And he would write about it and so on.
And he would say that no, this is not the core of the Dharma.
This is more like an encompassing explanation of the entire teaching and the purpose of it.
So in a way, when you look at it, it's not wrong.
Because any aspect of the Dharma contains the entire Dharma.
So you can say in relation to anything that it encompasses the entire Dharma.
Because it can't be enough for somebody to become an Arahant.
However, the Buddha himself said,
Dhamma is Patitsamapada.
Patitsamapada is the Dhamma.
Which means, oh no, it's actually quieter.
And then the Buddha also referred to Patitsamapada as the reason.
Not knowing that is why people remain bound to some sort.
So it's actually not an explanation of some ideal and overview.
It's a very direct insight.
And the fact is that every Patitsamapada formulation in the sutras
starts first by saying, with this, this is, or with the rising of this, this arises.
And that's already a calica.
So with the presence of this, this is present.
It doesn't say, as in the video pointed out, if you adopt a three-life interpretation,
it will be with the rising of this and then ceasing, then this arises,
then it ceases, then something else arises, then it ceases, then something like that.
But it doesn't say that.
It says, with the rising of this, this is.
So the determination, the reason, the cause, is present simultaneously with that,
which is being determined.
And then the Buddha would say himself, with the rising of what, this is,
and then he would formulate Patitsamapada.
And Bikobody was aware of that.
Because, you know, his palace is very good.
But he will refuse to give up his view of three-life interpretation.
So then he would dismiss this opening statement with this, this is,
and say, ah, this is just an abstract principle.
But actually, even an abstract principle is still a principle.
So whether it's an abstract or not, it's irrelevant.
But by saying abstract, you dismiss it.
But the fact is, it's a principle within which the whole Dharma is contained.
So if you dismiss that, and then your interpretation of that Patitsamapada
goes against the principle, means that's a contradiction.
And that's why it's wrong.
So he always, oh, just, ah, this is just an abstract principle.
And then puts it aside by labeling it such.
And then goes on into expounding how the feeling, connection,
and this, I even forgot what the traditional interpretation was.
But yeah, then you had other people say, well, it doesn't pretend.
I think that was K Nyananda Tehra, I think.
He was saying, doesn't pretend to the three-life, it pretends to one life.
But again, he took it as an explanation,
like as a kind of explaining what's happening.
That's not the Dharma.
If you're explaining what's happening, then it loses the aspect of open Ico,
leading on, that the Buddha talked about.
Because if I provide your explanation, you can say, oh, yes,
or you can say, oh, no.
But that's it, it stopped there.
Because it just remains in the level of intellect and the view.
But if the Buddha describes something that in order for you to understand,
it leads you on to more understanding.
That means, ah, that has the nature of the Dharma.
So you have to bear that in mind when you try to explain to somebody
who already has a different view.
There are very little chances of them understanding it.
Because it is possible for them to understand,
but it has to come from them.
In other words, they first have to see that they're wrong
and then have to start looking out for what is less wrong
in terms of their current view.
And then they might be receiving to hear it.
But if you're just trying to convince somebody otherwise,
it's useless. It won't work.
When I'm working on you, is it, ah, after if we try to understand
the teaching of Venomanyana Bhira,
a timeless relation, and then the past and the future,
both are not important, is it?
Is it correct?
Is it a traditional interpretation program
that passed on the future?
Oh, is it which means, oh, yeah.
No, that's it.
Well, whether it's your past, whether it's your future,
it's present as such.
Ah, past is present, future is present,
and the present is present,
which is the nature of humanism.
It's immediacy and reflection.
It's two modes of existence, so to speak.
So when you think about your past,
you think it in your present.
When you think about your present, you think it in your present.
When you think about your future, you think it in the present.
So if you abandon that present,
in terms of you and this full understanding,
then neither your past nor future,
nor that which is right in front of you,
can pertain to you anymore.
So in that sense, yeah, absolutely.
It's not important anymore.
Like, because if the past would be important
for the practice of the Dharma,
well, you couldn't practice the Dharma,
because you can't change what has happened.
If the future would be important,
in terms of how you just have to wait
and it will happen by itself,
well, then again, well, you just,
you can never know that directly for yourself.
You can just take it and faith and believe,
which is actually what most religions rely on.
Just these belief that eventually,
it will all work out fine for me.
But like, well, okay, good luck then.
But what makes you think so?
So even if, well, in the cases of people
who had horrible past, like Angulimala or other,
if they can overturn that,
and escape that sort of past,
but he couldn't, certainly,
he couldn't undo what he'd done.
And he'd done some serious things.
So you realize, it's in the present,
which is what I would have said.
It's here and now, visible, here and now.
You don't have to wait for it,
and you don't have to remember it.
It's here and now.
And in the same sense,
he called it up and I call it timeless,
not pertaining to time.
And that's exactly how it doesn't pertain.
If it was pertaining to time,
it would pertain to past.
It would require future.
But it doesn't.
It's timeless, which means all.
Because if past is present,
that's it.
One thing is present, like,
output it.
Okay.
Past is in present.
So that's a timeless relationship.
Present is in the present.
That's another timeless relationship.
Future is as future in the present.
When you look at it from the point of view of present,
even if it's present which you're looking at,
that's a timeless relationship.
So if you understand that,
then whatever particularly was that past you were thinking of,
or whatever particular thoughts were pertaining for the future,
that's irrelevant.
Because you abandoned present,
which means you abandoned past, future, and present,
that were in the present.
So nothing is left out.
And in terms of not having to understand,
but it's only about that.
Well, that's true, in a sense,
you don't have to understand all of the individual factors
the way the Buddha laid them down,
because they're quite subtle,
but you need to understand this timeless principle,
which is why the Buddha called Patitsambhara,
the Dhamma, Dhamma, Patitsambhara.
It's the same.
Actually, was it...
One who sees the Buddha sees the Dhamma,
one sees the Dhamma, one sees the Buddha.
Yeah, that's what the Buddha said.
And then, sorry, Buddha said,
in terms of Dhamma, Patitsambhara,
or Buddha, Patitsambhara.
What are you saying?
Yeah.
Either way, you don't have to understand all of the specific
factors of it.
But you have to understand that principle,
the big body dismisses is abstract,
because you understand that all of these things are implied.
And the fact that the Buddha, quite often,
described Patitsambhara differently,
sometimes it would have 12 factors,
sometimes it would have 15 factors,
sometimes it would stop,
if Nama Rupa, Vinyana, Vinyana, Nama Rupa,
he would omit the whole Vinyana,
Sankara, and then Sankara, Vija.
He wouldn't talk about it.
So you realize, oh, it's an exemplification
of a principle that can be laid out in different ways,
but it's still the same principle.
So if you dismiss the principle,
you get bogged down in the detail,
which becomes, basically,
you have to explain it,
you have to find the connections,
and it becomes linear psychological traditional commentary.
But if you keep the principle in mind,
as something that has been understood,
then you might even not think in terms of
the way the Buddha laid it down,
the whole Patitsambhara, it's your own.
You understood the principle,
and three different ignorance, and it's done.
Because again, all of those individual factors,
if you can refer to them as such,
it's not one to three, four, five, six, seven, eight.
They're all present simultaneously,
just on different layers,
of present on different layers within the same principle.
So it is all simultaneous.
But it doesn't mean that again,
you can approach it,
you can think in terms of these 12 factors
arising at the same time.
It depends how you look at it.
The principle arises at the same time.
With this, this is.
Now, if you take it further,
you can start defining the same principle,
further, and further, and further.
And that's how those factors were defined.
But it's not more than that.
And certainly, it's not about
drawing linear connection between the factors
and trying to present a chart
that will really encompass it all.
Well, that is definitely pointless.
And won't bring any,
well, any timeless understanding.
And I think the Unreal also mentioned
in one of the letters,
when somebody asked him,
well, this is the first time that they heard
that somebody defines
but did somebody learn that?
And so on.
They were not disagreeing with him,
but they were just curious,
how is that?
Well, he said, well, you know,
you might have another sort of partner
who wouldn't necessarily think in those terms.
Because if he didn't approach it
through that way in terms of understanding,
he won't be able to recognize that,
but what he would recognize,
what he will know is the principle
with this, this is.
And that principle is contained
in that representative insight
of a sort of partner,
which is whatever has the nature of rising
for every reason,
has the nature of ceasing
because it has a reason.
So permanence is implied
so that's how the being gets undone.
So again, it's not that, you know,
for a sort of partner,
for another hand, those 12 factors
just get kind of emerged,
like a glowing writing in the wall
and it's the principle that can be taken
as far as necessary.
Obviously, the Buddha being the foremost
of all of the Buddhas
in explaining the Dharma,
he really explained to the last
every possible detail,
which is why
the previous Buddha, when he explained
the Petit Sampada, he actually didn't go further
than Nama Rupa Vinanda.
Vinanda Nama Rupa.
And again, if you end up,
if you end the description
of the principle,
you end with mutual dependence
of two things.
And two things can be mutually dependent
only if they're simultaneously present.
If two sticks
hold each other,
which is that the similissari
put the gate for Nama Rupa,
determining Vinyana, Vinyana,
determining Nama Rupa,
they have to be up simultaneously.
They have to be down
and then lift the other one.
There is no dependence there.
So the entire relationship
which have a factor
of Petit Sampada,
you pick up, is
within that nature,
shares that nature.
Simultaneous dependence.
Well, this consciousness
is actually very important to anything.
Actually, before
many Christian people, they give
something like the desire.
Yeah.
Actually,
after actually knowing
the teaching of Vinyana,
and then, actually,
after meditating,
actually come to see, actually, this
consciousness is just like
supporting the
contact to arise.
Well, it's one of the aggregates.
So if somebody is after
the bond of understanding,
all of the aggregates need to be
understood.
Obviously, consciousness
is that which doesn't appear
like you can't see consciousness
directly as an object.
As you can see a cup
or a glance, or a door, or a car.
It just doesn't arise there.
Which is why
most often consciousness is
that with people regardless
of one way or the other.
But the fact that there is
something, even if you don't know
what it is, but
that there is a designation
that you can call consciousness,
you can see, and you can even
describe it, means there is something
in your experience that stands
for that.
So, full understanding of that
would mean full understanding
of consciousness.
In the same way, you would understand
objects of your senses.
Because it precedes them.
It's because your conscious
objects of your senses can arise.
If you are not conscious,
eyes won't be seen.
It is won't be hearing.
So it's a
negative phenomenon.
And that's why
when I told you before,
it's very important to
recognize this actual
and peripheral,
we spoke, because
consciousness is the ultimate
peripheral.
It's that peripheral that never
appears, but it's there.
And the most
precisely you can define,
you would be in the very
ambiguous terms,
such as, it's the presence,
presence of things.
The fact that things are
present means consciousness is there.
Obviously, people can now
overdo that,
and then end up
mystifying consciousness,
as the example you gave Christians,
or new age,
whatever, religion, really,
including Buddhism,
when they start over.
It's the ultimate consciousness.
It's the pure consciousness.
That consciousness is this consciousness.
You overmystify that presence,
but if there is nothing present,
you can't have the presence.
You need to have a thing
in order for it to appear.
So, that's why consciousness is
not independent.
It requires Nama Rupa.
If there isn't,
consciousness could not
be discerned.
So, as much as
consciousness determines that
which appears,
allows it to appear
to the same extent that which has appeared,
defines consciousness.
Otherwise, it wouldn't be there.
Consciousness is just
a six kind.
In particular,
you don't have to think of them
at the same time,
because they get complicated,
but you can take a sense.
Eyes are conscious.
That's the thing.
Most of people automatically assume
matter is out there,
consciousness is in here.
But actually matter
and consciousness
are on the same level
out there.
And their relationship
is known as Nama Rupa.
And that can have the internal aspect
and external aspect.
So actually, consciousness
is out there with the things.
Which is why
it can never be yourself.
For as long as you think
it's in here,
you will be taking it as me.
But if you see it out there,
in that material world,
then you realize,
well, I cannot have that
nothing more than I could
have matter to be mine.
And that's
what Yonero is talking about
instead of different terms.
When he was saying that Rupa
and Vinyana,
they were
well superimposed
or just like two different things
but they come together.
They don't mix.
I mean, they just get associated.
The result of that
is Nama Rupa.
It's the whole world
that you know that you can never know
your past, your future.
It's all within Nama Rupa.
Within the conscious matter.
Because if your consciousness is truly
in you, it would be independent from the body.
But when that material body
gets disintegrated,
consciousness goes.
It cannot stay.
You mean that the sense of self.
Sense of self.
The consciousness is in the body,
you know?
No.
Why would it be?
With the consciousness,
this body consciousness is associated
with the body.
The reason you can look in or out
or in and out or wherever you want
is because you are already conscious.
So the sense of space
the direction where you look
is possible only because
the body is already conscious.
The consciousness, the five aggregates
are already there.
So it's secondary to that.
If it's secondary means
you can't use it then to find
its origin.
Not the origin.
And if you, you know,
you look in the distance and you see
the tree really, really far out.
Well, your consciousness is out there.
Consciousness is out there.
I mean the...
Doesn't mean it's in that matter.
Means it's associated with that matter.
No matter how far it is.
Whether it's in your thoughts or through your senses.
It's actually external.
For other hand,
all of the aggregates become external.
Externally.
External means you mean
that they're not serve in the...
Well, yes, for other hand, yes.
External means not serve.
And the Buddha did say that
for somebody completely free from ignorance,
what is left is
this conscious body
and all
whatever name and form externally.
That's what's left.
So the body
that is associated with the consciousness
or consciousness associated with the body
is just like
two completely different things
that kind of come and stop together
which is the birth.
But then
when one of them goes
the other one cannot remain standing.
But it's not that consciousness enters
in the body.
Because any notion of space
is the fact that you're conscious.
So consciousness cannot be
in its own result.
For other hand,
does any idea appear that
as my body, but the thought itself
is not this.
Well, even when he thinks my
eye, I am or I am this
or this is my carp order,
that doesn't imply
the emotional significance
of me and sense of self.
In other words, I can say that's my cup
but if somebody comes and steal it
I won't suffer an account of it.
But as a designation of speech
you can, you know, in the Buddha said that.
Well, the target that says I am
but it doesn't mean that he really thinks he is.
He's just the figure of speech
becomes for him.
Where a practitioner, when he says
I am for him, that is his sense of self.
So as a designation, it's valid.
You have to designate it somehow.
He's just a misunderstanding
that goes with it.
That's removed.
In case of an other hand.
You thought itself was different?
Actually, different, you know, I think?
Well, differently as much as there is no
greedy version of the illusion ever.
Again, to arise.
Well, they cannot appear.
Cannot.
No. So, he's not just temporarily free from
greedy version of the illusion.
An other hand, he's free from
a possibility of those things arising.
Which is why he's another hand.
There might be pleasing thoughts,
displeasing thoughts, neutral thoughts.
But pleasing thoughts won't be inducing
any more lust.
Displeasing thoughts won't be inducing any anger.
And neutral thoughts won't be inducing any delusion.
Hmm.
Displeasing.
How it happens in the mind of our hunter?
Displeasingness.
Oh, this is disagreeable.
It's a feeling.
Well, I know, because if you could see the difference,
you would be on a way to become an hunter.
How can something be displeasing
without implying
ill will or aversion?
Hmm.
If you can see that, then, oh, keep doing it.
And then you learn how to be displeased
without being angry.
Hmm. Which means you free yourself from anger.
Hmm.
But
you can't, like, feeling
as feeling for a protugina
is not the same...
Well, it's not the same
as arrogance feeling
as an aggregate.
So then, that's why,
when the Buddha would talk,
he would make a categorical difference.
He would say, no feeling.
In case of an argument,
because there's no protugina feeling.
No.
But that doesn't mean that he's just dead.
Because, again, that's another protugina's reference, then.
Hmm.
And none of the protugina's references
can apply to another hunt.
Which is why, again, we have said,
if protugina would understand
what a state of our hunt is,
he would be on the way to become one.
Hmm.
So it's not that you can get a clear idea
and still be a protugina.
Clear idea frees you from the state of protugina.
Hmm.
In the case of an argument,
it's different.
Well, it's in between.
So, the overall picture,
the fundamental principle,
that's all understood,
that's all set.
But they have to keep repeating it.
Until all the habits,
they were based on unwholesome,
greedy version delusion,
disappear,
and then they can stop.
So, if you're trying to have, like, a clear definition,
you can't.
It's just,
well, the most precise you can get
is what Buddha himself used
to describe the four different
stages of enlightenment.
But in the beginning,
they weren't.
He didn't. They didn't exist.
That doesn't mean the dhamma didn't exist
or the stages didn't exist.
It was basically somebody who understood the dhamma
and somebody who fully developed it
and now went beyond and is free.
And then there was that whole,
whole chapter in Samyutani Kavan,
whenever somebody would die,
renderable under,
would go to the Buddha and ask him,
oh, such and such person died.
What's their destination?
And then we say,
oh, he will return one more time,
or he won't return it all.
Oh, he will be reborn in this heaven.
He will be reborn.
But it was just becoming all the time.
He said, well, if,
he will ask me about the river,
it's just going to be a real bother for me.
So why don't I tell you something,
that you can use as a criteria
to decide for yourself
where most likely that person will be reborn?
So Sotabana,
at most, will have seven rivers.
He might have less.
So it's not.
Sotabati, seven,
or something like that.
It's a guideline.
It's like a little
stopping points
of one, actually,
just one process,
which is developing,
understanding the Dharma,
and fully developing that understanding.
So then he would say,
he's suffering and we would return one more time.
And then he wouldn't return.
And then he would give that in relation to the ten fetters.
Because,
by dwelling on those ten fetters,
by contemplating them,
you will, you can fully understand them.
And when you fully understand them,
you understand that you understood.
So it's not like, oh,
however understood means, oh, there is doubt there.
It means you haven't understand them enough.
So sometimes people might,
when they get,
when they're overestimate themselves,
or are just plain deluded,
they refuse to doubt.
And they think that's the way to go beyond the doubt.
When they just do not doubt.
If somebody doubts, they just ignore that.
If somebody doesn't know,
I think no, no, I refuse to accept that.
But that's just ridiculous.
Doesn't, doesn't work like that.
So you should doubt all the time.
Because doubt keeps turning things around.
And then,
it can make you, it can enable you
to develop understanding
that will then be truly impenetrable
to your full-on acts of doubt.
Because if you never doubt,
you don't know if you'll be on the doubt.
If you doubt all the time
and learn how to,
while doubting, go beyond that doubt,
ah, then you can truly know for yourself
and you cannot doubt that.
Because you're doubting,
and it makes no difference.
Lord Buddha, you encouraged people to
question some doubts.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Whenever for you,
you're actually not only one.
Several times tower me that
Lord Buddha actually said
that we must believe what he said.
And not,
you don't actually encourage people
to question beliefs.
It's not correct.
No, it's not correct.
Oh, yeah, he said, don't take my word for it.
He said that himself.
Don't just believe what I say.
It's great for you if you have such faith.
But you don't have to.
No, you should examine it
and see why is it so.
And then your faith will be unshakable.
Because you understood it.
Yeah.
Quite the opposite, quite the opposite.
Because often, yes, you would have, no, no, just don't doubt.
Just do what I said. Stop asking.
No, no, he was, like, he would even encourage monks
to keep interrogating each other all the time.
Because that's how you progress.
That's how you develop understanding.
Obviously, sometimes people can take that,
oh, well, the Buddha encourages us to doubt and to question.
And then you state that for just being argumentative.
You know, when somebody just wants to argue
over any little point.
And then, well, the Buddha won't know.
He didn't say that. He said, if you have a genuine interest,
you have to keep overturning things.
And like digging, digging, and digging, and digging,
while you're through conversation with others
all inside of your mind.
Because that's how understanding can come.
But, yes, sometimes people just use that as an excuse
to indulge their habits of arguments
or just enjoying the debate or things like that.
And he didn't encourage that.
He didn't encourage debates for the sake of debate.
I think in the history, this is actually
I really wanted to know it.
I think there are a few other things that share
even from that, even for the Buddha's channel, you can see
the career, the record is perfect.
I've said, there are so many cases that in sutra
I've mentioned that there are some areas
that are like immoral or whatever.
But I actually want to understand this.
Some people thought he was angry.
But there is no anger in his mind.
Yeah.
How much does it have?
Because I heard it's a very harsh speech.
Yeah, that was your case.
Well, the first thing is, it's possible.
But it's very unlikely.
So when you get cases like that,
there are a few cases in the sutras,
or even Vanderbilt Chana and Sariput,
the one who committed suicide,
the Buddha thought that he wasn't an other hand.
And Buddha said, well, why do you say that?
Because he was associating with bad families,
with families of bad reputation.
He was very close with them.
So they all thought, bad of him.
But they said, no, he wasn't an other hand.
So the external measure, it's not necessarily a measure.
And the putusions criteria cannot encompass an other hand.
And if they do, it's accidentally.
They don't know why.
But nevertheless, from, I think, probably for 80 or 90%
of people, 100 means there won't be any of those things left.
I think there is some, well, like in the case of an angry,
well, seemingly angry aren't.
The Buddha said, well, the reason why his speech is still like that,
is for 500 lifetimes.
500 times, he was reborn and lived, I don't know, a long time.
So let's just say he lived 80 years each time.
It's like, oh, 4,000?
4,000.
But it's 4,000, 4,000 years.
He was reborn in the Brahmin family.
And they were always higher than the others.
They would always speak convincingly to the others.
So the habit just got so established that even he became an other hand.
He's actually just calculating the same form of speech.
The feeling itself is different for their hands.
There's no angry.
I was thinking there was something kind of anger that taught itself
already disowned.
Well, again, the only way you can look at it is through your own.
Like, window or experience, you can't really.
And you can actually relate to that.
I'm sure everyone at some point experienced when some person
told you something that you really believed it was like that.
And then you realized it was completely different.
While they were saying this, they meant something completely different.
And you didn't know that.
You couldn't know that.
So in the same sense, when you come across somebody who speaks angrily,
you end up assuming he's angry.
But then you can find a later on that actually, no, he wasn't.
He just says, have it.
Or if you go again, like, you know,
I've been in Thailand, Sri Lanka.
So you see the different cultures, different things people do.
And sometimes, some things people do in Thailand
consider very rude in Europe.
And vice versa, something we do in Europe.
So you know that there can be a different significance
of the identical external output.
So you can do something exactly the same in one country.
Do exactly the same in another country.
It can be completely different.
Or even coming from the same person.
Sometimes you can say something exactly the same.
And be angry about it.
And not be angry about it.
So anger is indifferent to that.
Often it's a manifestation of anger.
I act of both the speech of mind.
But if there is no anger, there is still both the speech of mind.
And they will still be doing things.
And that's why it's a manifestation of anger.
Hmm.
For areas, is it correct that I was thinking that
Aria means totally, I think,
become indifferent to any feeling or thought.
Or is it?
Actually, that's why I was thinking that some of
these behavioral, not the arhanda, are areas.
I basically couldn't understand because
any kind of an Angkor Santhor,
in the case of Aria, not the arhanda.
Just an Aria means totally indifferent to such a feeling of thought.
Well, no.
Totally different would be an arhanda.
Different.
Totally indifferent would be an arhanda.
Totally indifferent means the economy.
There would be fully developed to pay car.
That's totally indifferent.
40,000, by the way.
So, in case of an Aria,
again, it depends on how far his faculties developed.
Like, you know, when...
Well, there was that sutra when the Buddha
was staying in that forest.
And on the other side of that forest,
it was a group of young men and women.
They paid those courtesans to come with them in the forest.
They were all getting loose and central.
And then they all fell asleep after.
And one of them woke up,
one of the courtesans woke up and stole all of their gold money.
And ran away.
When they realized they start chasing them.
So, imagine their state of mind
after this pleasure,
central evening,
and then full of anger over like,
oh, we've been deceived and so on,
they were chasing to kill her most likely.
And then they accidentally,
as they were chasing,
they came across the Buddha.
They didn't even know he was the Buddha.
And so, he told them,
well, why don't you sit down
and I can teach you something instead.
They will be more beneficial to you than finding that gold.
So, you know,
I'm sure some of them come down,
but still,
I'm pretty sure they're still angry.
And then upset.
Yet, right there and then,
he calmed them down.
He first he talked about the significance of virtue,
why it's good to develop in generosity.
They understood that because everybody can understand that.
And there was a sufficient basis for them to then
develop right view,
because then he spoke about the Dharma
and they understood exactly what he meant.
And they all became sort of honest.
So, you realize,
oh, okay,
it's not that hard then.
If somebody can have their mind full of lust
and then aversion and anger,
and then they could come down
and then they could see the nature of things.
But that doesn't oblige them to follow it.
So, they might have well understood it,
but I think it comes from their previous rights.
I mean, they have many practices.
Well, I think what comes from previous life
is the fact that you're born as human
with all of your faculties intact.
Nothing else excuses somebody
for not understanding Dharma
or understanding it.
In other words,
those who make the effort will understand
those who don't, they won't.
But yeah, there is something's previous life,
but I think people put too much emphasis in that
as a way of absorbing
themself from responsibility.
Oh, well, no.
If you're a born, intelligent,
normal, human being who can think normally,
discern normally,
there is no excuse for not understanding Dharma.
They're just seasoned.
Everything is there.
So, if you don't understand it,
because you haven't been making the right effort.
And it's kind of blunt,
but that's exactly how it is.
So,
when you had those,
like when sometimes the householders
would come and see the Buddha
or even come to complain about something,
or criticize you,
and then he would come and down,
talk about them,
and then they would understand them,
and become sort of honest.
And sometimes they would say,
oh, from now on,
I'm going to become a monk,
and practice this.
But sometimes they would,
and sometimes they would say,
well, thank you, Lord.
We are very busy.
We have to go back home,
we have lots of things to attend to.
As sort of honest,
like his father,
when his father came and complained about
because he ordained him,
he came only tears and upset.
Because, well, first you went,
now you took my only grandson.
But then the Buddha came down,
made him a sort of money
through explaining the dharma,
and they all,
thank you very much,
I have to go now, I'm busy.
So, they don't necessarily always want to practice it,
especially because, oh,
this understanding is already quite an accomplishment,
and they get content in that,
which means that three quarters
of their mind still needs to be
dealt with,
but they don't.
They're still one quarter.
So, the spirit,
it's not that clear,
clear cut,
but in the nutshell,
then the student of one needs to be done,
but they don't necessarily want to do it right now.
They will eventually,
they can't ignore it for too long,
which is why,
so the one is that,
at most, seven beavers,
no more than that.
So, that, and even, even that,
the whole, as I said before,
the whole,
the vision of Suttapana,
Saka Gamyal Gamyal Gamyal Gamy,
sometimes the Buddha
would omit Saka the Gamy,
even he would just say,
Suttapana,
and then he would start talking about Anagami,
and then he would talk about Anagami,
and as I said,
in the beginning,
they were not.
He was just fully enlightened,
or not fully enlightened.
So, it's a guideline.
It's a guideline,
I don't know, basically,
of understanding the Dharma.
And he was also a guideline,
given to people to reassure them,
just reason they came again,
across that sort of,
Mahanam and the household there,
who was,
he wasn't clear in the suitors,
whether he was Saka the Gamyal Suttapana,
because he was never said,
he was always said that he's a noble disciple,
who still lives the household life.
And,
and there was this, this Suttapana,
and he says,
so he knew that he was a,
well, he knew that he was a noble disciple,
but it was before the Buddha,
defined all of these seven reverts,
so he came to the Buddha one night,
one evening, and he said,
oh, how is it Lord that,
like, you know,
I'm the one who understood the Dharma,
and I know that I understood it,
and so on.
But on some occasions,
when I walk on the,
like now,
when I come to see the Lord in the evening,
and it's getting dark,
and if I come across,
a stray dog,
a stray man,
or a stray elephant,
or some form of danger,
he forgets about all the Dharma he understood,
and, you know, he gets filled with fear,
and then he says,
what if I were to die
at that moment,
on account of that stray dog,
stray elephant or stray man,
what would my destination be?
So he was concerned,
that if he dies in that state of mind,
although he knew that he was a noble disciple,
he was concerned,
and if he dies in that state of mind,
his destination might be unfortunate,
because,
unless you have a supernatural body,
you can't see those things.
And the Buddha said,
oh, you have absolutely nothing to fear.
The one who understood the Dharma,
who developed that kind of noble virtue,
noble understanding,
nobody's,
even if your mind is overwhelmed with fear,
when you die,
it still won't make a difference
to your destination.
But the interesting bit, to me,
that is that,
oh, there was a sotapanarsaka,
the Rami,
who wasn't sure about certain things.
He was sure about the nature of the Dharma,
but he doesn't know
how far he's understanding of the Dharma,
the real understanding of the Dharma,
how far he takes him,
and for that,
the Buddha would often talk,
like,
I will see the mountain,
Himalayas,
and then he would pick up seven grains of sand.
And he said,
the size of that mountain
is the size of suffering
that sotapana has abandoned,
and all he has left,
is the amount of this,
seven grains of sand.
So that's how much he has destroyed.
So it's quite an accomplishment,
even to get that understanding.
And that's why he will give those encirigments
of that kind,
but sotapana doesn't see that.
He sees the Dharma,
he sees the time of principle,
he sees the four noble truths,
he sees the way out of suffering,
and actually that in itself,
is more than enough.
All of this comes in as an extra.
Over the other hand,
they don't remember their previous,
not over, not only some.
Sorry, Buddha couldn't remember,
I knew it.
He said,
the foremost,
after the Buddha,
in teaching the Dharma,
in expanding every angle,
and approach,
just like,
you know,
people couldn't see the difference
whether he would speak of the Buddha,
because he understood all of it,
but he said he couldn't see
even a little goblin.
Like nothing,
he couldn't see any of that.
Neither supernatural,
nothing,
he was just non-existent for him,
which is why it's irrelevant,
whether you see it or not.
It makes no difference.
Some people can,
but...
I was thinking that remembering the past,
it's very important to understand the role of karma.
It's not necessary.
No, no, no.
If karma is truly
determined by your past,
you're stuck.
You can't do anything about it.
If Angoli Mala's karma was in his past,
he couldn't have not overcome it,
because he couldn't bring those people back to life.
Action is intention,
and intention is very present thing,
and things you do are very present,
and that's where you abandon it.
And when you abandon your...
Through, like, a full understanding,
through abandoning ignorance,
when you abandon your action by both this speech and mind,
nothing you have done,
nothing you would have done
can pertain to you anymore.
In the same sense,
when you abandon the nature of present,
what's present,
you abandon past that can be present,
you abandon future that can be present,
and you abandon present,
that's present.
There are some people
they are always doing wrong things,
but it's quite important
to understand karma.
Well, no, it's not action, no.
I think it's important for them to understand Vipaka.
Because karma,
I think the whole notion
you've got overly mystified now,
it almost becomes like this energy
of righteousness,
like, well, that's your karma,
you deserve it,
or things like that,
but karma means action.
Feeling this carpet water is a form of karma.
Whole sum,
around whole sum,
people might want to dwell on Vipaka
on the results,
on that karma.
And that's something
that can cause sense awareness,
because if you start thinking,
well, if I misbehaved,
if I do these things,
I could end up experiencing
very bad results,
and then that can inspire them
to be more whole sum
and do less evil
or whatever they've been doing before.
But in terms of thinking about karma,
and understanding the workings of the karma,
or something like that,
the Buddha said
that it can only bring madness
or destruction.
Unless you're a Buddha,
who can then fully understand
the workings of the karma,
if he directs his mind towards it,
if somebody else tries,
you just end up distracting yourself
about pointless things,
or go mad on account
of really trying to understand
something that you cannot possibly comprehend.
Which, enough,
it just says it in a different way,
it's irrelevant
in terms of understanding.
Like you understand the nature of action,
you abandon it,
but you don't understand,
why when you've done something
in the past now,
that was the result of this,
that's a complete
like looking elsewhere
in a wrong direction.
How Buddha could teach
the importance to be a Burgess,
the Burgess,
how would he teach it?
Well, he would teach that
because of the,
he would say about the Vipaka,
he would say about the results.
And then again,
even that,
he said,
well, don't believe what I say,
but reflect for yourself.
And I think I've already said before,
when you told those people,
okay,
it's a fact that you don't know
whether there is an ex-life or not.
It's a matter of belief,
you don't want to take it or you want to know.
But actually,
even then,
you can use your intelligence.
So even puttuja,
I can understand that,
whereby you can kick in just,
basically,
sit and think,
okay, I don't know
that there is a future life,
or not.
If I misbehave here,
right now, in this life,
well, I'll get in trouble
from people,
that's a fact,
I'll be put in jail,
people will hate me,
if I get away with it,
people will trust me,
I have to be on the run,
I have to keep looking
around all the time,
I'll live in fear,
or whatever,
so that's all unhoveled,
some states.
And then,
if there is a future life,
then he'll experience
even worse rebirth
when a count of bad actions.
If there isn't no future life,
okay, he won't experience
any bad rebirth,
but he'll still suffer
in this life when a count
of his bad actions.
Now, the other person
who thinks,
well,
if I do good in this life,
well, people will praise me,
which is nice,
people will be helpful to me,
people will want to
repay my kindness,
which is nice,
people will trust me,
which is nice.
And then,
if there is no future life,
well, so big,
at least,
I live a good life here.
If there is a future life,
then I'll also get a better
rebirth,
so I'll win on both fronts,
and if I misbehave,
I'll lose on both fronts.
So even then,
it doesn't have to be a matter
of belief anymore.
There is a clear understanding,
almost a practical,
and oh,
so it's actually,
that's why this is awesome.
That's why that's awesome.
That's why it's better to behave,
than to misbehave.
And then,
they have no knowledge
of previous lives,
no knowledge of
future Vipaka,
waiting for them,
is just intelligence,
human intelligence,
basic discerning.
You just stop and think,
for a second,
and it becomes apparent.
Because there's no denying
that if you do unwholesome things,
people will complain.
If you meet someone,
if you can't stop doing wrongdoing,
how you can...
Some people,
there's a problem in front of me,
keep killing the snakes,
and all of those things,
and it's impossible for them to stop.
They say,
it's impossible.
How do you...
No, they're lying to themselves.
If they say it's impossible,
what that means,
doesn't mean it's impossible,
it means they can't be bothered
to try to stop.
So they'll keep doing it.
But you can't stop it,
if they don't want to stop it.
Unless you're stronger than them,
and twist their arm,
and restrain them
until the snake escapes.
You can't do it.
So...
So you never give in otherwise?
Well, the reason,
I mean, you could...
Again,
if you can...
If you try to convince people too hard,
they will start
ignoring you even harder.
So unless the person who just
done something silly,
unwholesome in front of you,
is not willing to listen to you.
No amount of things you say,
and you'll be wasting your words then.
They won't take any heed.
If they come and...
Oh, yeah, okay, well,
like if they really want to understand it,
then it's a different matter.
Matter.
And then you can tell them
just what I told you now.
Like,
even if you don't know
whether you're bad action,
we'll bring the...
the future misery in terms of the future rebirth.
Well, you can still know for sure
that in this life,
it will.
And also,
the fact is that you don't know
whether you're going to be reborn or not.
Surely you should play it safe.
As if you are going to be reborn.
So just in case,
I'll behave here.
I'll be praised here on my behavior.
And if there is a future rebirth,
then I'll be safe.
So it's almost like a precaution.
Just in case I'll behave.
If I know for sure that there is no life,
this is going to live here,
I'll do whatever I like,
but you cannot know that for sure.
And that's something you can know.
You can know for sure
that you don't know these things for sure
and you can never will,
which is why it's better to
use wisdom and say,
well, why would I like a risk?
Especially when
we're not risking our behaving properly,
we'll only respect in this life
and protect in the future life
if there is one.
It's a winner in every respect.
But people usually say,
well, I don't know that there is a rebirth.
Well, yeah.
But you don't know that there isn't a rebirth,
but they don't think that far.
They just think the first part
because that means,
oh, well, I don't believe that
I can do what I want here.
But actually,
even if you don't believe or believe,
if you stop and think,
it would become apparent
why you shouldn't be doing those things.
But again,
unless a person is willing to hear that,
everyone listen to you.
They don't want this to anybody.
You know,
a lot of people don't really get quite.
Well, yeah,
sometimes people come and ask,
ask him the wrong question
or they would formulate the question wrongly.
She said that.
Sometimes the target that
meets this person
and the target that has inclination
to teach him.
But then this misguided person
formulates his question wrongly
and then the target that goes silent.
And that's what I teach him then.
Ah, yeah.
Because they came from a wrong place.
Because whatever he says,
they'll take it wrongly.
Or sometimes they come with the question
and ask him,
like when they ask him,
oh, must they go down?
Is there a self?
So if you say,
yes, there is,
but there isn't that person
who will take,
that's not self.
A self.
Because you already implied in his question,
that there is a self.
So which one is it?
So the Buddha was quiet.
He said,
well, does that mean there isn't?
Well, there isn't.
There isn't.
Or both.
No, yeah.
And he was just quiet.
And then this person left.
And I asked him,
why didn't you answer?
He said, well,
because whatever I would have said,
he would have misunderstood.
Why?
Because he was coming
with a completely wrong attitude.
So he wasn't willing to understand.
Then I think on a later occasion,
when I'm in the told him,
you should answer like this.
Don't answer like that.
And then he asked rightly,
that the target of the told him
and then he understood.
Because that's a big surprise.
We thought that,
when I was going up on you,
actually, he first told me
that there is no self.
He's wrong.
There is no self.
Before, always,
I heard that,
the old monks,
they teach there is no self.
There is no self.
It's a denial.
He is quiet.
I have seen,
and didn't notice my mistake.
And he told me,
that in the case of Potuchana,
it's impossible to say that
there is no self.
Exactly.
But why many monks
they don't know is there?
Well, because they are Potuchana's.
Yeah, maybe.
Like,
if somebody is not a Potuchana,
they would know,
they wouldn't be saying it.
It's not written in sutra
that for Potuchana,
we can't say that there is no self.
Nothing written.
Nothing.
I mean, Potuchana
should see through the nature of herself,
that it cannot be his,
and that's why it becomes not self.
It doesn't mean no self.
It's not self.
It's not myself.
I think that's not just that everywhere,
in the West, in the entire of everywhere.
That's not just in Sri Lanka.
Because when anybody comes across Buddhism
on the superficial terms,
that's the first thing you come across.
Ah, there is no self.
And then that negative,
like, becomes yourself.
Oh, yes.
I don't believe in self.
That's my self, believe.
It's much harder than that.
As I said before,
no, you actually have to first see
what your self is,
in order to stop regarding it as yours.
And that's a very different thing.
And that's why you have atta,
and then you have an atta,
like, not, no self,
but not self.
But that which is taken as self,
and then understood as not self,
is still there.
That thing doesn't change.
But when you say no self,
you just deny the whole thing.
For us they are self,
but it's not self.
There is that which used to be taken as self.
Used to be.
Yeah, but now there is no self.
No, self.
Or rather it's not self.
Not self.
Every experience of an arahant is not self.
No, self.
What does it mean that the eight-pukarande,
the one-pukarande,
the part and the...
Well, it means what I said before.
It's only defined later.
So the commentator,
the interpretation of those mind moments
when you kind of want to
and then you enter into the...
You enter the path,
then you realize the fruit
to the next moment.
It's just a lot of nonsense.
In the certain means.
And again,
even that division came from the Buddha,
from somebody who had such vision.
But people might not know that,
necessarily for themselves.
Or for others.
When you inside the public,
you can recognize an arahant.
There is another sort,
I think,
I might mention before,
but Venerable Badiya,
wasn't it?
The dwarf.
You've been marked it.
Well, no, no.
You don't recognize it.
Yes.
In Udanas,
when Sariputra was teaching
this monk,
thinking he still had work to do.
But this monk was just sitting silently,
just hearing whatever Sariputra was saying.
And then the Buddha saw the occasion
and he said,
Oh, look at the occasion.
Venerable Sariputra
is very diligently teaching
Venerable Badiya,
not knowing the Venerable Badi
is already an arahant.
So he actually didn't have any work
to do any more.
But there wasn't a parent.
In Suta,
the clearly sweet one,
that A8,
Pukaral,
one Pukaral,
what does it mean?
Well, no.
It's clearly written in terms of again,
and it's clearly written
that there are four stages of enlightenment.
The Buddha talked about it.
Buddha said that
there is a somebody,
there is a difference,
within somebody with a sort of partner,
there is a difference
between somebody who
fully realized
that he's a sort of partner.
And somebody who didn't quite yet realize
that he is actually a sort of partner.
So in other words,
you develop understanding
of the four-nover truths, for example.
And you understood it.
But now the benefits of that understanding
have not become a parent yet.
And that's the difference
between the path and the fruit.
For some people,
they understood it
and they understood it so hard
that the benefits
are pretty much immediate.
For others,
they are not.
But what the Buddha said
in relation to that,
is that if somebody has,
like in case of a sort of partner,
somebody that is to the Dhamma,
the benefits will
have to be reached.
If not before,
then at the moment of its death.
And it's not nothing
kind of magical or mystical,
it simply means that
nature understanding of the Dhamma
basically goes through the nature of death
and panic and falling apart
and losing aggregate.
So if you understood that,
when those aggregates
do start falling apart,
you will fall apart
through that understanding.
Because that's what you have understood.
Which is why,
at the moment of death,
the latest,
you will get the benefits
of your understanding.
And that's the same
for any of the aggregates.
Whether it's a sort of partner
and his fruit,
circling, I mean,
his fruit,
orangami and his fruit,
or oranghan,
then his fruit.
There is a career
in between the
Anagami and oranghan.
What's up over here?
No, there isn't.
No, there isn't a career line at all.
That's why there's that
that suit them.
And those,
all those monks came.
I don't know, hundreds of them.
And they all declared
an orangish.
And somebody has the Buddha
is that really the case?
And he said,
some of them are truly
arahans, but some of them
overestimated themselves
and they're still anagamis.
So, he didn't like,
you know, they were not like
putunjanas completely
deluded thinking
they're arahans.
No, they were anagamis,
thinking they were arahans.
Road Buddha
but they couldn't.
He could distinguish it.
Yeah.
So, for road Buddha,
there is a career line
between Anagami and oranghan.
Yes.
Yeah, because he was
the same Buddha.
Only he can.
Well, only he can,
or sometimes people
had the ability to see
other people's minds,
especially when they could see.
But there was, you know,
random.
There was not a guarantee.
So, that is a meaning
of Aikukara.
It's basically,
right, not career.
It's basically, as I said,
it's one development.
That's why somebody
can become an arahant
in the first watch of the night.
But it doesn't mean,
it's the same path
they walk.
It's just how fast
they walk it.
And whether they stop
and the resting stops
or not.
That's the difference.
But it's one path.
It's the same path.
It's not, like,
trying to achieve
four different things,
or something like that.
And even those
four different things
are sometimes three different things.
When he admitted
Sakyadagami
from the descriptions.
Well, if you read
in the San Yutani kaya
part,
but you think,
Sakyadagami means rebirth
in pure bones.
But there is the whole chapter
in San Yutani kaya
of Adanagami's.
There are, like,
hundreds of
different realms
within the pure bones,
whereby
the Adanagami's
would be reborn,
depending on
how big Adanagami's
they were.
Yeah.
So it's just like,
it's, it's,
well, it's kind of irrelevant
in that sense.
It's relevant in a sense
of abandoning the
ten fetters.
And that's something
something people can
contemplate in practice
in regard to.
How far and what rebirth
unless they're
supernatural powers
or unless you live
with the Buddha
or somebody like that,
it will be a distraction.
And it's not,
it's not,
it's not directly related
to the practice of Adanagami.
It can be an encouragement
if it comes from,
well, again,
you don't need to have
somebody now.
If you read the sutras,
you can see what the Buddha
was saying in relation
to people who were
saying this, this, this,
this.
And that can be an encouragement
to the ten.
Mm-hmm.
I was to know that,
what did you mean
that you said that
what I see
bubble in the mind?
You said that
that is a total sound,
the total sight.
What does it mean?
Or a total?
Five senses.
I don't know.
For what they are
because of your mind.
They will meet
in your mind.
Mm-hmm.
And because of that,
the mind comes first,
like the,
is it the first verse
of Dhammapada?
The mind is the four-run,
of all things.
So in other words,
if you, like,
if you have an object
of your sight,
again,
if you look at a flux
in front of you,
see, you can't just
have a pure sight.
Because even colors
are distinguished
as different colors.
What is it?
Well, your eyes
cannot distinguish.
Like, if your eyes
would operate
without your mind,
well, it's inconceivable.
You can't even think
like that.
In other words,
when you look at the
flask, there is already
a significance
implied in it.
There is already a thought
of flask.
Even if you know,
don't know the name,
don't know what it is.
There is a thought
of object being seen.
Mm-hmm.
And that's the sight.
Before, before you heard this,
just up to the
with consciousness,
and this is a ton of object,
the ninth and the sense of organ.
With the help of consciousness,
the contact arise.
Then the sight is called
feeling.
It's not correct.
The perception means that
this is perhaps.
Yeah, perception means perception.
Yeah.
You see it?
You don't feel your perception.
You feel your feeling.
Feeling?
No.
Oh, the supposition.
There, you can be surprised.
What kind of feeling?
Maybe nothing.
Maybe neutral feeling.
Yes.
But if it's perhaps something,
I don't know,
something very significant
that some person gave you.
And if you look at that,
then the feeling will arise.
So it doesn't always.
That's the thing.
Like, feeling has its own domain.
Perception has its own domain.
If you want to understand it correctly,
you have to start applying that understanding
to those domains correctly.
In other words,
if I ask you,
how do you feel now?
There has to be a feeling there.
And you can say,
oh, I feel all right,
which is a form of pleasure.
You can say,
well, I don't feel that well.
I'm a bit tired,
which is a form of one pleasure.
You can feel neutral.
And that situation,
that general situation of
you sitting here in this city,
talking on Dhamma,
that is already
something that you are perceiving peripherally,
in your thoughts.
It's present,
because if I ask you,
where are you now?
You will immediately know where you are.
You will have to stop and figure out.
Because it's already there,
so you just have to access it with your attention.
Now, if you forget about that,
which is where actually
where it should start,
the contemplation starts to start
at the most general level you are capable of.
But if you don't know that,
then you will take a random object
and try to examine it
on a scientific psychological
and then try to discover the nature of perception
and the nature of feeling.
So I look at this thing in my hands.
What do I feel?
Even if you get any understanding from that,
it will be on the level of intellectual satisfaction.
Oh, yes, it makes sense.
But leaves the whole domain
of feeling and perception
on that general level,
absolutely intact.
So in other words,
you have to start
from the opposite direction.
So you have to think,
you are here,
away from home,
in this city,
talking about Dhamma.
Or you can define it,
whichever way you are.
But that's your current situation.
Within that situation,
there are objects around you.
Within those objects,
they are more particular objects.
They are more important objects.
They are less important objects.
They are more useful objects like that cushion.
They are less useful objects like that being
that you don't need at the moment.
And that's all within that experience
as a whole of you being in this room
sitting down and talking.
So that was the demandfulness
of the body postures
works on that level.
If you are aware of your body posture,
that's almost like the most general thing
that determines your current situation.
And that situation is perceived,
that situation is felt,
that situation is intended.
What's the technique at the...
And on the level of that situation
is where the contact happens.
And only because you are already contacted,
you can distinguish all these particular things
around you with your eyes, ears, nose, and so on.
So in that general situation,
is where the three meet.
They don't meet like cause and effect
as often the commenter is in terms of
you have one hand, another hand,
you have the sense organs
and the consciousness
and the meat and the sound is the sound
to whatever it was.
No, the sound is the contact.
I forgot it.
But the point is...
They don't meet like that.
Well, even the nature of meeting
is timeless.
It does not involve time.
Clapping hands involve time.
You can put it as simple as that.
Salayatana is part of the Patitson Pada.
Whatever is part of the Patitson Pada,
she is the principal of the Patitson Pada,
otherwise it wouldn't be included there.
So it means that conscious matter
is already there.
And if things come in range
as the Buddha said,
the corresponding engagement occurs.
But it doesn't occur always.
So if things come in range,
that can be the cause for the contact.
But then also consciousness
and their working sense organs
are a matter
are required.
Because if something happens to them,
there won't be any sight arising.
There won't be any hearing
or anything like that.
If your ear organs are damaged
or whatever, even while you're still alive,
that's it.
They'll stop working.
Would there be any explanation there
about the lambda and coma?
Well, like,
the Buddha did refer to a thing called
the Ayusankara,
that upon which life depends,
like vitality.
So sometimes you can be brained
that the body can be almost
completely dysfunctional
but not quite.
And for as long as it's not quite,
there might be still some vitality,
vitality left in the body,
in which case,
people wake up from the coma
or something like that.
But sometimes they just don't.
Well, there is a state of cessation
and perception and feeling,
where breathing stops
in meditation.
You're just the ultimate
form of development of your mind,
whereby, like,
you don't even breathe.
That's it.
The man,
when her ex,
when her husband came to visit her
and she thought he became
sort of one,
and he asked what's the difference
between somebody who is dead
and somebody who is
cessation and perception of feeling.
Instead, the difference is that the one
who is sensation and perception of feeling
still has his life vitality left.
So he returns.
on the level of metaphysics, but yeah, the relationship
between consciousness and body is external.
Conscious is not internal in the body.
And I think the Buddha compared in the suitors
like a gem.
And if there is a thread running clearly through the gem,
that's like conscious body.
But there are completely two different things.
Thread is not part of the gem.
Gem is not part of the thread.
It's entrapped in the gem.
And that's what Yenavira referred to it, actually.
Yeah.
He didn't say that body and consciousness
are superimposed.
He said they're jacks to post.
Means they're completely indifferent to each other.
He's just an occurrence of them coming together,
but not merging together.
They come together.
And as a result of that overlap,
you get Nama Rupa, which you can designate.
So you can ever directly access matter.
Nor can you ever directly access consciousness.
You can abandon matter by fully understanding it.
Sorry.
By fully understanding consciousness,
you remove the footing for the matter.
In other words, you stop misunderstanding
that overlap of conscious body.
But well, it helped me.
And I think it's probably more happened because everybody,
but they fault assumes consciousnesses inside
and everything else is external.
And I did actually remember that I didn't
make much out of it at the time.
But when I was reading existential philosophy
such and they were talking in terms of things
were being, like, not things are conscious
in terms of the dead matter has consciousness in it.
But no, their consciousness is out there with the things,
not in them.
In other words, that's why you have six types of consciousness
because you have six senses.
Every sense, the sun's things are there.
And the only reason it can be sun is because consciousness
is there with those things.
So the conscious matter.
And then if there is ignorance present,
when that contact arises, well, the contact will arise
as a result of you feeling conflicted.
So if you appropriate the contact, then you're contacted.
So contact always pertains to sense of self.
But if you see that thing out there already
a reason the conscious matter means, oh,
you can't do anything about it.
You can't prevent consciousness from disassociating
from the matter if it decides to do that.
Which is, I think what happens when sometimes people
lose their mind and they go cut-atonic.
They go completely like dead motionless.
Nor can you prevent that matter to be destroyed.
You absolutely know.
You can't even conceive having say in it.
It's just beyond your range.
Yet your entire life depends upon it.
So that's the parallel situation.
So if you realize that your consciousness
is as external as this matter that you see
and you have no say in it, then it ceases to be yours.
And then when corresponding engagement occurs,
you see that occurring as a result of things
that you have no say in it.
Therefore, whatever occurs on their account,
you have no say in that either.
It's not yours.
Near this experience, how old is it?
Some people have seen that they are the body either.
Well, I don't know.
Yeah, hard to say really.
It's quite early.
I'm sure something happens, but people use words differently.
They say they saw their body.
But without any ice, how old is it?
Yeah, I see that's the thing.
Some people.
I don't know.
As I say, it's hard to know what people mean
when they describe these things.
Because they might use certain words.
They would mean something for you, something else for them.
So they would say, oh, I saw my body.
You might have well been a thought of their body,
a thought of them abandoning the body.
But because it was a real life and death experience,
that thought was very significant.
It was so real as they would usually describe it.
It was as real as if I was looking at my body over there.
It can be that, or who knows, really.
I mean, when people even try to explain mundane things,
often misunderstanding happens.
Because you realize they're using the same words you know,
but completely differently.
They meant something completely different.
Imagine when you try to explain such personal things
or when people try to talk about spiritual thoughts
or whatever else, and you get all like, well,
you can't make sense out of it.
Because what it means for them doesn't necessarily
mean other things to others.
But that's exactly why the Buddha did
refer to the miracle of teaching.
He said, if a person understood the Dharma,
he's able to convey that to another.
And then they understand it.
That's what that equals a miracle.
Why?
Because the Dharma is so personal, the sense of self,
the senses and everything, that there is no way
that when I say something in regard to senses,
another person will think exactly the same thing,
unless we're both aren't, so something like that.
Because it's so personal that the meaning of it
is so personal.
So it really needs to be, you need to dig through it
and see what it's meant.
That, I think a mother said before, again,
it's like, when I said, you can just take these five aggregates,
poly terms, Rupa, Vedana, Sainas and Karavinyana,
and just take the English words, or Japanese words for them.
And think about it, and see how much we do,
you actually understand.
How do I remember when I was reading the sutras
and then the consciousness?
And you just read all your consciousness.
But then the spot wants to think, well,
OK, forget about it, Pali.
Forget about the sutras.
Just use the word consciousness that I think I know.
What is it?
What, like, when I say consciousness,
what is that that this designation consciousness
stands for in my experience?
What is it?
And then you realize, OK, consciousness is very hard.
Why don't I start with easy matter?
And then you start, and then you realize that's equally hard.
So what is that matter then?
And you realize, if you were to fully understand
these five designations, you would be an adult.
Because there is no difference between intellectual understanding
or real understanding.
Understanding is understanding.
You can start intellectually or non-intellectually,
but understanding that it's the same arrival.
So you might start pondering about it.
And as long as you're not doing, like,
scholastic comparison between the words and the truth,
if you're really trying to see what designation consciousness
stands in your experience, that's when the sutras,
if you read something, they say, think twice.
When they say, first-genre, first-genre, what is first-genre?
Or they say something else, they repeat it twice.
That's basically the way you're bringing it to the mind.
And then to see that, that you just brought to your mind
in your experience, for what it stands for.
Not just kind of an example, it's called an explain it,
or draw the parallel to the drawing or whatever, a scheme.
But they really understand, if consciousness, consciousness,
that I just said, what is that, what I said?
What is it that this saying stands for?
What is that?
What did I just designate in my experience
when I said feeling?
What is feeling now that I said it?
And the fact that you said feeling means it stands for something.
It designates something.
So you really have to push as hard as far as you need to
until same feeling stands for that which feeling really is,
not for your idea of what feeling is,
or for your misunderstanding of what feeling is.
And you can see how many people have not understood this
by seeing how many people cannot distinguish between what they perceive
and what they feel, or what they intend.
And it's all like a jungle, just everything and everything.
Is it that I remember that you sent me
that I can know some meditation something,
you are a disciple, the Lord, the Lord, the Lord, the Lord.
No, that was Dukka, on Dukka.
It was written that the difference,
the perception, the difference between the Dara and the Puduceno
is the Arahat and when you see the chair, he doesn't think it is his.
But Puduceno thinks it is his chair.
Only that is a difference, is it true?
Well, it's slightly subtler than that.
He might not think that's my chair,
because if it's his chair, I won't think it's my chair.
But I can think that chair is for me to sit on.
For me?
Yeah.
Not in the market.
It's for me to sit on.
Like the chair, the significance of the chair, is for sitting.
It's to be sat on.
And that doesn't necessarily mean sense of self.
But when somebody who holds sense of self and self,
you approaches it, he will inevitably take it like that.
So when a Puduceno sees a chair or any other sign,
a cup to drink water from, it will be a cup is for my eye
to drink water from.
It's for me to drink water from.
The chair is for me to sit on.
And that's already a sense of self.
For me?
The Puduceno sees the opposite, the river.
Oh, what's happening?
I never think that it's my river.
That's fine.
But as I said, seeing the river outside,
it's only a particular object within the general situation
that you're in.
And yourself is on the general level.
You'll never see your sense of self on the level
where you're seeing.
Your sense of self is in that peripheral situation
that determines everything particular that's
right in front of you.
That's why people never can ever understand an atom
and they go about.
And, oh, that's not real.
That doesn't exist.
See, it's so constantly changing.
I just destroyed it.
It means it's impermanent.
Those are all objects of your senses.
And your sense of self is way deeper than that.
It's on the level of that situation I was telling you about.
Yeah.
Oh, yeah.
So you are standing here from which position
you can see the river out there.
That's already something you perceive as one thing.
That's one thing.
Very general thing.
And your sense of self is on that level.
And that's where it has to be understood.
So if you look at the river out there
and start looking at your sense of self there,
then you already forgot half of the image.
What does it mean that you said that because of sense of self,
I think that there is a front contact feeling, right?
The next perception reason, next method formation.
I see this process because of sense of self.
What does it mean?
Otherwise, it doesn't think for contact.
Well, that process, as I said before,
it's not really a process like that.
It's all simultaneous.
So you can't think one, two, three, four, five,
occurring one after the other.
When ignorance, there is contact.
When ignorance, contact.
That's all you can say.
If the contact is manifest,
means ignorance is present there, right there and there.
For as long as contact is being manifested.
Contact, you mean that the...
Meaning being touched by things.
Before and they have contact.
No, they don't have ignorance.
So there is nothing to be contacted.
Contact about what do you mean by contact?
Being touched.
Means having...
Expaling your objects in the sense of the...
No, not necessarily, no.
Not necessarily.
As you see, you can be very indifferent to the external objects.
Care about the flask, I can care about the river.
I can care about anything.
But you can still be able to do that.
Yeah, aren't they have experience?
Well, no, I don't, they haven't done everything properly
on the level of that situation.
In other words, if you are not,
if there is no sense of self
on the most general level
of Michael sitting in a cave with him,
leaning on the cushion, talking about it down,
that's one experience, very general.
And you can define it as far as you want.
It still remains one experience
as a whole, general.
If you abandon that,
then whatever comes in front of you,
particularly,
pleasing with this pleasing,
or neutral, or extremely pleasing,
or extremely pleasing, or neutral,
you won't be moved by it, why?
Because you abandon its foundations.
And the foundations is the situation as a whole.
But if you keep chasing after particular objects,
you're not seeing the bigger picture,
and that's where the problem is.
I abandon you now, or what do you mean by that?
Full understanding, not regarding his ears.
OK, let's try it this.
Michael, in the cave, it's not easy.
It's not easy to understand.
So you don't have to, yeah, you don't have to worry about it.
Well, maybe a little bit,
because it can keep you going, but
Michael, in the cave,
living in a cushion, talking about the dharma.
That's a thought,
but not just a thought.
That's a thought that stands for your actual experience right now,
which means it's a very general experience,
very real as such.
And that's your situation,
and you can stop there now,
because that situation remains unchanged.
Whether we talk quickly, or slowly,
or stop talking for a moment,
it's still Michael in the cave,
living in a cushion, talking about the dharma.
So in that sense, it's independent of the particular.
So even if you move the cushion,
if you're not living on the cushion,
it's still generally Michael in the cave.
Within Michael sitting in the cave,
she leans on the cushion, sits on the floor,
and then within that, she talks the dharma.
She might stop talking about dharma,
she's still living on the cushion,
sitting on the floor in the cave.
She might stand up, stop leaning on the cushion.
She's still in the cave.
So that's how it's hierarchically ordered.
So you don't have to understand all of it.
You can take one of those levels,
which is the body posture.
I'm being seated right now.
That's a general thought that stands for your actual body posture.
And you can establish your mindfulness upon that.
Now see, the thing is,
Michael in the cave sitting in the floor talking dharma
is the fundamental situation you're in.
But if you look at it,
would it be possible for you to sit in this cave
that you can see now,
if there is no cave here,
or if somebody destroys it?
Would it be possible for you to sit on the floor
or lean on the cushion if I take the cushion?
It wouldn't.
So you realize that these objects of your senses,
things you can actually see and hear and touch,
in that indirect manner, not directly,
like this is not mine, this is not mine.
But in that indirect manner,
they indicate that that situation as a whole,
the general mindful picture, is not independent.
It depends upon these very particular objects.
Because if they're removed,
at any point,
this general situation cannot remain standing.
And the utmost general situation is your body.
The whole world is within your body.
And if your body is removed,
your whole world goes.
It's the same principle.
So if the body goes,
the one you can see,
you can see in the mirror,
like you can see in others.
If that's taken,
none of the general situation,
none of the most lofty feelings or thoughts
can remain standing.
So that's the relationship
with peripheral and actual understanding
about the needs to be understood.
Because that's how it works.
If you forget about the peripheral,
general,
you just end up chasing these particular objects.
But you're not seeing them correctly.
You don't see them as mutually determined
in the general situation.
You just see them in a very linear manner,
which is on the level of science,
scholastics,
or I don't know,
medicine,
any form of like natural psychology,
all of that is just linear observation.
But it doesn't reveal the timeless principle
of mutual dependence.
But it's no better.
Because for as long as the case is present,
your situation of being in the cave
can be maintained.
But then vice versa.
If there was no intention for you
to be in the cave in the first place,
this particular cave you see,
you wouldn't have come here,
therefore you wouldn't have seen it.
So as much as the particular things,
determine your general situation,
general situation defines the particular things.
So in terms of the practice of mindfulness,
works along those levels.
If you have a thought,
no matter how distant,
but even a little bit present,
in the back of your mind,
that you are in this cave.
If that's established as an anchor,
what I said before,
whatever you do,
while you are in the cave,
you'll be mindful of that.
Without having to trace
every particular thing you do
while you are in the cave.
Or you can anchor yourself in
being seated on the floor.
Whatever you do,
whatever you think,
whatever you say,
while you remain seated on the floor,
if you are established upon the thought
of being seated on the floor,
you'll be mindful of whatever you do.
Because mindfulness is about
not chasing these particular things,
but being established in regard to them.
And it's already seen as dependent.
Well, you don't have to like
strain yourself in terms of always seeing it
because it's already there.
You just have to remember
and step back into it.
Because your situation of sitting on the floor
in the cave is already there
and it's still there.
And even if you stop thinking about it,
it's still there.
Because the body is still in that situation.
That's why you can reestablish mindfulness.
And the more skilled you become,
the quicker you reestablish it.
The more skilled you become
in recognizing the things
that you can use to establish your mindfulness on.
And that's a very different
type of practice than what you get.
The Bermis retreat centers,
when you're all about focusing and staring
and observing and trying to catch
the particular moment.
That's as mindful as you can get.
And you end up forcing yourself into that,
more and more,
which is why all those people
get very intense.
Yeah.
So, it means that you don't need to worry so much
and what's feeling or what's the perception or what is the feeling.
Well, that's the thing.
Like, you can if you choose that as an approach,
but you don't have to understand everything
at once all the time.
You need to develop mindfulness
to the extent necessary
when understanding is developed
to a sufficient degree where
you don't take things to be yours anymore.
It doesn't mean that you actually have to go around destroying things
or giving things up.
I octane this because it's not mine.
It wasn't you able to begin with.
So, how can you even give it away?
So, and again, you can be mindful in regard
to any of the feeling, perception or intentions
through this form of mindfulness.
So, if you're mindful,
sitting of your situation and your body posture,
and then feeling arises
while you're seated in the cave.
It's your mindful in regard to that.
Oh, you can choose feeling to be
the anchor of your mindfulness.
You say, I'm feeling this way now.
While I feel like that through that,
I'm feeling this, through that, I'm feeling that.
And that's why in Anapurna Satisood
the Buddha said, when he was talking about
the development of mindfulness, he said,
while breathing in like this,
I feel like that.
While breathing in like that,
I'll observe my whole body.
While breathing in, breathing out,
breathing in, breathing both,
I will experience my body in this way.
I will feel this.
I will feel pleasure.
So, you actually do it rightly.
By doing it rightly,
you end up recognizing it rightly.
And that's why it brings the
force of the pathanas to complete
fulfillment in regard to body,
in regard to feeling, in regard to thoughts,
in regard to mind, in regard to mind,
in regard to thoughts.
So, you can do it actively,
you can do it passively.
Like while I'm seated right here,
breathing, I'm going to be thinking this.
Oh, while I'm seated here breathing,
these thoughts are arising.
That's passive.
You know they're actually actively thinking,
but you're just recognizing what your mind does.
I was practicing this as a director,
whatever I think the mind,
any kind of thought.
Any kind of thought.
Just see the...
Not mind means it for everything is appearing on their own standards.
Yeah, but the thing is,
you have to know what not mind is,
in order to be able to see particular things
as they arise, as not mind.
So, first the right view needs to be developed,
in order to be applied.
So, when I said that,
the nobody's argument should be contemplating,
this is not mind, not for me, not I am.
Not myself, and you should...
That requires the right view.
You won't work otherwise.
Everything is appearing on their own.
Is it not in the...
Well, it is, but the thing is,
when you're like,
whatever arises,
and then you regard it as not mind,
it's almost like a form of management for a pathogen.
You need to think to arise first,
and then you can...
Oh, this is not mind.
But actually,
you don't want to think to arise as yours to begin with.
You don't want to have to do anything.
That's what freedom means.
That's what I don't lay down his burden,
done his work,
in every conceivable regard.
There is no shoot for him anymore, in any way.
So if your practice is about doing things when this arises,
that requires that thing to keep arising.
So you want to start focusing on your practice,
taking you to a place whereby
arising things won't require you to do anything anymore.
In other words,
when they will not arise as yourself,
because the only reason you can...
Well, the only reason you have to
be saying to whatever arises,
this is not mind,
is because you first took his yours,
and then you say it's not mind.
So you want to stop taking it as yours,
and then you can stop saying it's not mind.
Because now it's true, it's not mind.
And again,
that's the difference between this general peripheral situation
you're in,
while you're looking at these particular things.
Do you take things as yours on this general level?
Well, that's what a sense of self is.
So then trying to address the particular things
that arise at you,
as not me, not mind,
actually leaves.
If you don't see the connection
between the particular,
determining the general,
and general defining the particular in return,
your application of not mind, not me,
won't work, just doesn't apply to anything.
But if you see that,
if I regard these particular things as not belonging to me,
while I see those particular things determining
this sense of me,
well, that's a different story then.
But that can only be done if you're fully aware
of the situation as it has a reason,
if the mindfulness is developed
in a sufficient extent,
to be aware of the situation
while the particular things are coming and going.
And then it can work.
Something that the mindfulness of body
or whatever,
something gets lost.
Like, it happens even for earlier.
It's just because you put it generally.
It happens.
Well, like,
for earlier, less and less,
and for an other hand,
forgetting things,
forgetting particular things,
does not induce ignorance anymore.
So when you forget something,
then you remember it.
There was no ignorance induced in you,
forgetting.
No sense of self-induced,
no appropriation induced,
no pedan induced.
For putugina, that's not the case.
When putugina forgets,
his habits,
when he's in the state of forgetfulness,
are habits of putugina,
are habits that maintain a Vija
and everything else.
So that's why,
that you cannot possibly be
100% mindful all the time.
It doesn't work like that.
What you want to do is try to be mindful
as much as you can,
and while you're mindful,
understand the things.
And then when you forget,
like when Adahans,
or even Adahs,
when they were,
when they were around
I was still a sort of runner, and when Sari put a diet, he was very shaken, he was very
effective, but he said, everything went black, and the clouds were dark, and I couldn't
... 20 years I've been serving the Lord and listening to the devil and I couldn't remember
a single thing.
But it doesn't mean that he stopped being a sort of runner.
Means when whatever the pressing circumstances were gone, things were back to normal or
earlier.
When the sense of self is, when you are reflecting, when you are thinking, whether
mindfully or not, there is an implication of me, that's the sense of self.
And that's what I meant.
When he might be forgetful in regard to things, that doesn't imply a sense of self anymore,
because self and the whole appropriation thing is not in the things, it's in a relationship
with the things, which means there is always a degree of awareness in that.
So forgetfulness is in regard to particular things, but forgetfulness as an experience is
something you can be mindful of, it's present, and it's something you don't have to forget.
And on that level is the level where the sense of self arises.
So that's why even when the act of forgetting does not adhere to the ignorance of the sense
of self anymore, that's when you know that mindfulness is being developed.
And you can afford to forget particular things, but obviously you forget less and less
of the nature of things, and generally you remember what better if the mindfulness is
developed, because that's how memory works.
And as I said, if you remember, if you remember that you are here in this cave, if you don't
forget that, whatever you're doing on account that you've been in the cave, you can be mindful
in regard to that.
Then you forget that you're in the cave, but the things you're still in the cave, then
you can remember that you're in the cave, and you're establishing mindfulness, obviously
a situation.
But I don't mean that now you just have to keep thinking I'm in the cave, I'm in the
cave.
Now the point of mindfulness is to recognize this relationship between peripheral and
actual, between general and particular.
So you're mindful in the cave, that's it.
Now through that mindfulness, while you're in the cave, do things.
Talk, sit, walk, whatever, well, you will be doing inevitably something, even if it's
nothing, I'm just sitting, well, that's something you're doing while you're in the cave.
And that's mindfulness.
And that's how the memory works, and if you read the sutras, that's why they always,
when whoever would be related to the sutra, well, when they were on under the sutras, they
said, that's a habit.
On one occasion, the Lord was staying in this province.
While he was staying in that occasion, in this province, he visited this forest.
While he was staying in that province, visited this forest, he was sitting under the root
of tree.
While he was in the province, in that forest, under the root of the tree, these people came
to visit.
So it's situation within, situation within, situation within, situation within, situation
within, and that's infinite.
There's none to it.
You can go as particular as you can observe, and as general as you can hold.
The point is not to kind of find the beginning with the end of it.
The point is to fully understand the relationship between more general and then more particular,
because that's how mindfulness is established.
So you don't have to necessarily start, oh, I mean, this province, in this forest, under
this tree, you can just start with the body posture, because it would be implied.
Well, you can just, while I'm under the root, while I'm under this tree, under the
root of the tree, these people came to visit.
While I'm still seated, under the root of this tree, we were talking about this.
While I'm seated, under the tree, and we were talking about this, they asked me this
particular question.
Within that question, I gave this particular answer, and you end up remembering the whole
thing, as opposed to linearly trying to list and just hold everything in mind at the same
time.
It doesn't work like that.
And that's how sometimes there is a, like, the establishment of mind in the suitors
when they would have said the monk goes off and lives in the forest, and then he observes
while in this forest, any perceptions and feelings, disturbances, based on the perceptions
of the village, cannot arise, because I'm in the forest.
So then he sets his mind like that, establishes it upon the perceptions of the forest.
So in the morning, when he goes to the village, he might see unsuitable sites, hear unsuitable
things, things they will provoke last, diversion and delusion, but because his mind is established
upon perception of the forest, none of these things can touch him.
They cannot disturb him.
And then he reflects further, he says, because I'm established upon the more refined perception
of the forest, perceptions of the village cannot disturb me.
Any disturbance in the rise will be on account of perceptions of the forest, because that's
what the mind is.
And he can go further, he can establish his mind upon the perception of the earth as
general as it is, element of earth.
And now, not even perceptions of the particular forest can bother him any more, let alone
the village.
So that's like the contemplation of the four elements, that's how it works.
More general, the most general is earth, water, fire and air.
It doesn't get more general than that.
Yet, as subtle as it is, the mind can get established.
And the Buddha said, I'll be like earth, or be like fire, when you contemplate the nature
of the earth, you get established through the mindfulness of the earth.
You don't even say element of earth, because a lot of people are in the implies of
you, element.
You just say earth, designation of earth, stands for solidity, stands for heart, stands
for earth, and that's it.
You establish the mind, and that's the meditation of casinos, that's exactly that.
Not nothing to do with what people do, exert color discs and stuff like that, they're
just from serious misunderstanding.
And then the ultimate casina, the ultimate establishment, is the establishment upon the
casina of consciousness.
So in the same sense that you establish upon the perceptions of the forest and established
upon earth, and so on, you can get established upon consciousness.
Why? Because if you establish upon the nature of presence, in regard to that which is
present, then whatever is present cannot disturb you.
Because you're established in regard to the nature of presence of that which is present.
So you cannot disturb you.
And literally whatever you experience is present, which means whatever you experience
cannot disturb you anyway.
And the Buddha said that the ultimate, that's the supreme, the most refined casina you
can get established.
But you don't need to go that far, even the first element of earth is enough to abandon
everything inferior to it, as the Buddha will refer to it, which is everything.
Because again, whatever arises in your experience has a degree, has an element of solidity in
it, has an element of earth present, a phenomenon of earth present.
If you establish upon that, you're surmounted everything that has that, and everything
has that, which means you're surmounted everything.
In my case, in my medicine station, now practice what I'm doing, it's all those things
are also with different things, like in my case, when you have thoughts coming up, or
bubbles as you refer to it, whatever it's different perceptions, try not to forget about
the general situation you're in.
The fact that you're sitting in your room, on the floor, or on the chair, that's already
the situation, seated in such and such situation.
That's a general thought, that's one experience.
Within that, and while you are in that position and that thought, whatever you're thinking
of, whatever you're feeling, whatever you're hearing, whatever you're seeing, you can
be mindful of that, from that perspective.
But if you forget about the general situation, then you'll end up chasing every particular
thought or perception of earth, and that's a problem, that there is no mindfulness there,
no rather very little mindfulness, not established.
So, in that case, I was thinking that the need to see all the bubbles, this is not mine,
and that these bubbles are calling it as I am, and the same view and the dependent relation
I have to think of.
Now we'll see the problem with that is I am seeing all of this, which means your general
sense of why it remains unaffected.
You have to reverse that, you have to start indirectly, whereby you see yourself first
in this situation, while you're in that situation, whatever is in front of you, you start
being mindful of that.
When that mindfulness is established enough, it becomes apparent then, like you don't
see it, you don't invent it, you just discern it as already there.
And what is already there is that, as I said before, the general situation during defines
these particular bubbles and thoughts and perceptions, but they are the ones enabling the
general situation to be such in the first place.
So you recognize that relationship with the dependence between this general and particular
level, out there, not me and I am doing it, not in front of me, not for me, it's just
there, because you are there sitting in the room, while you are there sitting in the room,
you are thinking certain things, while you are sitting in the room on your chair, looking
through the window, you are thinking certain things.
Would you be thinking those things, if you are not in that room sitting in that chair looking
through the window, you might well not be thinking that.
So your general situation determines, defines these certain things, defines significance
of those things, thought in that situation.
But then again, if you are not thinking in your room on your chair, like if there was
no chair, there was no room, no window, you are not thinking, would you be able to have
a situation of me sitting on the chair looking through the window thinking these things?
You couldn't.
So that's how they depend on each other, and none of it can be yours for that very reason.
Does mindfulness on body mean that not only the body, the situation on the ground?
Yeah, mindfulness on the body means mindfulness on the situation, the body is in.
Not the actual physical posture, and observing of like, oh, this is how my knee feels and
this is probably something, that's all already because you are in that situation, you can
look at those particular things.
And you can, if you want, while you are seated on the floor in a certain posture, if you
start looking particular aspects of your body, your hands, your knees, your feet, your
head, again, you can do it rightly, you can do it wrongly.
If you do it rightly, you see those particular components being defined by the fact that
the body is generally already there, but at the same time, without those particular components,
that body couldn't have not there is any such in the first place.
It's the same principle.
But if you just go at the components, forget about the whole picture, and just as this
is not mine, this is not mine, nothing will change really.
Before I was missing the point, if I was thinking this body, this body, or what is this body
doing?
It's not that important thing, just I only have to keep seeing the feelings arise, as
I thought, as a bubble in the mind, and just need to keep knowing that everything is
appearing on their own, so situation works so well, but anyway, feelings are rising,
wherever I am.
Yeah, again, you can do that, but even then, you need a reference point in regard to what
you're looking at.
So, you might not want to be mindful of the body, that's fine, if you want to be mindful
of the feelings, you need a reference point in regard to that.
In other words, there is always a situation that you have to be mindful of, there is always
more general and more particular, that's needed for mindfulness to be established.
You can't just be staring at the particular and being mindful, I am mindful, or rather
that mindfulness is not really established mindfulness.
So, if you're mindful of your feelings arising, again, you can be anchored, established in
your situation, in terms of bodily posture, while I'm walking fear arose, while I'm walking
fear is present, while I'm walking fear is present, while I'm walking fear is ceasing,
while I'm walking fear is gone, as opposed to I'm afraid, I'm not afraid.
Oh, it's like the most subtle, you can get established in terms of mind object, thought,
dhamma.
That's another satipatana, whereby I'm feeling this on account of this memory, or on
account of what somebody said, or on account of something I've seen.
For as long as that reason, I've seen something unpleasant, I feel bad.
For as long as this unpleasant thing is present, bad feeling endures.
I'm pleasant feeling, unpleasant thing ceases, bad feeling is gone.
So, you see the feeling coming from that thing.
Not from you, belonging to that thing, not to you.
And again, you can see the fear belonging to the body in the situation, not to me, I'm
afraid.
Because of the situation.
Yeah.
And that's how you abandon both, situation, and the particular thing that has a reason.
Not because of me.
Because if it comes from me, me will never be abandoned.
So, it's important to see that the relation, is it not enough support if I total forgot
about the situation with this body?
You can't forget about it.
You can ignore it, but it's already there.
In the meditation support if I just keep seeing the bubbles arising in the circle.
And just, whatever arises, everything actually arising on their own.
The only reason particular things that arise, can arise, is from the perspective of a more
general situation that it's already there.
In other words, the movement of arising and ceasing is impossible if there is no static
point in regard to it.
That's just the nature of things.
If everything is moving, there's no movement.
But the fact that you discern bubbles coming and going means there is a point that is
still in regard to that.
And that point is your situation.
That is more general than those particular changing bubbles.
So, you cannot, but not have it.
You can only ignore it.
And that's not good.
Does that know that they can't go through a less tanky mildly or somewhat like that?
No, there's a part, yeah, yeah, well, with that, there is only doing meditation also.
Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah, the whole thing, it's not like the A4 part and the A8 components
they need to be developed.
But it's not one, and then you develop two, and then you develop, in some of it is Sutta.
The Sutta they talk about, the main Sutta, Majemika 9, he says that, with every of those
factors, it's governed by the first factor of the right view.
So knowing things rightly, it's too fast to go through, yeah, yeah, yeah, let's get
you to see.
No, sorry.
No, it's fine.
What's right?
Knowing things rightly, would make your meditation right, would make your reading the
Sutta's right, would make your actions right, your seal of right, everything will become
right if you know that it's right.
So that's how it's done.
So the thing is, people misunderstand meditation as a separate thing from contemplating the
dharma, but it's not.
One like meditation brings contemplation, contemplation brings meditation.
So if your meditation is not making any difference to your contemplation, that's a wrong meditation.
And he said it's like two yokes pulling each other, and the two yokes, if one goes forward
what the other one will have, because they're connected.
So if you're putting forward some of that, the person that will be there, it's not like
I'll do some of that here, then I'll go the other way and do a bit of a person there.
No, if you don't be a person, your meditation is coming with it, you can't even conceive
being separate.
And if you read the Sutta's meditation, like Kanapana Sati, it's all this practice of
this mindfulness.
And you got to more generally like, while I'm reading, I will feel this, while I'm reading
I'll think that.
So being skilled in recognizing situation, you're inevitably, you can't even conceive
not being in situation, because if you think I'm not in a situation, that is your situation.
And then you don't even have to constantly think about your situation, but in your daily
life, the fact that there are particular things, like, oh, I need to sweep this floor now
and clean this up.
It's only possible, because the floor in the cave and all the significance of the whole
thing is already present in my situation, and then I can attempt to these particular things.
I can't fool with the situation, or what does it mean?
No, you can forget it, but you can't escape it, you forget it when you're not mindful.
You ignore it, then you get caught up in particular things, and then you suffer more on the
particular things, or you get elated more on a kind of particular things.
In either way, you get moved much more by the particular things, you suffer.
It's probably, I don't know, very new for you to hear this, but even if it's not, it's
not something.
It's not something you can just hear somebody say once, and then you are.
You can get the idea, but you have to keep doing it, and like the nature of intention
works the same, like, because you had intention to come here today to see me and talk about
the Dunlain, that's a very general intention you had.
While that intention was still present, you went and hired a tuk-tuk, there was a more
particular intention, calling the driver, telling him to come, giving him the time.
Walking to the tuk-tuk, sitting in the tuk-tuk, being in the tuk-tuk, coming here, walking,
finding the place, getting lost, realizing that you were lost, finding the right way.
All of those particular intentions were within the intention of you wanting to be here,
talk tuk-tuk.
If that general intention, you wanting to be here, tuk-tuk, disappears, but if you suddenly
change your mind on the way here, ooh, I can't go there today, that's it.
You go back.
All of those particular intentions then lose their general, like, a significant direction.
You change your mind, suddenly I called and said I had to go to a hospital or something
like that.
If the general intention of you wanting to be here, changes, whether through you or through
the circumstances, all of the particular intentions, then go.
I cannot go there, therefore, why would you be calling a tuk-tuk, telling him to bring
you here?
No.
If you're about to make a phone call to call a driver, but then you find out if you
can't come, you're not going to be doing this particular.
So that's how you can be mindful of all of those particular intentions by knowing what
the general intention in regard to them.
And obviously, there is no end to generality, nor there is an end to particularity.
But that's not important.
You won't have to reach the end or the first point, because there won't be any.
The whole point is to understand that relationship.
So if, sometimes, you had an intention to come here, but then your mindfulness is not
established upon that intention.
Well, then you can establish your mindfulness upon even more general intention of intention
of you wanting to understand the dharma.
As a result of you wanting to understand the dharma, you want to come here particularly
and talk about the dharma.
As a result of you wanting to understand the dharma, you want to come here and talk the
dharma.
You want to call the talk to driver and tell him to come at certain time and bring you
here.
As a result of all of that, you will sit in the talk to for two and a half hours.
As a result of that, you will be excellent and so on and so forth.
So you can pick any of those things as long as you're mindful in regard to particular.
Now just chase the particular or get lost in the general.
It's the relationship that's important.
And that relationship is Sankara, Sankata dharma.
The whole experience is dual in that sense.
Everything.
Everything experience falls into that.
That's when you recall the fundamental structure.
It's the structure of the experience, the structure of the aggregates.
And the Buddha said, even if somebody is remembering one previous life, five previous
lives, five hundred previous lives, all they're remembering is these five or one among
them.
These five aggregates are one among them.
Nothing.
Nothing out of that.
It's all within.
All within the same structure.
The intention of this choosing, these things actually are really confusing because they
have a sense of self, really, really, really, in intention.
Yeah.
The closest, closest relation, like intention is that with the sense of service, but again,
if you start looking in terms of the situation, the only reason you can intend to drink that
glass of water is because it's already there in your situation.
So the particular intention, well, exactly, you can choose what's already given.
If you haven't been given and displayed through your senses, you can't even conceive it,
let alone intend it.
But if you're just looking and focusing on the particular, then your intention will
always feel very direct, always feel me and Aliya.
Well, yeah, I want to drink water, but the only reason I can drink water is because there
is water here, drinkable water, and there is a little, and then you realize, even this
whole sense of I want to do this is actually determined by that general situation, because
if that thing changes, no matter how strong my sense of self is, if there is no water
to drink it here, that intention will not make sense, and I might have to go somewhere
else.
That's totally up here, you know, I don't know, I think it is.
Now, if you start looking through a situation, the relationship becomes more and more apparent,
the relationship that is mutually determining and kind of not requiring your sense of self
at all.
So the more you are aware of it, the more you discern it, less of it is yours.
Externally, not much can change, not much needs to change, obviously, virtuous behavior
and so on, but that's it.