So how's your meditation going?
I got a couple of emails about the thoughts.
Yeah, yeah.
It's very, I'll show you what it's contemplative.
The thing is, actually before meeting you,
or other Saturdays, or it's told me that it's very important to reduce the time of thinking.
Yeah, I got myself many times for people.
Yeah, yeah.
But I understand actually what you explain,
because if I try to control something,
it means, actually, based on something, I need to control,
based on self-view, actually, because of that,
and I try to control it.
So maybe that is...
I understand it, but...
The only thing with that is,
for as long as you don't think that everything is in your head,
so to speak, you know, at some of the speed,
because they are, it's all in my head.
It's not, it's real.
Anything that appears, through any of the senses,
it appears as a phenomenon,
which means, from that point of view, it is mental.
It pertains to the mind.
So even things that you see, objects around you,
again, they're real where they are,
and they are material, but you know them for what they are,
you perceive them for what they are,
all of that has this founding mental aspect.
So obviously, you have things that are more mental,
so to speak, like when you think about your thoughts,
about your past, future, some,
and then you have the immediate experience of the things
that you're seeing, hearing, touching, tasting.
None of those things would be known,
if that's already not a form of thought,
which is why all of the five senses,
they meet in the mind, which acts as a six,
in that regard.
So I just wanted to clarify that,
because sometimes people get,
oh, it's all in my head, it's all my thoughts,
and then they use that to dismiss
real things around them.
Oh, it's not real, because just in my thought,
well, your thoughts are very real.
And things here, things here,
things in between, that's all very real.
It's just a thinking on that properly,
could help people overcome the assumption
of the external world,
exists, and then I am in it,
and then I can think in regard to it.
But the fact that you can even designate
the external world,
in, well, whichever designation you choose,
the fact that you can do that means
it's already perceived, somehow,
and as such, it's actually a thought.
It's a dharma, like a phenomenon,
which means it's not really an external then.
It's external aspect,
it's only relative to something which is
maybe less external,
but fundamental, there is no external world that you,
that it's independent of you,
because in that case, you wouldn't be even conceiving it,
you couldn't.
Is it that before I remember,
if I see the tree,
my consciousness is out there?
Well, that's definitely, like, see,
the tree outside is real,
when you look at it, and it's there.
But again, the designation there,
the designation tree,
all of that, it's already perceived
on the level of the mind, and that's what the consciousness is.
So in that sense, you can say, yes,
it's more correct to say the consciousness
is with that matter of that tree
than in your head,
that's just a result of it.
Is it important that some people
they say that,
suppose, if I keep thinking,
it's about the tree or something,
but actually, your teaching is actually,
with maintaining the mind
for the supplement,
maintaining the mind for this on the body,
for the posture, something,
why are we mindful of the body itself?
And then, I should be mindful of the other thing.
It's quite an opposite.
Difficult assumption.
Attention, use your stays on one object.
Well, the attention usually goes after something.
So the point is to learn how to be mindful of the experience
as a whole, all of it.
No matter what particular things you're attending,
whether it's a tree,
or it's a cup, or it's whatever,
that's all particular,
but you want to remain mindful on the general level
of the experience as a whole,
which is why I would refer to it as a mindful of the background,
mindful of the peripheral.
Because it's not what you're attending,
it's the negative in regard to that.
Well, it's the background of that thing
that you're fully attending right now.
And because it is still present,
in a form of a background,
you can say it's slightly less present
than the thing that you're fully attending.
But it's still present.
So mindfulness means training your mind
to recognize the degree of the presence of that background,
and not interfere with it.
So you get established upon it.
And then you remain mindful of the background,
no matter what particular things
that are rising and how powerful they are,
or they might be.
It means why reading the book or something,
you are always aware of.
Okay, you look harder when you read the book,
because reading a book means reading the ideas,
the thoughts,
you have to think about it.
So it requires more of your attention.
So if you read the book,
yeah, okay, read the book.
Focus on what you're reading in the book.
But it's more like,
if you're doing things that are not necessarily
requiring 100% of your attention,
sweeping the leaves,
washing the dishes, or whatever,
you can be mindful of your experience
in regard to what you're doing right there and then.
So writing a complex letter
would require most of your attention to it.
Still, you can be mindful in regard to that,
but you don't have to worry about too much.
Like, oh, I lost my mindfulness.
I think, well, you didn't really.
You just diverter your attention more
to the thing that you willingly mind
from it decided to do beforehand.
So then that's absolutely fine.
It's not like if you're passing
that which is actually impossible,
that you can maintain constant sort of awareness
of the present or it's a contradiction in terms.
It doesn't work like that.
Because even that idea of the constant present moment
has a reason on the background
that you're completely not seeing.
And then you're just expecting everything
to exist to the same degree right in front of you.
And when it doesn't, oh, I lost my mindfulness.
I wasn't the mindfulness to begin with.
How do you understand the word
of attachment?
How do you explain the word of attachment?
Well, I am super-dana.
I translate it as assumption.
How do you...
Is it something like a usually people's
speaker or something dangerous?
But attachment means something
thinking about something.
Well, it's a bit more subtle.
It's subtle than that.
You're attached to things
when you take them to be yours.
No.
Even that background I'm talking about,
like the background that appears
like the less your experience as a whole,
that's already what you've taken to be yours.
The basis for your everyday experience,
which is the experience of your senses
in regard to the world,
your eye, your ear, your nose,
that's already taken as mine.
So even if things are right in front of you,
you're not necessarily yours.
Oh, like, I don't know,
this torch that I'm holding is not mine.
Well, all of the senses that I'm using
to experience are being helped by me,
which means in that way,
in that experience of that torch,
which is in mundane levels, not mine,
it's still mine,
because I took it through the senses.
And then always the things that
yours, even on a mundane level,
they're even more yours.
But if you undermine that,
if you recognize that you can't actually own
the senses to begin with,
it's impossible.
Not knowing that you can't own it,
you take up the ownership.
You find out that you can't own it,
you don't own it.
So it's mutually exclusive,
it's either or you either own it
or you don't.
So you want to not own it,
and you can do that only by fully understanding
that you could not have owned them,
in other ways.
And that means whatever,
then you experience an account of those senses,
you can't even conceive that to be yours,
or to imply your sense of self,
or to be for you, or anything like that.
In the case of Arya,
Arya, that they have,
they don't have,
they have some attachments still,
but they don't have any save of you.
What kind of attachment is it?
Well, it's,
well, as the similar in the synthesis,
like, imagine there is a poisonous arrow
stuck in your flesh,
that's sort of still oozing poison,
still making the whole wound,
in fact, in the sun.
So the first thing is to take that arrow,
take out that source of poison.
So when you take that out,
you can say, okay,
I'm further poisoning of the wound.
The source is taken out,
but it will still take some time,
until the poison that is still inside,
kind of,
evaporates, this disappears,
until the wound heals.
So that's basically what a sacred is.
Somebody who has taken out,
that poison is dead,
or ignorance,
but it will take some time now,
depending on how hard he applies himself,
how carefully he attends to his wound.
It might not take long,
but it might take longer,
if he is not dead careful.
But either way, there is no more doubt,
there is no more poison coming in,
which means sooner or later it will heal.
It will clear itself out.
So are you,
when they see something,
he never thinks,
that's his,
but he has no identification,
basically.
Well, it depends, really.
There is a, like,
for someone, he is free from the self-view,
which means
he still possesses a degree of,
let's say, attachment
in regard to things around him and so on.
But overall,
he can never, ever again,
assume that his sense of self
exists independently of his own experience,
which is usually what Buttigiegna thinks.
Not even so clearly,
but the assumption is that
your self is independent of your five aggregates.
It's independent of your body,
if you mind, it's independent of everything.
It's permanent.
Well, that view is completely gone
for a sort of one,
which means he can't even conceive that anymore.
He knows that whatever it is there,
he has a reason and such,
it will come to cease.
Even if it's his current sense of self,
that he's still not quite extinguished,
his conceit and so on,
he knows, even that,
there is a permanent,
and he won't stay forever,
which means he does not take even that
as ultimate, as eternal.
But it will take time
until that,
one more particular level
these things clear themselves out.
And if he makes the better quality effort,
more effort,
he will get there quicker.
What do you think is independentism?
Dependent organization?
No, that's completely not even seen.
If you ask an everyday person
about the sense of self or whatever,
nobody will doubt that they are.
I am.
Most of them probably won't be able to tell you what they are,
but the sense of self is undeniable.
And the degree that they have taken
that undeniable sense of self for granted,
makes it almost feel as if it's completely independent
of anything you're experiencing,
whether feeling perception intentions
it just feels entirely
myself is kind of myself.
It's the same self.
And that is a standard out of one,
that is a view where you think
that your sense of self exists independently
of your mind, of phenomena, of your experience,
of things that are rising in positive,
just don't even see the connection between the two.
So recognizing connection,
recognizing that no matter what sense of self,
no matter how ambiguous,
how well-established, how undeniable it is,
it's still a thing that you can talk about,
which means it exists as such.
It exists as an ambiguous,
undeniable vague peripheral general sense of self,
but it's real as such,
and you start recognizing it on that level,
which means you start recognizing it for what it is.
And when you see that it's just another reason thing,
like other reason things,
it slowly becomes apparent that,
yeah, that too is subject to impermanence
and because it's subject to impermanence,
it cannot possibly be my eternal self.
I think actually very contemplate on this too.
Actually, I think this is something of what you are realizing,
or the picture, I think,
that itself taking, of course,
everything up here in the mind,
or the thought, I think,
call the picture as taken as self,
and something like not something like a self-exit,
something separated,
not that kind.
I think maybe,
whatever you are realizing,
or the picture is just taken as self.
I'm thinking that everything is in my control.
That's the meaning of self,
but I think you're in that division.
Yeah, well, all of those pictures,
all of those stories are arising,
they are arising in regard to a background.
And that's for your sense of self-exit.
So if you're not mindful,
if you're not recognizing background,
to the extent that it is a background,
means you're taking it to be yourself,
and as such, whatever arising that arises for yourself.
So even if you're not necessarily thinking this is me,
this is my arising for me,
in front of me,
I can see that I can think about it,
I, and those remains,
I always remains the center of that experience.
But if you see that even that I,
is another thing that has a reason.
On that level of that background,
that's a different story, because if you see it as a background,
you'll see, oh, well,
that background is only background in regard to something
that it's right in front of you,
which means background is determined by that thing.
And vice versa,
background determines the actual,
because it can only arise,
something can only arise directly,
based on the peripheral bases.
So it's mutual determining,
and you realize, well, whatever,
yourself goes,
it will be either here or there.
There is no in between or the third place that you don't know.
It's either the background,
because both of these things
mutually determine each other,
which means none of them can remain standing on their own.
And if that is the case,
there is no room for the self,
which is usually the implication of
being able to stand by itself alone.
You mean the background,
still in standing,
so you mean the rec as a receiver,
all the things, what do you mean?
You can call it a chair, yeah, you can call it.
You can just say it's a background,
because it's a background.
The general ambiguous less defined thoughts,
the domain of those,
that's a background.
If you like, when people start using the terms,
like the witness,
the observer, the receiver,
then already implies
that they have taken that very much
to be their self.
Because background is not witnessing anything.
Background is a background.
Background is only a background,
because it's not foreground.
And then which is foreground,
is a foreground, because it's not background.
And then you realize that,
you recognize that all the possibilities
of your current foreground,
that's all they need in the background.
The new things you can attend
based on the current,
things that you've been attending,
and so on.
So that way you can't create anything,
you just find things already there
or reason in that background,
which determines what's right in front of you
because you can attend it,
as something that, as there isn't,
on account of that background.
But another way it also works as well,
because when you attend something directly
right in front of you,
that defines what,
what you're attending is that,
which is not the background,
which means,
in relation to that,
everything else is the background.
So that's what Niano Riro is talking as well.
The actual determine is the peripheral,
so it refers to the background
or the general experience as a negative experience
in regard to the positive thing you're attending.
But negative is determined only by the positive,
by not being positive,
hence the negative.
And positive is determined by that negative as well,
by not being that negative.
So that's why anything
can become positive,
downright in front of you,
or the negative form of determination.
And if the aggregate,
it all depends on how you're attending it.
Well, I contemplate sometimes,
I just feel like,
usually, this body is considered
like a prop container,
and you need to do things arising in the mind.
And just this whole picture,
it just taken itself,
you've got this canister,
why this general peripheral,
these two things should be separated.
Well, you're trying to separate them,
you're trying to separate them
on a direct actual level,
which means that's not really
the background I'm talking about.
When you start comparing
all actual and peripheral,
those are actually both actual for you.
Because peripheral is only that
which you're not attending.
The background of your attention,
right there and then,
which means if you want to look at it
with your attention,
it just becomes another actual.
And something else now,
is that which you're not looking at.
So it's learning how to see that
without having to directly look at it.
How to proceed with it?
It can happen.
Well, you can, it's possible.
And that's what Yonisomanasika means.
The proper attention,
depending on how you translate it.
Yonisom means the womb,
so usually your attention
pulls you out there
at whatever you're attending.
But it does, it's almost like a formal direction
between, it has been directed.
And that place of origin
where that attention came from,
that's something people know mindful
because mindful of,
because that's the background of what they're attending.
That's the negative.
So in the same sense,
your eye cannot see itself.
But you will, you can discern it
and know that it's there
based on the things that you see.
Eye, anything, sights.
So in the same sense,
the fact that you're already
find your attention attending things,
you can know it's roots.
You can know where that direction came from.
There is no solid source
that emits attention.
Not knowing that there is no solid source
that emits this attention
is basically why people assume
that there is a solid source,
which is a sense of self.
Always, no matter what culture,
what background people are,
whenever there is a sense of self,
it will always be the point of origin
of my attention, my intention,
my will, my volition.
That's inseparable from the sense of self.
But if you were to see
that actually there is no solid point
of it, it's just the direction.
Kind of almost infinite
in both directions.
Come from a solid point.
You're just finding there attending.
And then attending this is then attending that.
So you can start to discern
the origins of their direction
in a sense of the background
of what's being attended
by there and then.
And that's what you only see
when a secara is.
Recognizing things on a more general level
while you're attending something else.
Directly.
And that recognition
can come
like with that attention.
So to speak.
As I said before, if you
are attending something
and then just
you're aware of the background
to some extent.
But then if you look at it directly,
it's not the background anymore.
It's another direct thing.
So you have to learn how to see it very thoroughly,
how to see without moving your sight,
without having to look at it.
I'm aware of that already.
It's already in front.
Well, not necessarily.
It's in front when you attend it.
So you have to learn how to be aware of it.
Because you are aware of it.
You don't agree.
Everybody is.
That's how intentions operate.
But you have to learn how to remain aware
without needing to attend it.
Or in this case,
over-attended.
In which means basically
what's kind of extracted from that background
and now it's being fully attended.
So that's what the body posture
and some of these things are inherently
almost always in the background.
And establishing mindfulness upon that
will mean you're establishing mindfulness upon the background.
It's not as much
as a container
for your experience.
As you said, it's more
a necessary random cause
for your experience.
The body,
bodily organs, just the living body,
it's there in the world.
Same as every other object you can see.
It's a particular,
it's the most specific object
because it has an nature
to be the reason for your experience as a whole.
Like, if there is no living body,
there's nothing you can experience.
And you can't even conceive experience
without your living body.
But then the living body is
an object in the world.
It's just a part of matter for great elements.
It's just there, a subject
to elements, subject to aging,
to getting sick to die.
Subject to everything.
Just as you know, the stone is subject to whether
the animal is subject to other.
It's just out there.
Yet it is the thing because of which
your whole experience is there
and you know it,
whichever way you know it,
including your body.
I think because the body is already there,
is that because of which
you're able to designate things
including the body.
Sometimes I feel that there might be some meaning
that some, of course,
that's actually quite natural,
but sometimes I contemplate.
Sometimes we always use something
like reacting to some outside
of the people.
But suppose some people,
if someone tells me something
and if I get angry,
actually everything is happening within.
Nothing to do with others.
But sometimes I lose mindfulness
and then I feel that person is wrong.
Not my fault.
He is a one problem that it's something to me.
But he contemplates
everything is happening within our mind.
Just reacting to it.
Well, it doesn't really matter where it is happening.
Well, matters is that you are affected
by what's happening.
Things can happen inside,
it can happen inside, outside,
it can happen inside and outside.
The point is they are happening
and you are affected by that.
So that's what you want to be concerned with.
Not where it's happening,
how, why,
what reasons.
You want to be concerned with the fact
that you are affected by whatever
it's happening.
And you can eventually overcome that,
but again,
by learning how to not exclude
things out of your experience,
whether direct, whether peripheral,
you have to develop mindfulness
of your experience as a whole.
So if there is the experience of unpleasant person
telling you something offensive, unpleasant
and you are emotionally upset
on account of that,
well, all that is already one experience as a whole.
There is the living random body
in the world
that happens to be closest to you
because of which you are what you are
and you are able to hear this person speak
and think on account of it
and get upset.
And that's all simultaneous
because for as long as that living body
there is present,
means your whole experience
will stand on it.
And you can be distracted here.
Okay.
For as long as your experience
for as long as the living body is present,
while it's present,
the whole domain of the senses,
thoughts,
interaction with others, all that will stand.
If there is nobody,
none of this can stay even for a second longer.
It's a single ten years.
So start seeing it like that.
Eventually you will start recognizing
inherently that you're not able to hold,
you're not able to,
because that random body there,
it's clearly not in your control
and you don't possess that.
Yet it is the reason of your experience.
Which means that,
which means that
the very foundations
of your experience
are inaccessible to you.
So that means that your whole experience
equally cannot be yours.
Including your pollution,
your intention,
anything that closes associated to the sense of self,
you see that is fundamentally undermined
by the fact that
you're in no control over the four great elements,
they're basically the reason for,
for the shape of your body,
functionality of your body,
life associated with conscious and spirit,
that's removed,
all of which is gone.
So it's not about addressing,
sorting out the person that upset you or anything,
just surmounting the whole picture,
and then in order to discern that,
actually,
this could not have been yours to begin with.
And that's the whole point.
Then you will not be affected by whatever arises.
Even if it's you,
not a horrible experience,
sometimes they're really worried about it as soon as.
But the other hands, they were not affected by it.
I think,
but in the case of Pututana,
how it is, sometimes it's important
to the, like,
choosing the thinking,
the content,
something has to choose.
Otherwise, I wish sometimes,
I believe I keep thinking about the tree or something.
And if I keep thinking about the tree or something.
Well, what you should do then,
you should start thinking about yourself,
thinking about the tree,
or thinking about yourself doing this,
or thinking about yourself,
thinking something else.
Don't just think that,
or do that.
That's how you start developing mindfulness.
Seeing yourself do things.
Seeing yourself think things.
What that's been seen
will be recognized.
Oh, this is just another thing that I am seeing.
And as such,
it's a reason phenomena,
which means he's subject to all of those,
it's subject to impermanence,
suffering,
and therefore it cannot be taken itself.
But you have to keep seeing it like that,
because the tendency
for the sense of self is to be,
a privileged position in regard to your whole experience.
Which means,
you might see it as a thought,
you might see it as a consequence,
you might see it as a phenomena,
but it's always assumed to be more.
But by constantly seeing yourself doing things,
you're getting more familiar with it,
and being more familiar,
you're seeing it clearer,
and you realize there isn't anything more to this.
How can you be,
how can you start assuming consciousness
that are,
how can you be aware of consciousness?
You can't. You can't be aware of consciousness,
because it's your contradiction in terms.
But you can discern,
you can know that consciousness is there,
as that direction I was talking about
in regard to the attention.
So recognizing the nature of direction
means recognizing the nature of consciousness.
And consciousness is out there,
with that random matter.
It's that random matter
that's the post-consciousness
that your life is here known for what it is.
Usually people assume, again,
comes through that directionality
of the sense of self
as being the source for, you know,
the me-speaking,
thinking, doing things and so on.
But basically, whether it's me here,
things out there, younger,
all of that is already there together
because of that conscious body.
Which means even the sense of space
is secondary.
Here, there, here and there.
Sorry, here and younger, here and younger.
All of that is already given there.
And that there is that background
I'm talking about.
So it's not here, in here,
as opposed to the objects around me,
both are actually already there,
given, and known as thoughts
as representation, as dama,
whatever you want to translate it.
Actually, if I see that I think that
the B-personal, that kind of practice
actually is mistaken
because actually there is something
like a thinking with this,
some teachers, they teach
like a B-mindful with the movement
of the body.
But then like a drawing the right between
this body and the outside.
But it's already mistaken there.
It will just be reinforced
in the same mistake you began with.
Not just you don't want to be
drawing the line in between,
but you don't want to actually
be focusing constantly
on what's right, what's your
what's actual, what's actual.
Because the harder you try to focus on that,
the more oblivious of the background
you will be. You will not be seeing it.
Which means
less and less foundation for mindfulness.
Which it's not accidental
that all the people
will seriously get into the B-personal,
intense, very wonder.
Because it's just you
constantly just trying to catch
you, trying to see it.
And I was just saying to you there
that the similarly in the
sutras where the Buddha said the person
without the right view, he mismeditates,
premeditates, overmeditates,
undermeditates, says it's like a
jackal waiting by the bins
for the mouse to come out
or bird waiting for the fish.
You're just praying, praying, praying
just waiting for it
as an animal
which is hunting.
And that's a completely wrong attitude.
It's completely directed out there.
There is no background. There is no seeing yourself
waiting for a mouse to come out of the bin.
Because if you go,
you will recognize, well,
whether we're looking for a mouse or
whether it's after the element.
The point is to see myself what I'm doing.
And that's how you can also start distinguishing
wholesome and unwholesome.
By unwholesome things you don't really
think about and maybe later.
But if you get used to seeing
yourself doing things,
thinking things, feeling things,
whatever,
you will then always have that
like an extra space
to whatever has a reason
from which you can have a clear
point of view.
You can see that, well, yeah,
no matter how much I'm pulled or whatever,
this seems inherently unwholesome.
So I think there is nothing to worry about
something, some people,
even just reading the book or some people,
they worry that people too much,
like getting absorbed in it and...
Why would you worry? Because that random
body, living body,
paid with consciousness is already there.
Whether you're reading the book or not,
it's already there.
So you just have to learn how to maintain that knowledge
without the need to be constantly
bringing it to your mind.
What do you mean?
The knowledge of your
random living body there,
which is the reason for your whole experience
of reading the book.
That knowledge is really,
it's a real thing. It's a base for mindfulness.
Because it's the right knowledge.
It pertains to the things as they are.
If you know it,
you don't have to keep asking
yourself or reminding yourself,
whether you know what you have to do
that in the beginning.
You have to do that in the beginning.
But later on, you don't.
The knowledge is there.
That's what I mean. In the beginning, you will have to
stop doing whatever you're doing
in order to remind yourself
of the order of mindfulness.
But you do that only so that,
okay, now reminding myself,
now let me continue doing what I was doing
and try to remain mindful
that one percent of the background,
as I spoke before,
for as long as I can.
The person is completely opposite.
Stop being mindful of that background
and just focus as hard as you can
to whatever it's right in front of you.
Not seeing the background.
It's basically like, imagine,
I don't know, what would be the similar?
Okay, fishing rod.
You throw the fishing rod
into the water and then you have to wait for the fish
to grab the bait.
You throw the rod, you take it out,
you throw it, you throw it, you throw it, you throw it, you take it out.
And then it becomes a goal in itself.
And that's what you don't want to do.
So, yeah, sometimes you have to attend back
to the things, to the reasoning, to the thoughts,
to what you've read, based on mindfulness.
Only so to relieve it.
And see if it's going to settle the proper way.
When you forget about it, then okay.
Remind yourself again.
But that's the thing.
I have to keep it right in front of your mind all the time,
because that's impossible.
You want to be able to let it go,
like, seep into the background,
and still be aware of it.
No matter how far it goes,
you're aware to that extent.
But you're still aware.
That's why even 1% of such mindfulness
is actually more than enough
to be fully established
in the attitude of mindfulness.
It's actually that for me,
it would be to be fully established,
to have 99% of your attention
needing to be mindful, no.
Because mindfulness is a structural thing.
It's not something you do.
What have to do in the beginning, yes,
because you don't know what it is.
Once you discern it, knowing what mindfulness is,
is what makes you mindful.
Suppose if I'm mindful of the body posture,
it's in my background.
Is it the same?
The thing is, you can be mindful of it actually.
If you're thinking about your body posture,
then your body is always the background,
but now you're also thinking about it.
So it's present in both ways.
But sooner or later you have to stop thinking about it,
and when you do,
you still want to be able to remain aware of it as a background.
Be aware.
Yeah, because it is there.
That's the thing.
Your body is there.
Even if you forget about it,
it is there in a certain position,
in a certain posture, doing something.
And if somebody was to ask you,
how is your body now,
you would be able to give the answer right away.
Which means the knowledge of that is there.
It's just not being recognized.
If I'm aware of that,
it means that already it's in front of you.
Now, if you're aware,
if you can be aware of where it is,
if you append it,
then you make it in front.
Because whether you append something or not,
you're aware of it.
So awareness is more fundamental than the attention.
Structurally.
It means that our awareness is not noticed.
Yeah, I don't know this.
If you're not noticing awareness,
then you're unaware.
I know where.
But awareness as a potential is there.
Because if you weren't cleaned,
you wouldn't wake up,
you wouldn't be able to become aware.
What's the difference between awareness and consciousness?
Well, let's say the consciousness
is that direction given to you.
Direction that comes from that random body.
No, both of the water is present all the time.
Yeah.
Awareness is present all the time.
Well, awareness is probably all the time.
It is potential all the time.
But if you don't know it,
then you're unaware.
I don't know where.
But you see time always over the back time.
No, you're always in the direction.
There is always a background.
If there is a direction or something,
it means it has been directed from some point.
And that's the background to where it is.
So there is always that direction, that background.
So it's always possible for you to recognize it,
to know it, to be mindful of it.
But it doesn't mean that you always are mindful of it.
Hence the point of the practice of dharma.
Background, to see the background is important,
because I have to see the self,
from fear, from fear I'm attending.
But you can't see yourself directly.
Yeah.
And then say this is not myself.
You just want to start including everything,
actual and peripheral, foreground and background.
And if you do that long enough,
you will start to discern that your sense of self
can't be in between the two.
It's either the foreground or background.
And as such, it can't be permanent.
It's by not knowing that,
you assume yourself to be in limbo.
So neither foreground or background,
it's everywhere and nowhere.
That's only because you don't really know
either foreground or the background.
And that's that's your experience.
Usually, the view is usually standing background.
But it's not seen.
But before I remember,
I spoke to you a lot,
something about meditation.
In meditation, usually, I see that
the whole picture of the mind,
of course, being mindful of the body.
But at the same time, in the mind,
what kind of thought arising?
I see that.
And then you, I remember,
I have to see the whole picture,
the whole picture that I'm taking in this mind.
It means me or myself.
So I have to see the whole picture,
no need to focus on the one thought.
It's the same.
Yeah, we'll see it.
Like again,
you're sort of repeating what I said,
but you're not saying it in the same way.
And the difference is, again,
that being mindful of the background
means being mindful of your experience as a whole.
But when you say,
I have to see the whole picture,
that means I have to attend the whole picture.
So you're trying to put it all in front of you.
And that's not what I'm saying.
Because no matter how much you manage
to put it in front of you,
there's always going to be background to it.
And if you don't recognize it,
it means you have left quite a good bit out.
And that's where yourself is going to be then.
But if you start seeing,
okay, this is actually what I'm doing,
while with the back of my mind,
I'm mindful of myself doing that,
which is already a formal background
for what you're doing.
Eventually, you recognize that there is no room
for yourself to be anywhere in between,
or left, or it will be either here or there,
as such, it will pertain to either here or there,
and it won't be that sense of independent self.
It means that,
it means the purpose of the practice
is that to find out that there is nothing
actually can find that as a self,
that's suppose that if I'm mindful of the body,
I have to...
To find out that your sense of self,
basically, is not independent.
Because at the moment, for a particular sense of self,
feels independent of anything,
and everything.
So by always practicing mindfulness,
well, by developing the extent of mindfulness,
for as long as it's necessary,
then it can become apparent that,
even that sense of self,
that appears that can be talked about,
can be designated,
it's not independent.
It's depending upon this reason background,
and these things that I'm directly attending,
whatever they may be,
sweepingly,
washing dishes,
rigging books, whatever,
while your body randomly living,
is present there, your sense is working and so on.
So you realize the sense of self,
it's usually was hiding kind of in between,
by not knowing either of those things.
But now that you've practicing mindfulness correctly,
in regards to the experience as a whole,
means sooner or later,
that sense of self will lose that
independence,
and you just, well,
even if there is sense of self,
it's not mine.
It cannot be mine.
And that's what not self means.
I said it before,
it doesn't mean there is no self,
means that that which is taken as self,
is not yours.
Cannot be yours.
And that's the thing,
it concerns you,
ah, this is not myself,
that's not how you overcome the sense of self.
You overcome that by knowing that,
that cannot even be your sense of self
and could not have been your sense of self.
And then it won't be your sense of self.
So why are you moving?
You are using the main thing in mindfulness
that I am doing this,
that I'm washing the carpal.
You're thinking about that.
So you can be washing the carpal over there,
but you don't want to have to be telling yourself,
I am washing the carp,
I am washing the carp.
You want to know,
you want to be seeing yourself
with the back of your mind,
seeing yourself washing the carp.
So it's, let's say,
let's put it like this,
it's a bit more relaxed
than needing to constantly attend it.
I am washing the carp,
I am holding the carp.
No, you already picked up the carp,
you don't have to keep telling yourself,
what you're doing,
you know what you're doing.
So you just want to,
almost like,
almost imagine,
another view,
looking at you,
doing this,
but not interfering,
not telling you anything,
just keeping an eye
on what you're doing.
And that's the practice of reflection.
You just reflect upon yourself,
doing whatever you happen to be doing.
It means not keeping someone
like outside,
you know,
some people,
they advise you
to really keep someone,
like the observer.
Yeah, but there's a thing,
if you start keeping the observer,
you start assuming
that observer to be your
more real self.
But no,
the only reason you can reflect
upon yourself doing something
is because you're doing something,
you're able to do something.
So that particular thing you're doing
is the reason,
or rather,
that particular body
that you're using
in doing these things,
is the reason
that you're alive,
that you're able to think,
and do these things,
and discern them
as something to be done.
So no matter how far you go
in your reflection,
and your observer,
or whatever else,
that will never be independent
of this living body
right here,
that it's washing the dishes.
And vice versa,
washing the dishes
will never be intelligible or known
if there is no reflection
in regard to it.
Hence, now,
you should determine
each other like the two sticks,
you move on,
the other one falls,
instantly.
So that anchor is anything
working,
like a background,
it depends on the person
that some people
they like to keep,
anchoring in some
regular breath,
or something.
Anything working well.
Well,
everything can be an anchor,
but not,
there doesn't
say we mean that people can actually
establish an anchor
of mindfulness in everything.
What's the purpose of anchor?
I mean,
it's a disability.
Well, anchor means mindfulness.
Anchor in that means
you're mindful of that.
You are reflecting upon yourself
while you're washing the dishes.
You're mindful of the background
And when I say mindful of the background,
I don't mean mindful of different things.
I mean,
I wash the dishes,
but I'm listening to this sound,
which,
because of that, I mindful no.
Wash the dishes means
you're mindful of your body washing the dishes.
So you're mindful of standing.
You're mindful of the given body,
while you're doing particular dishes
with your hands and so on.
Well, you can even be mindful of the intention.
To wash the dishes.
Because for as long as you're
intention to have the dishes washed,
is present,
you'll be washing the dishes.
When that intention changes,
you stop doing it.
Either because you finished
or because something more important came up.
But that's the thing.
What people do,
they don't see them.
So you have the intention to wash the dishes,
and you start washing the dishes
and you forgot about the intention to wash the dishes.
But it's actually still present there,
just now in that background,
on a more general level.
Why? Because if it were not present there,
you wouldn't be picking up the sponge,
taking more washing up liquid,
getting another cup.
But all of that is bombed
by a more general intention of having these dishes washed,
having the sink clean.
And if you're mindful of that more general intention,
they're still there.
So you don't have to create it,
fabricate it,
you just have to disown it because it's there.
Then you'll be mindful of whatever particular things you do
on account of that intention.
And that's just,
and that intention and so on,
it's another thought.
But it's a more subtle thought.
Then the actual thoughts you're having
while you're washing the dishes.
It means if my mindfulness is on the body posture,
then being aware of the intention.
You can be mindful of your body posture
and then don't interfere with your thoughts
and what you're doing,
why are you mindful of your body posture?
That may be simple.
I didn't know what I'm doing with that scene.
Whatever you're doing,
you can do only because your body is still there alive.
Senses are working and functioning.
So if you're mindful of that body,
body posture more specifically,
and then allow yourself,
allow your mind to go and do things.
While peripherally,
you do, like,
keep the corner of your eyes,
so to speak,
on that body posture,
while you're doing this stuff.
And that will always already be a more accurate practice
of mindfulness.
So you don't want to be overly intending,
overly intending things.
You don't want to be,
I'm washing the dishes,
I'm standing, I'm standing, I'm standing,
because they're just bringing things forward,
forcefully,
which means you'll never ever see that background
and there won't be any anchor established in it.
But if you recognize that this standing body,
or sitting body,
this body in itself,
for as long as it's alive,
will be the direct reason for this whole world,
existing and standing,
and these feelings,
experience and so on.
If those elements break apart,
if they're taken away,
and they will be,
because I have no idea
where they came from,
how they're given,
or how can they even be,
what they can't even be accessed in any way,
but they are the reason
for your whole experience as a whole.
So when those four great elements go,
you can't even conceive the experience
to remain standing.
So how about you just simply
do body contemplation?
This is body contemplation.
Well again,
if you do it correctly,
it's fine.
But if you're doing body contemplation,
in terms of just bringing things forward into your mind,
while not seeing the background,
you won't be mindful of it.
Body contemplation over to see the body contemplation.
Well, body contemplation,
the correct one in the sutras,
it's just recognizing the random parts of the body,
as that, because of which,
you're able to even think about the random parts of your body.
Taking the body as mine.
Yeah, that's the result of it.
How is it,
isn't going to be,
is it teased at the right of the body
feeling in common,
the changing?
It's not feeling.
The sensation they talk about,
is just the bodily perceptions.
But obviously,
by calling them feelings,
they kind of give them a more prominent position,
which results if you can observe that
long enough, you'll be purified.
But that's already the contradiction in terms.
There is no moving feeling through your hand or through your arm.
That's a sensation.
You can call it that's a perception,
which means you think your perception is what you feel.
So you're more confused than you were before you started doing that method.
Contemporary on the perception
that the changing in common is positive.
Nothing.
Why is that relevant?
Yeah.
Why is it relevant how my elbow feels?
It doesn't matter.
Mine is hurt.
So what?
The main problem is
you're taking the body as mine.
No.
The main problem is not,
he doesn't know the way out of unpleasant feeling.
That's the main problem.
That's why protrusion is protrusion.
He doesn't know for no truth.
But it's the truth.
So you can say that his body
for the eternity,
he's looking in the wrong place.
It's not why and how I feel this body
and how it changes and how it moves.
It's why do I not know escape
from the feelings that arise
dependent on this body?
Any feelings?
Can't escape because
taking the body as mine.
Well, they can escape
because they don't know what escape is.
But if someone here
like contemplated this body
with airmen, firemen,
some of these are the changing...
Again, is there doing it
running from to them
overattending it?
It will not stand for that
which elements are.
Because elements are always
the background.
The four grey elements
can be discerned
and recognized
in that very distant background.
That is present.
It's right there and now,
but it's much, much, much subtler.
And unless your attention
has been trained
to the subtler levels,
you just won't be able to see it.
You look like,
well, imagine you have a lens.
Camera lens or a pair of glasses, whatever.
That it's only for a certain distance.
Like 50 millimeters to 80 millimeters distance,
which means anything before that you won't see.
No matter how close you look,
you're just overseeing it.
And then that's basically
untrained attention.
You're just used to overattending things.
That's what you used to regard.
That's what you're able to recognize.
Anything less than that you won't see.
So with person with such attention,
even if they think about elements,
or whatever they want to be thinking about elements,
they think what they are.
But they'll think about that,
which they think elements are,
based on that scope of attention that they have.
But if you start training your attention
in regard to the background,
you start seeing more of that direction
without actually having to change it.
Why?
Is it how to contemplate
all the implements of the body?
Well, again, if you,
your body right there right now,
whatever, you have saved
position and you have saved more particular things.
But overall, that body aging,
that body growing, that body getting sick,
that body being subject and permanent,
you can't stop that.
You can't even conceive
how it would be if you could control it.
It's just inaccessible to you.
And if you clarify that,
you can start seeing that body
as actually a reason for your whole life,
for your whole experience,
for everything.
Everything you ever experienced,
everything you ever experienced,
is because your body was there living
with senses functioning.
So your experience can't remain standing
without that body.
So the implements is not looking at the change,
because change is just another experience.
The implements is recognizing that
it's inaccessible.
The thing has a reason on its own,
that body is there on its own, really.
You didn't have say,
it's creation, it's manifestation,
it's a sense, it's not anything.
You're just using it.
But you can only use it because
it was already given beforehand,
and that's what impermanence means.
Ah, this using won't last forever.
Why? Because where these things came from
is inconceivable to me.
I can't even imagine
where and how the elements, whatever.
But you can't even access it.
Because of that, it's impermanent.
Not because, not because you can see it being destroyed.
There is nothing to do with your body.
We don't have to see that it is there,
where the body or thought or whatever.
Only has to see, no need to see any change.
Only has to see that it is there.
Actually, you want to not see the change.
Because change is always on a more particular level,
while thing remains the same on a more general level.
And that's what you want to start distinguishing.
Because for as long as you're going after change,
your mind is going with it.
So you're not seeing the nature of that.
Because when the thing is changing,
there has to be a degree of that thing standing the same.
And that's always on a more general level.
That's why.
Well, it's always it ends like that.
Some, I think some, some, some, they don't have identification with the body.
But some would, just identify with the mental aggregates on it.
Well, I mean, theoretically, that's possible,
but I said that.
But I think now there is, it's more than a potential identity identified with the body and everything.
If, if the potential was to have that much wisdom,
to truly, truly abandon his body for what it is,
with all of the instruction today and all the suitors
and coming across the dominant Buddhist teaching,
he won't need much more to then discern the general nature of the mind
and any other phenomena as impermanent
and not being able to hold his own self.
So most likely, the potential...
It's possible that 100% of the,
never identify with the body for what it is.
Is it possible to do that?
Well, theoretically, it's possible, but it would still mean a lot of wisdom.
But it's quite unlikely that the person today will develop so much wisdom
and not come across the Buddhist teaching to kind of get the final right tune of the right view.
There is no different mental and bodily aggregates.
The experiences are always experienced as well.
Your body wouldn't be known as your body,
if it's not already appearing on a mental level.
Your thoughts wouldn't be known as your thoughts
if your living body is not already there.
So that distinction between body and mind,
it's kind of unnecessary.
What do you mean by resistance,
the designation of something,
you wrote in your book,
what do you mean by resistance?
Well, it's what I was talking about,
the four great elements, for example.
They are what your body made of.
I just had a question.
Why is it used in sutra instead of for greater?
Why is this great?
Because they're so general.
So much in the background.
It's the great.
Great.
The great elements, yeah.
Mahabuddha.
Mahabuddha is the power.
And...
Your body being made out of those elements.
Again, as I said,
your body is known as your body
because it's still living there.
You can download it.
Your body is known as such
because the body is there as that
because of which you can know that body.
Well, there is that
a resisting aspect to that body,
the aspect that you can't even access,
you can't even comprehend.
Because of which your body is aging,
subject to elements change,
disappearance, destruction, and so on.
So it's that extent
of that resistance that comes from these elements.
But that is upon which your whole experience is actually founded.
So you start to discern,
you start to know
that you are fully depending upon something
you can't even think of
and you can't even comprehend.
You just get the sense of it resisting you.
Hence resistance.
Resistance.
Means the resistance.
Means not being in your control.
Means you can't even conceive it to be in your control.
It's offering...
That means your volition, your will, has its limits.
It can't reach its own foundations.
They are resisting it.
They are showing their own independence.
You can't even change.
You can't even think of it.
It is only for those who have served you.
In a distance of 30 years.
Well, no.
That's basically the four elements.
They find the footing in the experience
for as long as it is in or of the present.
So they are and can talk about resistance
but there is nothing resisting it or resisting him
or resisting in it or out of it.
It's just the four elements
will remain sort of floating about
for as long as the followers are there
and when he dies they are ticked.
No more even because it's all talking about.
For Arya again there is sort of a bit of both
until all of the poison and toxins are cleared out.
But a putogenite would be me and then whenever he needs the resistance
he would be resisting me, resisting in regard to me.
I am resisting it.
I am resisting in it or out of it or whatever.
It means trying to control it.
Trying to control it.
I was suffering.
Yes.
But you want to recognize just that the foundations of your experience
are there which resist you
because it can never even be taken up.
You can't see directly the four great elements.
They are always in the background.
The four great elements as the foundation of this random body
is just because what you see will be your perception
and four great elements are determining your perception
which means you can't ever access them with that perception.
You can only know that your perception is there because of
that which resist out there that you can't even see.
Resistance and designation?
Well that's the designation.
Perception would be the designation.
What you can perceive, you can talk about,
you can designate, you can think it.
But not that because of which that perception is there
in the first place.
So that which resist is what's being designated.
As that because of which designation is possible in the first place.
So this is all kind of a slightly more advanced way of saying
that fundamentally things are completely out of your control,
including your own sense of control.
Nobody is denying your sense of control.
What you want to realize is that you can't own even that.
Why? Because it's fully found that which is completely out of your hands.
Self is always in regard to that sense of control.
So once you start recognizing that your own sense of control is enclosed
with this whole thing that it's limiting you.
Then that you realize that well even this control that I can't access
as modified things to an extent I can't know about.
It's not permanent because when its foundations go, it will all go.
But what's the raw concentration?
Because it's part of the eightfold path.
Concentration is the key more things together.
Like usually people think concentration is focusing hard on one point.
No, it's finding the one point that includes everything else.
Not finding the one that excludes everything else.
Concentration means being fully established and steady in that background
that I'm talking about.
When you concentrate it is when your mind is settled in that background.
And no matter what actually you're doing,
what things are attacking you, harassing you, coming your way,
pleasing you, displeasing you.
That concentration remains steady and I'm all alone.
And so the will always use those descriptions of unshakeable
and so on and so forth.
So because it's fully established in this,
so whatever it's coming, it still stays to your constant mind.
It's concentrated.
So it's about taking everything like that.
It's about becoming so established.
It's about, well again, becoming so stepping back so much
that you get really, really settled in that background.
So there is no concentration without mindfulness.
If the concentration is about focusing and not seeing anything else,
that's not concentration.
The concentration of the sutras is the concentration where you're so mindful
that even when you're not making effort to be mindful,
you're still mindful of that.
But none of us said that no matter how far the puturjuna reflects
that there's still an aspect of ignorance and that reflection.
Yeah, which is why he has to take it on artificially
and start looking for what he reflects upon
as in permanent, as suffering,
and then as his experience is not.
He doesn't see any of that.
Oh, so he starts emulating it from inside
and if he does it correctly and if it corresponds
to the things the way they are,
it will take the...
So if you refer to it as a graph,
if they are on an alien graph,
and then it takes over eventually.
So then formal meditation,
I've done that so often like clamping up and trying to focus
really hard on the body or the breath, but instead...
No, just find your body as already there breathing.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
And that's a very clear...
Yeah, yeah, it's just there.
You have to go grasp it or reach out for it.
And the mind will always inevitably be attending to something.
Yeah, essentially it doesn't matter what it is.
Yeah, in that sense.
Like if you're mindful of your body,
you don't have to worry about...
In that correct sense,
if you find your body present there,
you don't have to worry about what exactly you are thinking
that second on a particular level,
because you have to be thinking something.
And then being aware of thoughts,
like when you're thinking,
it takes a lot of your mental focus and energy,
but you still have to add some reflection...
Well, again, like thinking.
You know, if mostly attention is gone,
dedicated to whatever you're thinking about,
still, you know you're there alive,
this random body is still living and functioning.
Yeah.
And that's the reason for you being able to think in the first place.
So having that little knowledge is enough,
because no matter how much you're caught up in your thoughts,
if this body is not there present,
alive on its own completely indifferent to your thoughts,
those thoughts are going to be there.
They couldn't.
Inconservable.
Okay.
Sometimes I feel like,
I'm a monster,
but sometimes, some of the automatic things are created
and the interest of what you think,
thoughts are very automatic reviews.
And sometimes it's just the only different.
Well, look, particular thoughts are reduced.
Thoughts are not reduced.
They can just be in slower or whatever else,
but it's not reduced because your particular thoughts
about this might disappear,
but the fact that you're aware of your experiences
or your breathing means.
But you're thinking of that,
That's being thought.
So that's not in progress.
Suppose it's more time thinking about this bread.
Automatically it's become related.
If it's just thinking about the bread only,
it's not thinking much.
Well, you can think about the bread.
For as long as you're still established mindfully
upon the experiences, upon that background,
upon your body breathing,
and you're intending then bread.
But if you're just thinking what's right in front of you,
you're trying to turn yourself into a robot,
and it will not work.
Because you're not mindful.
You're mindful only in reference to the background.
That's what mindfulness is.
If you're just bringing things forward,
that's not mindfulness.
Some people, when they just want to practice jhana, jhana.
That's not jhana either, yeah.
Jhana is being fully established in that background.
To the extent where the domain is,
you step outside of the domain of centrality,
the first jhana.
Then the domain of thought in the second jhana.
So you're not any more thinking about this thought,
or that thought, means...
Yeah.
Means...
You're not thinking about this thought,
the nature of thinking is there.
Nature of a thought.
And that's very, very general, as you can see,
that it's just completely not specific,
yet it's really such.
And that's what I mean when I say a background.
And that's the first jhana.
The second jhana goes beyond that.
Goes beyond the domain of the nature of thought.
In the civil war, doing the daily, daily activity,
sometimes when I feel a little...
like some day feel like there's so many,
like too much thinking sometimes,
so much of thought.
And if I just want to reduce that thought,
then just...
Don't reduce the thought.
Reduce your emotional involvement with that thought.
If you try interfering with your thoughts,
you just try and you end up thinking more.
That's not what.
So you'll be worse than before.
But if you're mindful of your body
being present there while you're thinking,
it can give you enough space
to know to be fully,
completely immersed in whatever your mind is thinking.
And that's all, that's enough.
You just have to be patient with that,
and it will be recognized as enough.
Why? Because no matter how hard your mind is working,
for as long as you're not emotional disturbed,
it's absolutely fine.
Even if it's horrible thoughts,
even if it's thoughts that you don't want to have,
emotionally you're not involved,
that's your concern.
Because whatever thoughts ever is,
and they will have to cease.
But if you try to interfere with them before,
means, oh, well, you've taken
then the main thought is yours.
You think you have said
in what you should be thinking, and so on.
So you start interfering with it.
Sometimes I write a little contemplative.
Very well, it's like suffering arises.
A lot of times I'm actually more like identification to you.
So then I hear any kind of suffering.
No, the suffering, the suffering has a reason.
It means identification was there beforehand.
That's already like a symptom of the underlying problem.
Are you bored?
That's the symptom of the underlying problem.
It's not that that's when you're in the identification happens.
And you have to catch it or something like that.
So for you, in your mind,
a lot of thoughts appear.
No problem at all, right?
Yes, your mind...
They were never a problem, yeah?
How do you...
How do you still...
What is a reason to cease?
You contemplate on the individual.
Well, you just...
Again, you stop concerning yourself with a particular thought,
unless there is a reason for it.
You just recognize there is a nature of thinking.
You can go out if you want.
So there is a nature of thinking.
Thoughts are there.
It doesn't matter what thoughts.
It means you're already mindful in regard to whatever you're thinking.
You finish something stronger than fear.
Well, that's the thing.
So then you just endure it.
And then when the fear is gone,
practice even harder in regard to things
that are not too powerful and too overwhelming.
That's how you develop strength.
So then when the next time fear comes,
well, it will be stronger.
So you'll be less affected by it.
But at the time, you can't feel it.
Now the problem has to fix it.
Right now, right now, right now, you won't work.
Fixing it right here, right now,
will be not interfering with it.
That's the closest to fixing that you can get.
This need to endure.
For what is there?
Because you won't be there all the time.
And then next time,
if you're not practicing hard enough,
then you'll remember, well,
there was that time when fear arose
and I didn't know how to escape that fear.
And it was very frightening and painful.
So I better practice now when there is no fear.
So when the fear comes,
I'll be able to handle it and hold it
without being moved by it.
So you use that as an incentive
to make more effort.
What the moment only has to endure.
When the fear is there,
you can sometimes, you know, the fear might be there.
And you still might be able to be mindful,
but if it gets too much, then again,
you can keep trying to be mindful,
but bottom line is don't forget
to endure and be patient.
That's always the end basis.
If everything else fails,
well, at least I'll be able to endure it.
Why not?
Well, for 100, there's no contact with it.
Well, for 100, there is no endurance.
Yeah, there's no more fear.
Yeah, depending on how much toxins are left.
More toxins, more endurance.
More fear.
More liability to fear,
even if he doesn't necessarily experience it.
But I don't think
even the possibility of fear is gone.
Not just that he doesn't experience any fear actually,
but even the possibility of it cannot be...
How do you still think you are very sick
and you're also pain?
How do you...
It's a discomfort,
but it doesn't bring the fear
and it doesn't bring the mental suffering.
How do you make the mindful decisions?
Well, you maintain it by developing it beforehand.
Before you can take it.
That's why the Buddha urged monks and people.
Like, don't wait until it's too late.
Because there is a point when it's too late to practice.
You haven't done enough.
Now it's just too late.
If you spend your whole life not keeping the precepts,
not really making the effort
at the moment of it's too late,
you can't expect nothing.
I've been all fixed in the last year of your life
or something like that.
And every year might be your last year.
And if any time you might be too late already,
or last year or not,
that's why you kept bringing the sense of urgency
in monks and people.
Well, practicing the egon during sickness
will give you a peace for a year later.
Yeah, you can't suffer now.
Like, suffering is when this comfort
or this pleasure affects you mentally,
causing you pain.
No suffering means you can have
even this comfort and this pleasure
and not suffer on that account.
It doesn't affect you.
It's present, it's discomfortable,
but it's not a reason for the pain.
Why? Because it never was.
It was always craving in regard to an experience
that was the reason for your pain.
Now that craving is gone, there's no pain.
Even in the midst of this comfort,
you can't possibly suffer.
That doesn't mean you don't perceive the discomfort.
But you certainly don't feel the pain on the canvas.
Pupiner, when you had a fever,
how would you feel?
Even so, but there was some sort of suffering.
Yeah, yeah.
Because you still had lots of toxins left.
So he was a sort of a doctor,
but you still had a long way to go,
but he couldn't go because he was so sick
with medicines and everything else.
He couldn't be making the effort,
he couldn't be doing nothing, feeling sick,
in pain and not being able to practice.
So he thought, well, I might as well speed it up.
But, you know, sort of on a nose,
he's a sort of on that.
So he had knocked out about that.
Well, a genuine sort of on a nose,
he's a sort of on that.
Sometimes you have people who think they're on that.
That's what it would be.