What are you saying? Anywhere around the corner?
Yeah, the whole work from a cherry.
Uh-huh.
It's the way of life.
Oh yeah.
The way of the gods.
Yeah, the way of the gods.
So the more you know.
The cleaner, the more virtues, the loftier.
The more kind life.
The human life is led.
It becomes more godlike.
The more proliferated, the more based on senses,
revolving around senses,
observed in the senses,
more animal-like is.
Based around sensual pleasures and gratification
and so on.
It's more like animals.
So that's why the human choice,
based on which you perform certain actions,
also not kind of determines
your future sort of direction.
Because it's a sort of realm
in between.
It gives you glimpse about,
you know, animals don't have much,
they're fully responsible,
but they don't have much choice.
And they certainly can't behave like gods.
They can sometimes exhibit human-like behaviour,
which is already a big step forward for them anyway.
Oh, wow, look at that.
And also, when they are good for gods,
they can't behave.
It's harder for them to behave like animals.
But for human being kind of in between,
you can get both,
which is why the distinction is clear to you,
which is why the human realm
has both suffering and pleasure
to such an extent that it's most optimal
for practice.
You get both, you can really recognize.
Animals are just so deeply in pain, basically.
Constant drive, constant fear,
constant need,
no much reflection,
so they don't really know anything better.
Gods, on the other hand,
are usually between intoxicated with pleasure
and no one's never experienced pain,
so they don't stop and think about it.
Human realm is exposed to both,
and you kind of have the threat of the pain
of the suffering,
but then you do have pleasure and gratification,
which is also valid, valid phenomenon.
And that's like the most optimal
to really develop wisdom.
It's really, really, really spectacular,
not just the animal,
just to watch a god, you know?
Yeah.
Just to see how agitated it is.
You can't, like, you know, when you train,
when you train a dog,
in order to get into the list,
you have to get his attention.
So then through little repetition and training,
you keep learning how to get his attention,
and that's when you're telling one command
and you always listen.
But you realize how quickly that attention changes,
and you know sometimes there's no point saying now,
I don't have, like, something else has taken.
Obviously, the well-trained dog
would be able to be snacked out
of whatever has taken his attention,
no matter what.
But that requires, you know,
obviously it depends on the breed
and the skill of the trainer and so on.
But it already was,
and when you do that,
you notice how that attention
is just all over the place constantly.
Sound, sound, smell, smell, smell, smell, smell,
sound, sound, sound,
around the left, right, back,
ah, something agitates, jump, calm, hungry,
constantly, just constantly.
And that's the anyway,
you know, you look at the little cute little bird,
you look at it,
it's just constant terror,
constant threats,
just keeps looking around, switching,
buzzing, switching,
because next moment,
it might be very last,
do some attack or something.
Either birds,
other prey,
preying animals,
I think,
things of that nature.
So you're just constantly,
and that's the anyway though,
constant struggle,
constant fight,
constant survival.
You do?
Like yet?
Well, the other day will.
And for some people,
like to get into,
like you hear this whole,
getting into contact with the animal spirit
and stuff, I guess,
that hold it.
Well, that's ridiculous.
You know, as you,
that the lion,
just gets, you know,
the lion's got no feel.
You can use the similar,
you can say,
the lion is the fearless,
you become fearless,
but you don't emulate a lion.
No, you don't.
Because what else is lion?
It's a killer,
it's a murderer,
it's a rapist,
if that's what lions are.
Or when people glorify animals,
as if they kind of have some deeper,
six cents that we don't have.
Yeah, they have their own ways
of perception, sure.
You know, they can detect
subtly things,
better smells,
but that's the thing.
It's not necessarily,
it's not better,
it's actually more proliferated,
more particular,
more based upon it,
which means less reflection of power
you have in regard to your senses,
more you pull,
driven,
constant drive.
That's what animals are like.
So this whole kind of, you know,
one with a nature,
like I'm a snow into fear,
with a nature self.
Well, that's quite silly actually,
because nature is what some sort of is.
Nature wants you to stay ignorant.
Nature is ignorant,
and it's all about ignorance.
So it's not the getting in touch
with nature,
becoming one with nature,
means becoming one with your ignorance,
fully endorsing it,
as a valid,
as a valid thing that should be
cherished and protected.
Because nature is what it is,
and what it is,
it's affected with religion.
So going against the stream
means going against the nature.
Yeah, sure.
The nature of the body
is to run after its like,
senses,
and that's what the super sick,
five senses are like five wild animals,
they have their feeding grounds,
and that's all they want to do.
They just want to go
and feed in their own feeding grounds.
Eyes will pull you towards sides,
nose will pull you towards mouth,
ears will pull you to the inside,
and that's what your senses are,
and that's what nature is.
So you actually go against that,
against the stream,
against the grain.
Are you going against the nature
or are you understanding
nature for what it is?
Well, that means going against the nature.
Obviously, you know,
there are different ways you can understand
going against the nature.
People can just take that to mean
denying the nature,
but again,
in order to deny something,
that thing has to be accepted first,
which means denial of rebellion
against nature is just confirmation of the nature.
Full understanding,
on the other hand,
is truly going against it,
like overcoming it,
swimming against the stream.
So, yeah, sure.
Going against needs to be
clarified,
like individually,
and understood correctly,
whereas everything else
could be things to done.
One thing is,
once a person
has entered the stream,
sort of on a
three-metre era,
on someone has achieved sort of
one that's a guarantee
that he wouldn't do a lot,
but he wouldn't fall back to ignore us.
So, what do you mean exactly,
but fall back,
before and after fall back?
He would.
He can't unbecome,
a sort of one.
He can't become profusion again.
He can't have
the personality view anymore.
He can't.
No.
But anything below that,
we can break all the precepts,
despite the popular belief.
He can, you know,
break all the precepts.
He cannot practice at all.
But it will require
a lot of carelessness,
lots of exposure to unwholesome circumstances
for him to go that bad,
because he inherently possesses
a criteria of wholesome,
and has that permanently available view,
right view,
that he can effortlessly engage in.
So, it's quite unlikely,
but it's possible,
as they were case in the
cities of Adhrankin,
Sotapana and so on.
We spoke about it before,
I think I spoke there with Tonya.
The Sotas mentioned clearly,
things that Sotapana cannot do,
which is hold anything,
any determination is permanent,
any determination is pleasurable,
anything to assume to be his self.
He can't kill his mother,
he can't kill his father,
he can't kill an other hand,
he can't violate the killing,
can't disparage the Buddha,
or boom the Buddha,
can't take anybody else
other than the Buddha
as his teacher.
Can I say that?
That's all.
Change it.
Can't take,
I can't follow any other teacher.
Why?
Because the Dharma is not just a view,
it's a recognition of the,
like a universal criteria,
that it claims,
you know,
to recognize discern in your experience as a whole,
which means,
once you discern that,
those things are fundamental,
those things are universal.
So that's confirmed,
that becomes the core criteria for everything else.
So whenever you come across any other view,
it's just going to be seen as either chords
to the universal principle,
the right principle,
or it doesn't.
So if you come across some other teaching,
as a Sotapani,
you'll see,
ah, this actually
accords to the principles of the Dharma.
So this teaching is the Dharma.
Or you'll see,
you know,
it doesn't accord the Dharma
for such and such reasons,
that's not Dharma.
And by saying Dharma,
it refers to that universal principle.
You don't have to call it Buddhism,
because often,
today, now,
modern Buddhism,
contemporary Buddhism,
there's nothing to do with the actual Dharma.
This is the views they have evolved,
wrong views,
wrong methods,
wrong principles,
wrong techniques.
So it takes a religion,
product of society,
ignorance,
and so on.
But the Dharma
as a universal principle stands,
and always will stand,
which is why liberation always remains possible.
As the Buddha says,
like, really discovering an ancient path,
and he found the Dharma,
like that,
that has been worked before,
by others,
because he didn't create anything,
nor invent,
he rediscovered it,
and then reformulated it.
So anyone,
that develops wisdom,
but haven't attained,
a state,
could develop it,
no matter what level,
that they fall back to Sansaara,
continuously.
Well, what do you mean by state?
I mean, sort of unknown.
Yeah, yeah.
Like,
putugenus wisdom,
unless he develops it enough,
to cease to be a putugenus,
he remains at risk.
That's why as the Buddha pointed out,
a person really,
a genuine person,
a genuine interest in practice,
you really have to start thinking about,
you know,
developing a right view,
as not an optional thing.
It's your duty to become a Sotapana.
And all of your faculties,
reasoning,
powers of reflection are intact.
You have no reason to not become a Sotapana,
except laziness and lack of effort,
lack of commitment,
lack of determination,
and so on.
Absolutely no reason.
Family, children, wives,
husbands,
none of that is actual excuse.
Obviously people make an excuse out of that,
so they won't feel guilty
on a kind of,
not following the way out.
So they absolve themselves
from responsibility for,
for practice,
for determination,
for giving up,
because they say,
oh, well, I have a family,
I have duties and stuff.
Yeah, it's a worldly duty,
but this pertains to something much more.
So actually,
the worldly duty can never serve
as a reason,
or as an excuse.
It just might require more of your determination,
but then there is no excuse
for not having more determination.
Unless your faculties are impaired,
you're mad,
they range to whatever else,
then there is actually an excuse
for not doing it.
And if you stop and think about it,
how many times have you been reborn?
You might not know,
but you can have a safe guess.
And if you have faith in the Buddha
and trusting his words,
he said how many times,
countless times,
eons, and eons,
and eons,
and eons of rebirth
in every possible realm
that there was,
there's nothing left,
unexperienced,
unexplored,
or anything like that,
so real as well.
From that point of view,
and that's why the Buddha
would talk about that,
because from that point of view,
you can actually look
at this entire life differently,
and real as well,
what is one life dedicated to Dharma?
Nothing.
Because you know,
now something feels all right.
Well, I can't give everything up
in this life
and just go and practice,
because it just feels too much.
Well, from the perspective
of only this life,
it feels too much.
But if you start reflecting,
like from a greater point of view,
you realize what is one life,
dedicated in one life,
succeeding,
maybe failing,
maybe partially succeeding.
Well, at least you know you try.
Because you know,
you can believe in rebirth or not,
or whatever else.
But the point is,
you don't know those things.
One thing you know for sure is,
you will die.
And what if,
the Buddha was right,
when he was talking about
rebirth and everything else,
are you willing,
to kind of just better it,
and gamble in it,
and spend this life carelessly,
doing whatever you want,
whatever it pleases you,
and then the Buddha turns out to be right,
and then you end up much worse
for like thousands of beings.
You know, the chances of coming back up,
the human realm wants to fall lower
into any matter,
for example,
was like the blind seater,
so it comes out every 500 years,
it just comes out to the top of the sea,
and goes down.
So it doesn't linger.
And then there is a yoke
with a piece of wood with a hole in it,
being thrown around by the, you know,
raised winds in the sea,
left and right everywhere.
This turtle has a great chance of sticking its neck
through their little hole,
then somebody who is falling back
onto the animal realm has a chance
to come back on the human realm.
So you consider that, and like again,
you can't have a empirical proof,
or give me a scientific,
but it's because science is all based on senses.
You should expect it to experience
three senses as a proof
that which precedes your senses,
rebuts and realms.
But if you just allow it
as a valid possibility,
you should then,
it will become obvious that
the safe course of action would be,
well, let me assume that there is
just in case that there is.
Because then, I'll be safe.
Rather than gambling,
and just deciding that there isn't,
because there is no more proof
that there is no rebirth,
and there is a proof that there is rebirth.
So people who say,
well, I don't believe in rebirth,
they are no more justified
than those who believe in it.
So you won't accept both,
and then reckon as well,
I don't really know
whether there is or there isn't.
Thus, I should act
just in case that there is.
Because if there is,
I'll be much worse off
if I behave as if there isn't.
Wouldn't that be,
wouldn't that same argument be applied
to a lot of different views?
What do you mean?
Like,
just anything like, you know,
whether it's
a view about how many persons,
or any sort of other philosophical
or religious view.
Well, this is not really a philosophical view.
This clearly pertains something that precedes
or comes after succeeds
after your existence that you know.
Which means,
it's truly metaphysical.
It can't be experienced.
It can be speculated about.
And that's what you reckon as.
This is inherently never,
can never go beyond the level of speculation.
Thus, I should act
just in case,
choose a wise course of action.
But, you know,
views whether there is suffering
and there is freedom of suffering,
that's not metaphysical.
That's not like,
you know,
that can be speculative,
but can also be proven
to yourself,
fully understood,
discerned,
and confirmed.
Okay.
So is that,
especially like,
you know,
that is metaphysical?
Yeah, exactly.
And that's what the Buddha said.
When he said,
well, you don't know,
thus, you should act.
And actually,
you don't even have to believe in it.
You can just use your reasoning right here
and now that you do have,
and just discern.
Well, in case there is a label,
it's actually better to behave here.
And then, plus,
if I do behave here,
people will like me here,
respect me here,
find me trustworthy here,
searchers person,
and then they know they can rely on me.
And then if there is a next life,
great,
then I win,
like on both accounts.
I win here,
I win in the next life.
If there is a next life,
well, so big,
then we all end up the same,
but at least here,
I live happily and respect you by others,
and have my life smoother,
than if I'm a crook of criminal,
and always worrying,
being caught,
or whatever else.
So you really,
you don't need a proof for it.
Just use your reasoning,
and recognize that it's better to act as if there is.
And that's all it matters,
how you act right here right now.
It doesn't matter whether there is or there isn't.
And that's why I brought this up,
because if you start thinking that it really is,
what is
dedicating this life then
to the practice of Dharma?
It's nothing.
This is one life.
Big deal.
You'll be dead anyway,
and you know that for sure.
And not in 50 years,
might be much sooner,
might be much later.
Point is,
it will happen.
So it will come to an end.
So having the spending your time pursuing
mundane goals,
of course,
just plain gratification
of your senses,
just scratching your itch.
You know that,
even from the worldly point of view,
that it doesn't amount to anything more than that.
And then you're dead.
Then your senses start breaking up.
You can't enjoy them anymore.
Everything becomes rather unpleasant.
Your hearing goes.
Your body doesn't listen.
Sickness sets in.
And then you're dead.
And how you spend the life,
being completely controlled by those five wild animals,
just yanking your left and right,
as they please.
And now you're kind of stuck all too weak
to do anything better,
and then you're dead.
And then if there is the next life,
then you'll be really, really screwed.
Because there's obviously the
what I've heard,
common, you know,
just enjoy the life now.
Is there anyone you can,
anyone you have,
just enjoy it.
Do the best you can.
Good time.
Go out.
And then.
Great.
But as I said,
you don't even have to wait for the next life,
or so you can see that,
that view and logic,
well, works, only body,
you have your health,
you have your youth,
you have your life.
And none of those things
are guaranteed that you're going to have the very next moment.
All of them are based upon a gratuitous assumption
that you'll live forever,
or at least for a long time,
and that you will always be healthy.
Well, yeah, life is happening
so that you can go out and enjoy it.
But what about the person who's
going to go out and enjoy it?
Or what about you just next day,
you'll find you have cancer.
Does it work?
It doesn't work.
How are you going to enjoy that?
What happens to that view then,
when you realize,
I'm subject to death,
and now it's confirmed.
And those of you,
that's a fact,
you're going to die,
what's going to happen afterwards as much.
So what's the point?
What's the point of life, you know,
you can just say,
if you have the view that this is all there is,
you know,
you say they don't think very far
further than that, really.
You know, because if you think further than that,
what,
then what's the point of anything?
Is it really the point
just to be enjoying?
Again, as I was just said,
like a few minutes ago,
I'm saying,
like those people having a view,
this is all there is,
well,
that's something you decided,
as a view,
you don't know that for a fact.
So you're no more justified in deciding that,
than deciding,
you know, this isn't all there is.
And as it turns out,
you're less justified,
why?
Because that's much,
less,
much riskier,
course of assumption,
or this is all there is,
to which you can,
while you can.
And then you realize,
well, what if this isn't all there is,
and all my time that I had,
I spent misbehaving
and just running after like an animal,
after any gratification I could get?
Then you end up much worse.
So you want to consider it,
that you don't know,
whether this is all there is,
thus it's better to act,
as if it isn't all there is.
Why?
Because if there is something afterwards,
those people who do say that
there is something afterwards,
they say,
because of that,
you should behave right here right now.
And there is a good sense in that.
And you can see that for yourself,
right here, right now,
even as a protuginous,
protuginous can see that as well.
And then obviously,
if you want even more,
if you want to be free
from suffering right here,
right now,
let alone any future,
instances,
then yeah,
you have to apply yourself even harder,
but again,
it comes from the,
from the same perspective,
except in the fact,
well rather,
recognizing the fact,
that one thing is sure is,
you will grow sick,
age and dying.
That's it.
So, you know,
spend your life enjoying your senses,
works when you're 20-year-old,
when you think you live forever.
Mind you,
you can be 50-year-old
and still say that,
because you think you live forever,
and you're healthy at the time.
But find your sick person,
in a hospital,
bedridden,
saying that,
holding that view.
Oh yeah,
enjoy your life.
This is great.
See,
and I'm still alive,
bedridden in a hospital,
oozing out,
whatever I,
I don't know,
depending on the illness,
I guess.
And,
and that person,
would they be saying,
oh yeah,
enjoy your senses while you,
while you're still alive?
They might be telling others that.
Well, they might,
oh see,
now I'm sick,
really make the most of it.
And they might listen
because the others are not sick.
They're intoxicated
with health.
And you know that,
for yourself,
everybody experienced
that more or less,
when you're healthy,
you don't care,
when you get sick,
then you get all really worried,
and then you're,
oh,
and you got sick
because of your stupidity
or foolishness,
and then you make all those grand,
they think, oh,
never did that again.
And then you recover,
and then you're back
to the old ways
you completely forgot.
It's pure intoxication.
It's what you have at the time.
It's like,
complete,
like the mindfulness.
Absence.
And saying,
you make grand plans
and projects,
and ideas,
and hopes,
and whatever else,
just because you assume
you will live forever,
you assume your life
will last for a long time.
And if you stop
and think about that assumption,
it's completely gratuitous.
As every assumption is,
but this one,
it really can hit you.
So, as Buddha said,
even if somebody went for,
and they don't achieve anything,
but they don't disrupt the state,
they keep the rules,
and they keep trying to practice.
Even if they don't get anywhere,
even if they spend every single day,
for the rest of their life,
in tears, in pain,
imposed by the restraint,
it's still better than going back.
Why?
Because you've been around so long,
so many times,
it's spending
a third of your lifetime now,
crying in pain,
but holding that restraint,
will actually contribute much more,
than just giving in to the senses.
And then, at the same time,
we stop thinking,
well, it's impossible to spend every single day,
for the rest of your life,
in tears, in pain.
No matter how great that pain is,
it will fade.
But if you're ready for every single day of pain,
anything less than that will be a blessing.
And people, nobody likes this strain,
because it feels like a chore.
It feels like an effort.
And it feels like that,
only from the point of view,
where your sensuality feels effortless.
Now, the actual gratification of the senses,
might feel effortless,
but it never comes on its own.
It always comes with a price.
And it's not seeing the connection
between sensuality and gratification
and the price and the toll it takes.
You reflect on the connection long enough,
and it would become apparent
because it is there.
And then you realize,
it's much harder,
much more taxing,
much more,
much more of a chore,
to be following your senses,
and enjoying them,
then saying no to the whole thing.
But that connection needs to be well on long enough
until it becomes apparent,
because it's not apparent,
because if it were apparent so easily,
everybody would be free from sensuality.
And you can start with a simple reflection of,
if you are a layperson,
living a household life,
enjoying the pleasures of your senses,
means pleasant pastes,
touches sounds,
finding a pleasant wife,
or a girlfriend,
living a pleasant life.
How do you achieve that?
You need to work.
You need to earn.
You need to really
put up with stuff you don't like,
very often.
You might find the work you like,
you might be your own boss,
but then you have to protect it.
You have to fend off.
People who want the same.
People who cheated,
people who lie,
and people want to take things away from you.
So there's always that risk.
Then you're committing your life to it.
You're spending 90% of doing things
you don't want,
just so you get that 5% enjoyment.
It doesn't feel directly related to it,
and that's the ignorance,
obscuring it.
But if you realize that it's impossible
to have enjoyment,
without 95% of pain revolving around it,
directly or indirectly,
you realize that enjoyment is not worth it.
And that's when the Buddha talks about
seeing the danger
in the sensuality.
So by choosing to pursue
the ways of the senses,
which is basically choosing to have family,
children, wives or husbands,
whatever else,
living that kind of life,
you accept that whole central domain
with these things pertain,
with these things are,
which means you don't practice restraint,
but you practice pursuit.
And that's a form of commitment.
Pursuing your senses is a form of commitment,
but then you realize,
by accepting, by engaging in that pursuit,
you make yourself liable
to a great loss.
So say, you commit yourself to a pursuit
of having a family,
having children.
Well, now that you have family and children,
you have to work harder for them.
For the food, for the clothing, for the school.
What if they get sick?
What if they die on you?
You spent 20, 30 years,
cultivating, investing in those things,
dedicating your whole life,
praising your children,
then they turn away on you,
or they die, or an accident happened,
and they just snatched away
in a second,
and you have not had say in that
from the beginning.
Like, from the day one,
you have no say in the destiny of your child.
Well, you have no say in your own destiny,
but you have ignored that
when you decided to pursue the senses.
But if you reflect on that,
you realize that even the pursuit of the senses
is actually completely out of your hands.
That's why the suitors compare it to climbing a tree.
Oh, you see the ripe mangoes
on the tree, so you climb the tree
to eat them, to enjoy them.
And then somebody else while you're on top of that tree
comes, and he can't climb the tree,
so he decides to cut it.
While you're still on the top,
he doesn't see or he doesn't care.
You chop the tree, you fall down, break in there,
and you're done.
And pursue the senses
exposes you to that,
means going down, or climbing up the tree,
off a kind,
or the other,
and something might come at a direct cross-purpose
and just snatch it away from you.
Be it an accident, being other people,
being both.
Who knows?
The point is, the exposure is there.
So there is the inherent danger in that pursuit.
So you realize that danger is 95% of luck.
Easy worth risking your life,
putting your head on a chopping block
when there is a good chance of accident falling down,
just so you get that 5% thrill.
And in this worth,
that gratification is worth
for as long as you don't establish that connection
between the two.
I, for as long as you don't see the danger in centrality.
You establish the connection
and then the danger became apparent.
The visible.
The mind turned away.
Spear is the passion.
As the suit is described.
Oh, like the disgust became real.
This is danger.
This is not like mind turned away.
Never to go back to it.
Why?
Because it is like that.
Essentiality and gratification
would not inherently be dangerous
and risky,
and much more revolving around pain
in this satisfaction.
If it wouldn't be inherently that,
then it wouldn't be unholy.
And that certainly freedom from it would not be possible.
But because it is inherently dangerous, risky,
and not worthy,
it is inherently like that.
But dwelling on that freedom from it is possible.
And then you realize,
saying no as a formal restraint to centrality,
it's 5% of effort,
95% of peace,
and it's well worth it.
And that's when you find,
when a person finds pleasure over renunciation,
like actually you experience pleasure
by being, by recognizing strength
that you have of saying no,
not being you are stronger than senses,
senses are not stronger than you.
There's also a view that you will actually
through those challenges in life.
If you're having a family in the child,
you will get to know yourself.
Yeah.
You will evolve.
You will evolve in a way,
in a discovering different ways
of pursuing the senses.
But whether you evolve this way or that way,
bottom line is,
it's still within the nature of pursuing the senses,
and that's still within the nature of their danger and risk.
Does any evolving that you do
will be within that?
It's basically like going in a muddy swamp
and finding different ways
to wash yourself with a muddy water.
No matter how liberated your ways become,
it's still filled with water.
Means you'll never be clean.
Evolving the same way.
Evolving.
Like, you can be in prison.
In prison, behind a low door.
Sure, you can evolve in that environment.
Whatever evolving you do,
it will be evolving in the prison.
But you really want to be out of the prison.
It's better to be uninvolved out of the prison
than involved in very common sense in the prison.
Because that's not really involvement.
It's just a further proliferation.
And it's people say that they never say
for any other sense,
any other purpose than a purpose of justifying their pursuit
of the senses upon which they already decided.
But now they need to keep justifying it.
And sure, you can.
But you do that to others
because you might feel guilty,
or you might feel watched or judged.
So you justify yourself.
But basically,
that's done already when you're deeply committed to the senses.
So now you're just trying to make the best out of it.
Cover up any doubt in regard to your choices,
in regard to your commitment.
Above all, observe all the responsibility for it.
Oh, well, you know, I can't.
I can't go forth now because I have wife and children.
Well, they were not given to you,
like, you know, out of nowhere.
You've chosen that.
So basically what you're saying,
you can't go forth because of the choices you make.
And the choices that you're still accepting.
And that means you can't go forth
because you're choosing to not go forth.
That's it.
Oh, if you put it like that,
you realize I'm so responsible for them going forth,
for not practicing the Dharma.
So saying, oh, well, you evolve,
you grow as a fight by engaging in these challenges.
It's like, well, you really grow
by recognizing how to completely overcome those challenges
so they don't rise.
Why would you keep yourself in the environment
where those challenges will be coming the over?
It's silly.
Surely the wisdom is finding a place
that's free from any challenge.
But only a person who doesn't know how to free himself
from their challenges will say,
no, no, no, challenges are good.
They only say that because they don't know how to escape
and how to overcome them.
So they need to make himself feel important
or more valuable than they actually are.
I remember we spoke a while back about seeing an attractive thing.
I see.
We see an attractive object.
I can quite a bit.
It feels painful if I...
Yeah.
So if I see a beautiful woman
walking around in the city,
I don't try to drown this.
But I can see the beauty from the corner of my eye.
I don't have to look at it.
I can see it on the other side of the road.
And then I have to restrain myself.
But I was reflecting on the third of it.
That sign of beauty comes with pain somehow.
Yeah.
That's what I was saying before.
That sign of beauty is that which is painful.
It's not the restraint.
Yes, not the restraint.
Because when you say no to a prospect of pleasure
that it's pulling you,
whether it's a pleasurable sight,
sound, smell or any other sense,
it feels like the pain has a reason
because you said no.
You finally go with it.
No, the pain has a reason
because you've been yanked by that enemy
of that sense.
It's just usually you immediately go with it
so there is no yank.
Like as the leash starts pulling you,
you go with it.
So there is no tension created.
So you just feel smooth sailing
because you're just being driven.
When you start reflecting on it,
you sort of don't go instantaneously
and then there is a pain arising.
And you think, oh, this pain has a reason
because I didn't go immediately
with this animal that pulled me
and animal of sight.
But actually, no.
You go step further and you realize no.
The pain has a reason
because it's stupid.
The animal yanked me.
And for as long as I go with it,
it will keep yanking
because I'm allowing you to do it.
Same you take a dog on a leash
you let it yank your arm
and that's what I get used to.
So instead of going with it,
you invest the effort
to overpower that yank
so you actually control the animal.
And then eventually animal learns
it's pointless to yank.
I won't be let go when I am.
And then it listens.
And then it goes where you did it after to go.
But then that's what it is.
But that needs to...
So yeah, the inevitable...
Oh, I've been yanked.
It's because I didn't go with the animal as quickly
as I should have.
But no, you've been yanked
because the animal pulled you.
So you have to endure that initial pain
and also see through it
as not originating from you saying no
to the animal that started to run
with you holding on to its chain.
But it has a reason
because the animal is wild.
The animal is untrained, the animal ends.
The eye goes towards that...
Exactly. The eye goes for the sights.
And that's what...
So when there is a pain of a pleasurable sight,
it's because of the eye goes there
not because you're saying no to it.
And you stick to saying no to it
until eventually you overpower the eye
and it stops yanking here.
Because it realized it's pointless.
You know, you tie the dog
to a post.
It will yank and yank.
And then no, the post doesn't budge.
It doesn't break.
It will sit down and calm down.
And actually that's a super similar.
When you, like a strong post,
you tie this fire animals to the chain.
They will go wild and try to pull the rope.
When they come break it eventually,
they'll quiet down and sit down.
And then you can take them off for a walk
and they'll be there.
Let the training of the senses.
Because with the eye,
you're going into the city
where it likes pretty girls, beautiful women.
And like I said, now,
you can see that it's not yours
because you realize
that you're all of a sudden
you're looking at this pretty girl
on the outside of the road.
But the whole time, your attention,
your intention was, say,
you're looking at the pavement,
following you or whatever.
And then all of a sudden my head turns,
my vision turns to that specific thing,
which I can say.
I can say, yeah, that's attractive.
From the hundreds of people walking around.
We're not attractive.
We're not a joke.
I picked the one which I'm not even looking at.
I'm not attractive.
It's because my eye is not mine.
It's seen more than what I'm looking at.
The eye wants that.
The eye sees that.
And it's the same,
like the same,
the suit I was talking about yesterday,
when the weather asked the man,
what do you think,
which is more numerous,
things that you haven't seen
or things that you've seen.
Things that you haven't seen, obviously.
You use, because of that,
you abandon all the things that you've seen.
All the things that you will see
with always be less numerous
the things that are unseen.
Thus, but reflecting on that,
unseen, we can abandon
everything that you've seen
and you will see.
In the same sense,
which is more numerous?
Beautiful or ugly?
Ugly.
Out of 100 people,
you might find one or five attractive.
Yet,
there of the same material,
of the same make,
like 95 unattractive ones,
old, sick, aging,
overweights,
whatever,
things you don't find attractive,
they're more numerous
than the ones you pick as attractive.
So you realize
how circumstantial attractive this is,
and how random,
and how exactly,
nothing to do with you.
It's entirely your eye,
finding this circumstantially pleasing.
But you just run with it,
why because it pulls you?
Because you don't know any better.
And that's it.
So that's why
a protrusion that can free himself from sensuality.
Obviously,
there will be a lot of wisdom.
It's quite unlikely
that a protrusion of free from sensuality
that has come across
Buddha's teaching
wouldn't discern enough
to get the right view either.
Like, it's unlikely.
Because it's kind of along
the same way of abandoning assumptions.
But it is possible,
technically,
seeing they've never had
a protrusion,
it's possible, why?
Because those things are obvious.
Well, not obvious.
Sorry, those things can be discerned,
can be made obvious.
That is what's insured it is.
It's pain.
And by going with it,
you avoid the pain of the yank
or the pull.
Well, especially,
imagine if you're a weak little man,
have a massive
rot-weather,
or even some crossbreed,
and bull-master,
powerful dog.
Oh, you better go with it.
Because it will rip your arm out.
But when you go with it?
Well, exactly.
Go with it means
you're going to end up
in the places you don't want to be.
Yeah.
Inevitably.
You'll be dragged over things
just so you get a final satisfaction
while the animal wants.
But 95% of it,
you'll be dragged over thorns
and bushes and sharp rocks
and whatever else.
You have to put up with
just so you get that last moment of
life.
Oh, okay, I go with it.
And then another one.
So it's much better actually
to start developing your arms
so you can overpower the animal
rather than animal overpowering you.
It will take time,
but there's any other strength
development will,
physical and mental.
Yeah.
Everything takes time,
but it's worth it.
And in this case,
obviously,
pretending to the mind,
it's, well,
the benefits are immeasurable.
There's that,
one translation
in the 60-year fighter.
I don't know what to say about this,
but it's his guide.
Not guiding the doors,
well, guiding the doors of the
senses is quite good in there.
We said guiding the aperture
of the senses,
apertures.
I don't know.
It sounded quite nice,
because...
What was that?
A sutra.
Yeah, a sutra in the fighter.
Someone just translated
guiding the apertures
of the senses,
which just seems a bit more...
I don't know.
Because you can get that sense
or that sense of that door
of the senses.
Yeah.
That's all you're doing.
You're not trying to,
you're trying to be pulled into,
into this.
Yeah.
That sense of that door.
So it's not,
it's not like...
You can't just go 24-7
saying no,
go everything.
It's just going to collapse.
You can't,
you can't sustain that.
So you discern
when a dog is about to pull you,
when a wild animal of the senses
is about to pull you.
What direction is heading?
Olsum or an Olsum?
Olsum?
Fine.
Go.
Don't go too fast.
Don't let it yank you.
So, be mindful in other words.
Okay, you have to eat.
The animal of the taste
will inevitably enjoy it,
but you also have to eat.
So,
you do let the animal go and eat.
But you're mindful of it,
so make sure
it's not about enjoyment.
It's about eating.
But you don't go,
you don't have to go
for the wild music parties.
Or, you know,
even worse,
take drugs
or immoral sexual behavior
or who knows what else.
You don't have to do that.
So,
you don't let the animal go there.
If animal is used to going there,
which every animal is,
it will hurt saying no to that animal,
because it will keep yanking you.
You're yanking you.
But you do as well.
It can't yank me forever.
But if I do give in,
well,
it will end up yanking me for much longer.
And,
you have 95% of pain
revolving around it.
Being dragged out of your control.
And then you come up with a counter.
Once you, you know,
when you think yanks you,
if you stand your ground still,
you can withstand.
But if you give in,
when the animal picks up more pace,
more speed,
then it's much harder to stop.
Then you just have to wait for the crash
and hope to survive the crash,
and then restart again.
Oh, painful elephant,
like so many similes in the suit.
Power is there,
a pain,
in full control.
So,
this is in regard to yourself,
your own senses,
which means,
like, you know,
teaching an animal,
a dog,
training it,
training to listen to your voice.
Well,
it's identical.
You have to train yourself
to listen to your voice,
the voice of reason,
of wisdom,
of discernment.
Because, you know,
people know,
deep down,
you know,
whether you're just giving in,
or whether you're going about it.
As soon as you look,
you know.
That's right.
Because you know,
you feel guilty,
and that's where I need to come up
with those excuses
that, that time,
you just listed the people
who will often say,
ah,
it's a real great deal.
This is the real challenge.
There's no nonsense.
You do that only just to cover up
your sense of guilt
and response really.
You know deep down inside,
what are you doing,
whether you're doing what it's,
whether it's indulgent or not.
But it's awesome, right?
Awesome.
You just have to listen.
Learn how to listen to that.
Or rather,
you have to make that voice powerful
to override the pull of the senses.
So when that voice says no,
there is absolutely no debate.
The animals stay still.
And it's far from impossible.
This takes a method.
But everything takes effort.
Being yanked by an animal
takes effort,
it's indulgence.
Putting up with things.
And that's much worse
because you're not in control at all.
So sometimes it can take you down a way
that ends up fatal,
or much worse than what you anticipate
as people often do.
And that's based on sensuality.
But saying no,
and investing in training,
your mind to be stronger
than the senses,
is like,
well,
there's nothing dangerous about that.
All on the contrary.
Thus,
even if you spend your entire life
for the rest of your life in tears
and pain of restraint,
it's still more awesome
and more peaceful actually
than being driven around
by the fine wild animals.
Did you know?
You can teach them how to enjoy other things.
Well, that's the thing.
When they're prevented
from going wild
as far as they can,
then they started joining what they have.
What you give them.
Yes, sir.
That's how I work.
And that's actually,
there is another suit
where the Buddha says that
to a venerable ameluda,
just practice janas,
which is like the ultimate
establishments of your mind,
the strength,
which is developed.
Why?
Because if you develop janas,
then the course
rice that you're eating
will feel like the finest
hand-picked rice grains
from, you know,
the most,
the richest caries.
So the course rice
would feel the finest.
Why?
Because that's what you gave your mind.
And that's where your mind
got established.
And now it finds
tremendous contentment.
And that's it.
Contentment comes from the mind.
It doesn't come from
the prey that your animals chase
and hunt.
You prevent that.
Then they'll have to settle
with what they have.
And when they do,
then you have even more.
Then he said,
practice janas
because they,
the course hand probes
that you wear
will feel
will be perceived
as finest
Kashmir silk.
Practice janas
because sleeping
on the root of
three or cage
like this where we are now
will feel like
spending time
in the fully-plasted
mentions,
King's palaces.
Why?
Because the mind
determines
how it's going to feel
like.
Undeveloped mind
will need more
to get any sense
of gratification,
fully-developed mind
warning any
essential
to get sense of
content and gratification.
Which people work
for their whole lives.
They give you
all life,
sleeping, you know.
Having a boss
whom you hate
who is abusing you
to make you do things
you don't want,
colleagues you don't trust.
And you just have
your friends.
Well, like,
keep a living with your family
that you don't get on with.
They,
that's human life.
You spend your whole life
why?
For that
five percent of the
that they find
like itch,
just rickering the
itch open,
bleeding out.
But having
a little sense of
gratification of
scratching it,
to scratch,
just a bit.
Ignoring 95% of the
mess you're creating
just because they're
tiny little scratch.
And then,
compared that to the pleasure
of somebody
whose itchy wounds
have healed completely
and it feels
nowhere to whatsoever
at all
ever again.
You can't even compare it.
Are you right about
that?
Yeah.
I mean, I was thinking
the other day too,
and when I'm meeting
these British bulls
and like,
this
brown rice and all of that,
I'm enjoying it
far much better than
anything I used to have.
In the earlier times,
I went to
the...
Well, you can see that.
Like, you can see it.
You know,
when you have a plate full
of a table full of different
plates of food,
and you just, you know,
go for the ones
really you like,
and the mind gets overly
excited all the way.
You kind of get
some enjoyment,
but it's not
the same as if like,
when you're like this
in the middle of the jungle,
no village inside,
nothing,
and then you have some
plain food,
but that's all you have.
It feels much
more gratifying
and satisfying
than when you have a full
plate full table of
all sorts of plates and stuff.
When you're just so concerned
about picking the word
exactly what you want,
if you don't end up
really
appreciating anything.
It will, if you
if you only eat
when you're hungry,
I mean,
whatever you eat.
Exactly.
If you only eat
when you're hungry,
whatever you eat,
you'll enjoy it.
Yeah, if you can drink it.
Like, if you just try
to fast drink
two days.
Then,
then like, you know,
the plainest
cream crack is
well, you know,
when you haven't
been eating for days.
So it's just like
how far your animals
have proliferated.
How far they
you got used to going.
As I say, you have a
wild dog.
He's just used to
running around
wherever he wants.
But you can't expect him
to be content
sitting in one spot.
He won't.
He will be
angry,
mad.
But he will come down.
Training.
That's why
the suit is off to
about training.
Training yourself.
They're becoming
a master of your sense of
him.
And it's not
which we need to be
then you become a
master of your life.
Well, then wisdom is
easy.
You're not being
distracted,
pulled around,
controlled by your
senses.
Insight is just
the matter of time.
So,
you're not
being distracted,
pulled around,
controlled by
your senses.
Insight is just
the matter of time.
Yeah.
You start to see
way more things.
Is it obvious?
Then you need
very little instruction.
You don't need a
PhD or a degree of
listening.
A job.
Work yourself up.
Get out.
Because you've got
your senses already.
Well, the senses
got you.
Changing it
around.
So,
you're not
being distracted.
You're not being
distracted.
So,
you're not being
distracted.
You're not being
Well, yeah.
All the
pursuits were
the ambitious stuff
comes through the
senses.
Through wanting more
for your senses.
You know,
later on security,
safety,
all of that comes
comes through
being controlled
by the senses.
Living on that
domain,
where those
animals control
you and
pull you around,
pull you apart
as they please.
So, sometimes people
it, some restraint, just don't run out just now, wait, because then you can run further
later, but it still pertains to the same round, same yank, same pull by the same animal
with the same chain. So you really want to start addressing the nature of being pulled
by your senses. In other words, you really want to start addressing the unwholesome pull
and then controlling the wholesome ones. And you address that then it becomes apparent
that it was never you who was going after sights. It couldn't have been you because sights
pertain to your eyes. That's why it's called Salayatuna, 6th sense space. Then you have
the 5 senses and in the sutras they refer to as fields, which means these fields are
where these sights run and pertain to, which means your eyes goes after the sights. By
being constantly pulled, you just stop, you don't even see that. All you see is me and
the stuff around sights around. So you end up appropriating, you end up thinking you
are those animals. But you start distinguishing yourself, there is no sight without this
fleshy organ of my eyes, inconceivable to have sights, to see sights, even eyes. Same for
any other of the 5 senses, inconceivable without the corresponding sense. So if you think
inconceivable without which means it's inseparable from, it's fully determined by, it's fully
bound by, it's fully made by that, which means you and your senses self is completely redundant.
And that can be discerned even when you are not free from sensuality. But imagine how
easy that would be to discern when you are not being driven around by those animals.
Then you just see, hey, I have no interest in this at all and now I have proven that to
myself, I have confirmed it to myself, better world than proven, I have confirmed for myself
that I have no interest in it because I am in control, not the animals. And all you see
is just pathetic animals trying to run left and right. And then even they will come down
eventually. And then it becomes apparent, yeah, this was not mine to begin with. Because
if it were yours, you would have say in it, if it were yours, those eyes would not be
subject to destruction, subject to sickness, subject to death. You wouldn't, but they are,
which means it's all yours. You can't have it both.