And again, I don't dare to tradition it, but in the West, it's the same.
It's just in regard to different things, maybe more specific views as opposed to generic tradition.
But it's the same.
If you get very upset, you point out, and the fact that you get upset on account of your downward view,
if you don't see that as a big problem, as there's nothing else you can really discuss with that person.
Yeah, I can get upset, you know, you find me, you kick my doll, you do this, you do that.
But if you disagree with my downward views, if that bothers me,
it means, well, those are not the views of downward, it's that simple.
But yeah, it's remarkable, how far people would go.
Kind of knowing that, but ignoring it.
You know what I mean?
Yeah, people hold to views so strong, and in the West, definitely as much as any place.
Yeah, yeah.
And it means that how strong this objective, this type of attitude is.
But maybe in America, especially, because it's like a sensualism.
I think it's Western culture generally, because any of these individuals write the education,
mainly, the way you grow up, the way you're taught in schools and stuff,
you just end up being, and no doubt, involuntarily, they're not aware of it themselves.
But you end up being channeled in the direction of that kind of objective sort of materialistic view,
whereby, you know, if you really commit to it, you come to a point where you think your thoughts don't exist.
That's not the real thing. The real thing is only thing that is accessible to five senses,
things that you can see.
If you were to stop and think about what the senses are, you'll get very confused.
So you wouldn't do it, you'll just keep going forward into the things, into the science, into the other things.
Are there in the world, basically?
Which is all based on the assumption that the world is there, independent of you.
Yeah.
Which is the wrong assumption, because, you know, either the assumption, you need to exist first.
So it's a contradictory assumption.
And that was the main, like, a line of existentialism, such as existence precedes the essence.
That's just the big, you know, whatever, whatever.
I think it takes us, we need to come back to this first principle, that existence precedes the essence.
So you can't provide explanation, you can't develop an external view that will sort of then in return define your existence.
Or something, why? Because you need to exist first, in order to do any of that.
Which means that's all secondary, which means you cannot stand for existence.
Obviously, they couldn't go further than that.
That's a huge change that happened to me, you know, to be honest.
It just twisted everything around suddenly.
These things make more sense to this world.
I thought it was so real.
And I'm just, you know, one little thing in this world that's real is,
I know the world through my own, through experience.
So, experience is more fundamental than the objects that I'm really just creating a model of a world that I might experience.
Yeah, it's determined.
Inasmuch, the objects of your senses define the domain of your sense.
In that sense, they are also determined by those senses now.
So, you know, if your eyes are not working on limited or whatever,
they will limit the whole domain, the whole world of vision.
Everything you've ever seen, everything you will see, everything you see.
Same with any other sense.
And it is just that little material organ.
Sitting in the world, same as that cup, same as that bin, same as the stone, eyes.
But as Annabella said, causing that sort of thing.
Well, yeah, it's like that.
It's just that they have this privileged position of, it's an object in the world,
because of which there are objects in the world, because of which you see objects in the world.
But it's an object in the world.
So, the practice is really to remove that privilege from your senses, from your sense-bases.
And which is why whenever they've described, they've described in that kind of external terms,
as a fresh eye in organs and so on, because that's what they are.
They can't be more than that.
That's the instrument in the world by which you are the perceiver and the conceiver of the world.
I think this weird thing happening in this minute, I'm not used to meditating so much,
so I don't know if it probably doesn't mean anything, but that's a couple of days.
When my eyes are open and unseen things, sometimes it feels like I'm not looking,
I'm not seeing objects, I'm seeing images of objects.
Well, that can be, I mean, a computer screen or something.
Yeah, well, for as long as, when you say you're seeing images of objects,
the objects that are now pushed in a background are not regarded as more real or more fundamental
than the images of them that you see.
Because that's the problem that the assumption can kind of take up anything in that sense.
Oh, these are just images. Well, if you say, well, your mind comes first,
and people can get the hint of that, that the mind basically determines the experience as such,
internal or external, but because just that kind of little taste, little glimpse of that insight, so to speak,
the assumption takes it up and then you kind of overshoot the mark and then you end up
everything is in my mind, like solipses or no idea, the world is just in me,
but you don't exist just in my head, kind of thing.
But that you can see that being remotely rooted in something that resembles the truth,
but actually they overshoot them and I was just a view that misrepresents.
So if you see the images of objects, well, that's what's real for you at a time of seeing.
So then the background of the objects just becomes another possibility of those objects.
In other words, the objects now that are pushed to the side because you've seen the image,
become possibility away that those objects can appear again.
Because now you see them as images, and you see them as non-image, you see them as the real object,
they're just their modes of manifesting, and they're all equally real as such in their own domain.
So it's not that the real objects are more real than images,
because if you stop and you worry, even the real object is a metal image.
Not entirely, it's founded upon the four great elements,
but if that image is not there, you wouldn't be able to even designate it as an object.
You just couldn't.
And that is actually again, that can be a very good practice,
even the external things, the things that clearly define the things that you access through your senses,
to start recognizing the mental presence in them,
and not just default to an assumption that they are solid objects out there,
the way you see them in the scene.
So it doesn't mean that there is a hidden reality behind them,
they're real, whichever way they appear,
but you can't even conceive the idea of appearance if it's not mental.
Right.
If it doesn't take, at least to some extent, in a domain of mental and mentality.
There has to be some, yeah, all that other stuff.
Today I had a strange thing,
or the meditation has been very mild, I think,
because tired or something.
Today my mind is wandering a bit, and I would have like an image just popped in my head,
in this case, it was like a bullet ice cream.
And all it wants, all together, the image, the intense image,
and then sort of the awareness that I was aware of it,
and then this flame of desire, you know, craving,
and then pleasure, strong pleasure.
And it just sort of push all at once,
and three, four, five seconds later, it just disappeared.
You know, and I went on to something else,
but that was very interesting,
and I started to play with that a little bit,
because it was not an overwhelming kind of loss.
But there was one reason it was interesting,
is because I could really feel the feeling,
the pleasure of feeling, and a lot of things.
Well, there was the pure kind of example of delight,
sensual delight, which is entirely mental.
Your senses, they recognize agreeable and disagreeable,
the five senses, and with a said, they're like five animals,
they have their domains, they want to feed in grounds,
how they call them, and they want to go after
what they like to eat, so to speak.
So the eyes go out the pleasant sights,
but that's only to a certain extent,
the actual notion of sensuality,
and the delight in central pleasures.
That's what keeps you bound to them.
It's not that the existence of the five senses is the problem.
So, and that's when you start to recognize,
by seeing that delight, how actually,
it's the mental take on pleasure,
the associated with the senses,
that keeps you kind of enslaved to them,
not the actual plane.
So, Arahand Kuddi, the nice, his favorite one,
but he will not induce their mental delight anymore.
That doesn't mean that he won't feel any pleasure
of that pleasant agreeable taste,
but for the arising, for the ceasing,
and for the persisting of that pleasure,
at any time, he won't feel any delight,
associated with it.
And that's another thing that comes down to what I said,
when you have to start recognizing the mental image,
the presentation, the dharma, basically.
In your thoughts, n, in things that you access through your senses,
because they are determined as such,
because of the mind.
So, if you recognize the image in any ice cream,
and then the real ice cream,
they're having common that they both appeared mentally.
In a way, as a presentation of an ice cream,
as an image of an ice cream,
as a phenomenon of an ice cream,
and that's where the practice needs to pertain.
So, it can't pertain just to you,
originally, like dismissing your thoughts,
or just thinking, or thinking this in response to that,
or whatever.
Nor can it pertain only to that which concerns the senses.
No, just say no to everything.
Just do not engage in any agreeable sense experience
it's not necessarily central, because it will miss the point.
But if you fear mind on the level of that mental presentation,
that dharma, that phenomenon,
that's in common to both,
then you'll be free from both whichever it is,
whether you think about an ice cream,
or you're actually eating the ice cream,
it will not induce delight,
which is that which keeps you bound,
which is why its centrality is unwholesome.
Yeah, because usually people are saying,
ah, thinking is the problem,
because when I think about it,
I'll get all bound up,
so I'll stop thinking about it.
But then, yeah, you might do that one,
but you won't be always able to stop thinking about it,
and then when you do come,
because ice cream, you just,
well, they won't be much restraint.
Even if you're restraint,
even if you're just moderate,
and you just eat one spoon a day,
still, you eat that one spoon a day with delight.
Even if you eat no spoon at all,
you will have delight in the experience.
Which is why a satisism,
per se, is wrong,
when people just,
the simile of the deer,
the herd,
and imagine what I think in the beginning fourth,
fifth shooter,
when it says,
the first group of deer,
eats the bait,
the maralais,
and where they just eat it.
They don't think well.
Because that maralais does whatever he wants.
The second group of deer,
they see the first group,
and then they blame the bait,
so then they completely shun the bait,
and they run into the mountains,
when there's no bait around to provoke them.
But after a while,
their energy, you know, goes down,
not enough food,
then they come back,
and they eat the bait,
unwarily.
And then the third group sees the third group,
and says, well, what if we stay among the bait,
but eat carefully?
And then,
they do that,
and then the mara,
the hunter comes,
and he sees the bait eaten,
but nothing is caught on the bait.
So he can't see those deer anymore.
They come and eat his bait,
but he can't catch them.
So then,
then it says in the suit,
so then the mara decides to leave them alone,
not try to harass him further,
in case he harasses them further.
They'll start telling everybody else
how to avoid his bait.
And then,
it's a comparison to,
kind of, obviously,
essentially, Dalgons,
and then the formal set,
which is, kind of,
a default mode for many monks,
and many people,
all this volume,
you know, just kind of determination,
and just say no to everything.
And you can spend your whole life doing it.
And, you know, you might not be, kind of,
wearing a, going around naked,
like, does a set,
or wearing a good bag,
or sleeping in thorns,
and torturing yourself.
But the fact that your mental attitude,
denies the bait,
blames the bait,
means,
you're not escaping it.
Yeah, you're still hooked on it.
Yeah, exactly.
And it's impossible, really,
for anyone in our heart,
as well, to,
you can't,
not have experience,
pain and pleasure.
That's true.
And so that's what I mean.
That's the,
the wisdom of Finara
is found in a completely different direction,
or in the middle direction,
which is basically,
saying yes to the bait,
saying no to the bait.
What does it have in common?
Any of these reactions.
It has in common,
the phenomenon of the bait.
If I free my mind
in regard to the phenomenon of the bait,
if I see it as in permanent,
as disagreeable,
and as something that cannot be appropriated,
and practice the long enough,
whether you're among the bait,
or without the bait,
you'll be fine.
Because there was never a problem.
Right.
Who would say,
that's what delight is.
Hmm.
Thinking that it's.
Well, delight, you can do.
It's actually,
it's delight.
Delighting in the idea
of engaging in something
with your senses,
whether it's this pleasant taste,
pleasant sight, pleasant delight,
and allowing your mind
to be overtaken by that,
means you're delighting.
If falling into it,
means you're.
Well, it means you're,
you're, you're hooked onto the bait.
So, but if you remove the delight,
the bait can stay.
It can be right in front of your face,
if you're not pressured into biting it.
And you, you remove that by understanding objects.
Well, no, by understanding both.
It's your sense.
By understanding the phenomena
that's in common,
to the objects,
whether externally,
internally or internally,
externally.
Understanding what appears.
Phenomenological, yes.
Not explaining it
in terms of, oh,
this is only permanent,
this ice cream, you know,
it's going to melt,
it's going to disappear in the sun,
it's never real.
No.
An image of an ice cream,
an image of pleasant taste,
an image of a pleasant sight,
pleasant touch,
that enchants.
That has in common,
in your mind,
with the actual image,
even if you're not actually looking at somebody
or something,
eating something,
those things are,
so you don't need exposure
to centrality in order to define centrality,
because it's defined by your mind.
So, you actually need to draw from it
in order to see that,
like the main,
the main reason for being centrally bound
is your mind,
your mental assumption,
in regard to it.
Then you approve that,
and then it's fine,
even if you have things right
up front to you.
So,
it comes down to,
being able to either think,
or directly experience
through the senses,
a pleasant thing,
and not be taken by it,
being able to think,
or directly experience the senses,
unpleasant thing,
and not feel aversion towards it,
in terms of this kind of pressing
need to get rid of it.
How would I look to you?
Extends down to what we spoke before,
about the neutrophilic,
which is where people,
well, people don't see it.
So, usually that's what's associated
with boredom or the indolence.
So, you need excitement,
or you need,
well, you need anything, really.
So, when you don't feel anything,
you don't want to be resting
on that feeling either.
And that's the important bit.
That's a subtle one.
Yeah, it's a form of delight.
I earned this rest.
You did.
You might have earned physical rest,
but you've never earned,
unless you're another
mental rest.
And by mental rest, I mean,
giving in.
Like, when they both together,
similarly, of cow,
with open wounds,
if it lays on the ground,
it's eaten by the insects on the ground.
If it lays on the tree,
or a wall,
it's eaten by the insects,
they live there.
So, whatever,
whatever it chooses to,
whew, rest just for a second,
it's being eaten by that.
That's the attitude you need to develop.
Mentally.
Obviously, people, again,
they overshoot
the assumption of the mind.
And so, you end up thinking,
it's just this constant tension
that you have to live through.
But it's not.
You can set your body to sleep.
Feed it.
Take it for a walk.
Send it for a swing, whatever.
Mentally, don't rest upon any of those actions.
And don't rest,
means, don't lose mindfulness
in regard to it, basically.
Don't let your mind overtake it.
And you forget about yourself.
And then you really
are taken by what you're doing.
Even if it's not unwholesome.
It's unwholesome for that reason.
So, that's how you approved the delight.
Because if you can notice,
if your mind remains unwavered
in regard to that subtle,
neutral feeling,
doesn't eat anything,
doesn't require anything,
doesn't run away from anything.
The pressure arises,
you'll be able to leave it alone.
Because the pleasure of the senses,
the delight is mental,
in regard to the central pleasure.
But one thing you can recognize
is that, no matter how great
that central pleasure might be,
it can never ever be anything more
than was defined by your sense organs.
It can be the greatest taste.
It's still a taste.
It's still dependent on the tongue.
And it can never be more than that.
It can be the most beautiful sight in the world, again.
When you forget that it's fully determined
by the pair of flesh-y eyes,
you can have the whole image
in the drum and the apprehension,
the expectation and the realization
of this great spectacle.
Because you lost sight of yourself
completely taken by it.
But if you know,
whatever you see,
whatever you hear,
whatever you taste, touch,
smell,
it can never be more than that.
So, in scene,
let it just be seen,
you heard,
let it just be heard.
And so, that's basically what it is.
It comes down when you recognize that,
again,
the entire spectrum
of sense objects,
no matter how great it is,
let's write up down any direction,
it's fully determined.
It cannot kind of step outside
even a millimeter
out of the sensor of the domain,
which is a six-cent base,
which is something that the translation
like the fields,
the senses are like the fields for these things,
it cannot be more than that ever.
Why?
Why then?
If I...
But not knowing it cannot be more than that,
you delight at the prospect
of being more.
And that's mental.
Because they delight,
can pull you,
push you,
make you pursue the senses,
but in the end,
all you're going to get is sense
and it's object.
And I agree with it,
which is why usually people
are giving into the desires like,
oh, was that all?
The expectations are always high,
because that's how the mind,
that's how the delight works.
And it's nothing unusual about it,
it's actually quite normal.
But obviously not knowing that,
you associate that delight,
that is mentioned
with this prospect
of that sensual desire
and fulfillment,
feeling to see that
that delight takes you
in the domain of that sense
that has its own scope.
So eyes cannot experience
more anything more than sights.
ears cannot get you anything more
than pleasure of a sound.
So whether the greatest
most refined is still a sound.
The thing with pleasure
is the feeling of perception.
If you think of eyescream,
there's a pleasant feeling.
Every time you think of eyescream,
there's a pleasant feeling
every single time.
There seems to suggest
in a mind that there is
something there.
Well, the pleasure is real.
But why is it always connected
with a particular perception
or image?
Well, it can be random.
It can be circumstantial,
because you try to eyescream
and you really like it.
Because there is such a thing
as a pleasant taste by default.
But the problem is,
your question,
why is this connected?
Assumes that the connection
between the two somewhere,
somewhere inside,
of the sense objects.
So if you kind of unravel it all,
then you will be able to kind of
cut those wires,
and it will not be,
that's not enough.
The problem,
the question you asked
is a symptom
that you were already affected
by the perception of eyescream.
It's your response
to the fact that you don't want
this cave
from the eyescream.
You don't know the gratification
in that regard.
You don't recognize the danger,
and you don't see the escape from it.
Hence, why?
Hence, yes.
Hence, no.
Hence, maybe.
Hence, yes and no.
Any of those acts
are just response,
your ways of responding to the fact
that you are already touched by that,
but that phenomenon.
You are taking back.
Because whatever,
whatever is perceived,
there is a feeling.
There is always a feeling.
Feeling perception.
Yes.
So,
you are trying to do it.
You are trying to separate them,
so you are not affected by any more.
The thing is,
you have to go the other way.
And by the other way,
I mean,
by seeing the perception
and feeling are inseparable.
And the dear eyes on their own
means,
well, you can wander
for the rest of your life.
Why is the thought
of ice cream always pleasant?
Oh,
you can just accept that.
And instead of questioning that,
try to find a place
whereby you don't care.
And by that,
I mean,
you don't care
not in a sense you can order it,
but in a sense,
perception of pleasant ice cream
doesn't bother me anymore.
It doesn't touch me anymore,
it doesn't command me anymore.
It doesn't make me do things anymore,
it doesn't make me think things anymore.
Cannot overtake me.
And then,
you might wonder,
why is it pleasant
or you might not wonder that?
But there will be relevant.
Because the only reason you wonder
is that now,
is because you do realize,
you do recognize the problem
of being pulled by your senses.
So, your question,
is kind of trying to solve it.
But if you actually solve it,
the proper way,
questions become,
but it doesn't.
Because it's not,
why is it always pleasant?
You should really ask yourself,
why,
why am I being touched by that?
By that image.
By that pleasure.
Why am I being,
why is it controlling me?
Why is it better
if I'm,
well, if I get already,
so to speak,
why is it better
if, if I find a way,
where that pleasure
cannot access me?
You think about that,
and you will start to recognize the danger.
You will start to recognize the gratification,
and gratification is what I was speaking about.
Not knowing gratification means
confusing your delight,
with the actual,
like, central consumption.
And you recognize that,
not matter how great the light is,
gratification remains confined
to the domain of a particular sense.
It's inconceivable for it to be anything more,
despite what your delight makes you expect.
The pleasure of a sight
cannot be experienced
by anything other than your eyes.
So you recognize,
ah, that's the extent of gratification.
There is no more.
Then you recognize the danger as well.
Expecting more.
Well,
through that expectation of more,
you blindly jump back
into those domains
that are not yours.
You're going between the eye and sight.
You're going between the nose
and smells, ears,
and sounds.
And basically, it's just like running
in the middle of a motorway,
which is not yours,
but you don't know it.
So you just run right in the middle,
and then something will hit you sooner or later,
which is what it will compare,
giving you the sincerity,
like, putting your head on a chocolate block,
where the X falls,
and it will fall.
It's not yours.
Neither that perception
nor that feeling.
So if you're wondering why,
how did that come about?
It means you already took it as mind,
which that's where it must take it.
Not finding out the answer
to those particular questions.
So you can't help.
You can't just stop
and will the opposite.
I will not engage in sensuality anymore.
Well, I guess you could do that
if you develop genres,
and then through them,
you could think that,
and then you could stand
for that determination.
But otherwise,
you have to recognize
gratification,
the danger.
Why is it dangerous
if I give in?
And that will offer
the sight of escape.
Ah,
if I remove the delight,
in this,
nothing to gather the whole world,
just in this particular sense,
in these five senses.
So you're not chasing after every object,
you remove the delight in the eye,
because of which,
you delight in the sight.
But if you recognize
it's fully confined to your eyes,
fully confined to your ears,
you remove the delight in regard to that,
and you're like,
oh, okay, I'm free from this,
because no matter how much it arises,
it can never sort of,
well, go behind me
and kind of scoop me out again
as he used to do.
Which is why there,
there's a similar in the suitters,
when the Buddha compares,
well, somebody is free from sensuality,
it leaves like, like,
a drop of water on the blade,
on a sharp blade,
but it's not cut bad.
Because the five senses, basically,
entirely, which means
your whole world really,
is not actually yours,
it belongs to the mind.
The eyes in your head,
ears, nose, tongue,
body, everything.
Anyway, it's easy,
it's not just mouth,
stasis, and so on.
It's not yours.
Never would.
I'm realizing again that,
it marries the detour,
well,
those things are,
as I've been around,
undetermined,
those, those bases.
What do you mean?
Well, when he,
you don't have to take service here.
No, his mind becomes undetermined.
Or each is the undetermined.
The undetermined.
Those things are just senses.
Well, the determinations have ceased,
they don't become the undetermined.
They just cease to act as determinations.
The determinations of his self.
To just another way of saying,
he stops taking it as his.
And they have ceased.
He let, he leaves them be.
They have ceased.
Seists to exist as me and mine
and determining me and mine.
So that's what the undetermined is.
Because if there wouldn't be undetermined,
freedom from the determined
would not be possible.
But because there is the undetermined,
freedom from the determined is possible.
So the island doesn't create anyone.
He just kind of finds a way
to step into it.
Because it's already there.
The undetermined.
And you step to it
through developing full knowledge of it.
There is absolutely not a way.
Another question was related to this.
For the wrong question.
That everything seems to,
obviously things seem to correspond to each other.
Like a sight, a sound,
you know, a sight of a river,
a sound of a river,
a touch of a river,
all that.
You know, a correspondence.
Yeah.
I can feed it.
I mean, I can touch it.
You can experience it through different senses.
Yeah.
So they correspond.
So it's very easy to assume that it's,
there's that one thing out there.
The river.
That's what the river said.
Either things usually appears
itself when it's seen twice,
either in reflection,
or experience simultaneously
through two different senses or more.
Yeah.
Then they conclude,
like, it's effortless.
That's what ignorance means going with the grain.
That's the grain.
Or the direction of the stream.
So you go against it.
If you were to practice correctly,
you're against holding it apart.
Well, you go against it by,
by full understanding, really.
There's a method or something.
By full understanding,
they each domain,
each sense,
if that's what your approach is.
It would be, well, it wouldn't be,
inducing the sense of self anymore.
And you said, actually,
the self disappears.
When a thing is seen twice in reflection,
or experience through two different senses simultaneously,
it's the self of that thing,
the self identity of the same thing
that you hear and that you see.
Oh, it's the same thing.
That same is,
be neither in what you see,
nor do what you hear,
I, it's in me.
Oh, it's the same self thing.
Myself is experiencing the same as of these things.
Myself is.
Myself is independent of any other thing
that I experience through my sense.
That's how it kind of goes.
I'm using these senses to access these things.
Yeah, their mind.
So you, you, you will have to be able,
which is what I, what I mean,
when I talk about the,
the simultane,
or the principle of simultaneity
and the notes of meditation.
When you simultaneously hear,
see something.
If your mindfulness is established properly,
you'll be aware of it as too independent,
but simultaneity is the mains.
So they don't actually meet any of the senses ever on their own.
They will kind of come together in your mind,
but in their own domains,
like, well, as I said,
in other words,
they've got to find it indifferent to each other.
It's just not even a,
like, there is not even awareness
in your hearing,
in your hearing of your sight.
It's inconceivable.
Because having awareness of your sight,
in your hearing,
would be, well,
your sight appears in your hearing,
even as a possibility,
even as some,
as a different,
and that seems inconceivable,
which doesn't exist.
Which is why you have five consciousnesses
in regard to five senses,
and then six ones.
So you have six types of consciousness.
You know, when I...
Always.
When if I see something here,
something,
and also touch and experience...
Imagine six layers
of your experience.
But...
Symbol tenures.
This stuff seems like there is
a pain-different attention
from this center here.
From one.
You give...
You still have the assumption
of me and myself as the core.
Or your experience.
When you have to keep developing mindfulness
as long as it's necessary,
and then, well, as I said before,
when you feel that core,
you can't start straight
onto the senses now.
The contemplation I'm talking about.
They can come later.
It gives us to suffer.
So now you would have to take up the experience
as a whole,
and include in that sense of core,
that sense of center,
which is sense of me and I are,
as a phenomenon,
as a peripheral phenomenon,
without making it actual.
All that we spoke before.
Because by including it,
bit by bit,
you become aware of it.
So then,
the time will come when you recognize,
well, if I'm aware of it,
means it appears as a phenomenon,
which means it will cease as a phenomenon,
which means it can possibly be me,
or anything related to me,
in any way.
It's just a thought.
Well, just everything is just a thought.
It's not a sight.
It's an image.
Oh, yeah, the sense of stuff.
Yeah, yeah.
It's independent of the senses,
which is how it has that
assumed privileged position over then.
But if you stop and think as we spoke before,
this body here,
this physical body right here,
which basically covers up the basis
of the senses,
the five senses,
and then the experienced general experience
as at all,
in my sense of self,
or whatever else,
would that be conceivable
in any shape or form
if this physical body
is to be destroyed
next instance?
He wouldn't.
So then,
the privileged position
and attitude is slowly being undermined.
But you have to keep doing it.
And then you can,
you're not even denying
the sense of privilege of you.
No, you include it.
So you make sure it gets undermined
with the right,
with the right setup,
with the right insight,
with the right reflection.
Which is why,
in the Anapala Saksata,
I will breathe in like this.
I will breathe,
so you're,
keep including yourself.
You keep including yourself
in the next breath,
in this breath.
Now, do it like this.
So you include in your very
volition,
and intention,
while you're seeing it clearly,
it even the most,
the strongest willed thing,
the most determined thing,
well, could have never been yours
to begin with it.
Absolutely.
There simply no room
for itself.
And not just there's no room,
it's unnecessary at all.
Which is why there is no room for it.
Because that's a,
you see the breath is intentional.
Hmm.
So you,
you've paid attention to the breath.
You find that it's really
intending.
Well, you can find it,
but as long as you include
your sense of self,
in regard to it,
what happens is people
would kind of forget about
itself,
and then it will be our breathing
that happens.
Oh, it's this thing breathing me
or it's this body really.
All that is,
you can say that,
it's not inaccurate,
but the fact that you left
a sense of self out of it,
means you're not really
addressing the problem.
It's like getting the
decent medicine,
but applying it over a
cover-up wound.
So it doesn't actually reach
the point where it's
supposed to be active.
So you keep including
your sense of self.
You keep bringing it forward.
You're not letting it
kind of wiggle out,
which is the same,
the combination of
discraft to you,
when you recognize,
okay, this body is right
here, right now,
in this situation,
in this position,
in this shape of form,
fully material,
entirely,
composed of elements.
There's absolutely nothing
in this body
that doesn't pertain
to one of the four
great elements.
So it's a hundred percent
object,
because of which
your thinking of what objects are,
and that right reflection
while you're thinking,
stands there,
because of that
random object,
like that kettle,
like that bottle,
like that cup.
So if something happens to it,
on that material level,
in which you have no axis,
at all,
you realize nothing can
remain standing,
even the greatest sense of
self.
So establish your mind
upon that,
and by establishing your mind
I mean, in the beginning,
you have to keep bringing it up,
then you fall from
that,
but then you bring it up,
and that thought,
that perception,
of that relationship,
stays.
Means, ah,
the mind is established
to the degree.
Keep it.
When you lose it,
you have to keep it.
Good one, say that,
you recognize in that,
in this sense of self,
this sort of derivative,
like the different senses,
sort of different senses
pointing to that one focal point,
and then recognizing that,
this, the,
impermanence of,
of the sense,
is a way to get to realize
that, that sense of self,
which is derived from,
is, um,
not solid,
not solid.
It can be,
for as long as you,
uh, first acknowledge,
that focal point,
because it's real,
as such,
and it's there.
Because usually people
would result,
the contemplation of impermanence
of,
a kind,
to obscure,
or to deny,
or to cover up,
or to remove,
that focal point.
Uh, but that's,
that's the result.
If it's there,
then,
it has a reason.
Whatever has a reason,
means you want to rise.
This is no interference
with that.
So,
if you were to comprehend
impermanence like that,
yeah,
it will point out that
this focal point
is not,
well,
it cannot be taken as me,
in mind,
because it's fully dependent,
upon these external,
organs,
they have no control over.
But that can become very,
only after,
that focal point has been acknowledged,
as phenomena,
because people often get,
too quick,
to say,
there's no self.
There is no self,
no self,
no self.
There is self.
There is focal point.
It's not yours.
That's what no self is.
It's like throwing out the self,
throwing out the whole problem,
and,
yeah,
like a scientist,
just,
just your objective,
exactly,
you're ignoring the problem.
Yeah.
So, that's what meant
before,
it's not possible,
meditation here today.
Whatever,
you include that.
It's the same principle.
Whatever,
it has a reason.
Like,
trying to exclude it,
is a mistake,
just for that very reason.
Because you have no say
over things arising,
because if you would,
well,
there would be a sense of self there.
But they manifest,
when they manifest.
And if you stop,
trying to interfere with it,
if you recognize that,
whatever has a reason,
you will see that,
for those already reasons,
of simple rising,
that's why,
if you have to cease,
not for anything else.
And that's what impermanence is.
So, impermanence,
actually,
is in the rising of things,
not like looking,
waiting for the destruction
to prove that they're impermanent.
Now, they're impermanent
because you're experiencing that.
And to recognize that,
whatever is arising,
it's complex,
it's like an integrated system,
and everything integrated
has to descend to it.
Well,
it's not even that,
like that's,
that's another designation
that you will put on top.
System integrated or simple,
or whatever.
The most accurate you can get
is saying,
it has a reason.
It is.
That's it.
And that's the most accurate phenomenon.
And you don't have to go for,
well, you can't actually go further than that.
Because any other,
more elaborate explanation,
would be sort of going back down,
and then provide an explanation for it.
And an explanation,
even if it's the other pleasing one,
is still an explanation.
So it has to,
it has to be recognized on that general level,
where it just arises.
And for that very reason,
it's impermanent.
It will have to cease.
You have no say in its manifestation,
which is why,
it will cease.
That's it.
When that's recognized,
then everything,
whether it's particular or general,
is seen through that principle.
And the sense,
and the very sense of self,
arises depending on these things.
Yes, they arise.
So then you recognize,
because you recognize principle,
then you got to anything,
that manifests.
For that reason,
it's impermanent.
You, well,
yourself manifests.
And big is,
general, not specific yet,
it's manifested as such,
thus,
it's impermanent.
It can, with me,
it doesn't even occur anymore.
Oh, this is messy.
It cannot even be assumed.
Even be thought of,
a fantasized,
anymore as myself.
It's just inconceivable,
becomes, when that principle is understood,
which is about the system of Jiram
and, oh,
she lost the dimension of her thought.
Yeah, it's just...
Well, actually,
she didn't quite lose it fully.
Back then,
but she's clearly recognizing it,
because if she lost it,
she couldn't even remember it,
in that sense.
Like, you can't even bring it back as a memory,
because even the preview,
the memory,
and the past,
is seen,
because impermanent,
which means,
yourself ceases to reside,
even there.
So, the dimension,
it's gone, it's gone.
So,
sort of on it,
cannot even remember,
well,
he can recognize what a father is,
assuming,
a father or a father is,
but he cannot even conceive that,
even as a memory.
He knows, oh,
I used to do this.
I used to,
like,
I used to think that I existed,
independent of my senses,
independent of my aggregates,
but actually,
how that,
was experienced actually,
it's inconceivable.
It cannot arise anymore.
Which is what passed
and the future
and the present
is reflected,
with it I knew.
So, a real key is
seeing how,
this sense of self,
is dependent on,
these rising and falling phenomena.
The standard view,
for a protrusion,
I think,
is that,
I'm here solid,
and I'm experiencing all these things,
and whether they come and go,
or whether they come and go,
and that will be what?
So, that's what the mind
by impermanence.
And the point is,
no, the impermanence
has to be personal,
which means the impermanence
has to pertain to that sense of self.
So, if you're contemplating something
that's coming and going,
and you don't feel anything,
is that's irrelevant?
You need to find the impermanence
that will concern you,
or rather,
the thought of this thing,
disappearing,
will concern you.
Which is what I mean,
impermanence,
like,
if you, like, seeing a thing,
manifest,
and then seeing the destruction of the thing,
it's actually another,
another arising.
It's a manifestation,
appearance,
of a thing being,
of a particular thing being disintegrated.
It's not a impermanence.
It's not,
it's actually more arising.
It's a worldly type of impermanence
in terms of things
that have changed the shape,
or whatever else,
but,
phenomenologically speaking,
it's just another arising experience.
So,
you can't actually experience
impermanence through your senses.
Any,
in any way,
you can't even conceal it.
The true impermanence.
Because if you would,
you would need the Buddha
to tell you how to find the way out of the self-view.
You just need to,
as most of the mystics believe,
and, hopefully,
access it.
I threw,
threw a vision,
threw a mantle of another,
and it's impossible.
So, instead of trying to see,
disappearing,
you recognize that the appearance
is the disease,
because of which,
it's gone.
It will be gone,
even if it isn't.
Because if it is,
that's another experience
that has a reason,
because it has a reason,
the impermanence is impermanent.
So,
that's what you regarded as permanent,
is also impermanent,
and even the impermanent things
that you regarded before
are even more impermanent.
So, it's just impermanence,
and more impermanence,
as opposed to impermanence,
and then,
too much,
of permanence.
Thank you.