What is your permanence?
That's it.
A rising is manifest.
In the soupers, it says,
a rising is manifested,
ceasing is manifested,
possessing or changing is manifested.
So, I don't want to repeat myself,
but basically,
impermanence pertains to that manifested bit.
So, he won't be found
in actual arising, or ceasing,
or possessing or changing, because those things
are all phenomena.
And impermanence pertains to the nature
of the phenomena.
Yeah.
Presisting or changing is a phenomena.
Yeah, enduring. Well, a rising
is already possessing or changing.
You don't see the actual origin of the thing.
The point, I mean the exact split second.
No, you just have a thing origin.
Which means, whether it's a rising,
or whether it's ceasing,
it's like fading in and fading out.
And fading in, it's only the form of endurance.
It's the same thing that it's increasing in its presence.
But it's the same thing.
So, it's persisting.
As the same thing,
while it's changing, I increase in its presence.
And same goes for fading out.
For decreasing in its presence.
But the point is,
whether you're witnessing
which your senses,
arising of something like
manifestation of a thing,
or something just disappeared.
Both of those things arise for you
in your experience.
So, when you're looking at the actual
disappearance of something,
that is appearing for you.
So, the disappearance in a particular level,
external level.
But as an experience,
it's actually arising.
It's appearing for you.
It's manifesting for you.
But it's that confusion that I spoke before
between the users of arising and the rising.
Like, you should really distinguish between the rising,
ceasing, persisting, or changing,
and word manifesting.
Because arising is manifested.
Ceasing is manifested.
Persisting, or changing is manifested.
So, from that point of view,
ceasing arises.
Persisting, or changing arises.
All right, appears.
So, seeing is always,
and is always,
impermanence pertains to that
manifestation.
To that level,
doesn't pertain to you having to witness a destruction
and disappearance of a thing in order for you to know the impermanence.
And even the Sotapana's insight says,
whatever has the nature of arising
has the nature of ceasing.
And knowing the nature means actually
so far from seeing it being destroyed in order to realize the impermanence,
you actually need it to be
a reason in order to see it as impermanent.
So, that's why people have a problem.
People who think the practice is like denying,
nothing's real, nothing exists,
see the science, show this is only a journey.
They basically never allow things to manifest.
Or, are they? I mean,
you can't really stop them from manifesting.
But they never discern the fact that things manifest
because they're too busy denying them.
As a result of that,
well, they just completely cover up
any possibility of understanding
what the real impermanence is,
the impermanence that matters.
The impermanence, which, if you were to understand,
is pretty different suffering.
Well, what about impermanence?
So, things
a thing is a vision,
always. There's always this thing of vision,
like the fiber,
I hope it's art.
There's always the thing manifested.
Yeah. Manifested experience is
so that general experience.
The only thing is that the design manifested
isn't bug.
Is it?
Yeah, the unborn needs, like,
that's something
that the ultimate, like,
negative of your experience is there.
But it doesn't manifest
in a sense of everything else manifests.
It's like a negative.
For abandoning everything else,
you develop nibbana.
But you can't just go into nibbana
because there will be another thing.
The most general level
of experience,
a thing.
So, exactly. So, for as long as you have
the fiber aggregates,
there's always something manifested.
That's why.
Well, Buddha before he became the Buddha,
a rising and falling,
I mean, manifestations
of any kind of the five aggregates.
So, on the most general level,
he was contemplating the nature of a rising means
nature of ceasing because he has a reason.
And he became the Buddha,
just to that contemplation.
So, exactly. Whether you witness,
unless your aggregates break apart,
any experience that you witness,
that you go through,
that you experience,
even if it's a destruction of every single thing in the world,
even if it's a destruction of your own senses,
then arises for you.
That disappearance appears for you
as disappearance of those things.
Because things arise,
or rather, everything is discerned
and arises on the level of the mind.
That's why the mind comes first.
That's why I have to understand impermanence.
Well, in order to understand impermanence,
you have to discern the
arising of things,
their manifestation.
You have to discern the nature of their manifestation.
And that's it.
If you see that they manifest,
and you have absolutely,
it's inconceivable for you
to have any say in their manifestation.
That is just like you completely,
it's inaccessible.
You cannot possibly,
even conceive it
in the utmost obstruction,
how it would be.
The mind cannot go there.
Because of that, you know,
for this very reason,
that I have no say in their manifestation,
that's why things are impermanent.
That's why things are this,
that's why they cannot be,
myself.
Impossible.
So it's not that you need to figure out
that what not self means,
means by seeing impermanence correctly for what it is,
that's automatically the experience of not self.
It's the same.
It's the same thing.
Well,
it's a different thing,
but it's basically the same experience,
that consists of the different things.
It's within the same thing.
Because,
always like when people,
when you read the sutras,
or any contemporary Buddhist,
whatever,
interpretations,
you just assume,
oh, impermanence, impermanence,
you must see a rise.
Yes, and then you look for the impermanence.
But that's why lots of people
really commit to it.
The end of experience
and I thought I was speaking from experience,
because,
no matter how much,
you might even destroy things that mean to you,
just to show,
but actually that's another arising
of another experience.
And it's the experience that is impermanent.
That's what Nietzsche means,
not the actual things.
Because,
as one of the wrong views
of the Western science,
and I remember we studied that from chemistry.
So, like, nothing can get destroyed.
It's only the energy,
and the molecules just changed the shape.
So, I've got the names.
I don't want to get them wrong,
but it was the name of that law in the early commerce,
which was basically like,
when you burn,
say, you burn a piece of wood,
well, that energy,
that,
that object,
it's formed now.
So, now it's smoke, and I think that's transmuted.
Well, it's basically like,
it's impossible to destroy the matter.
Uh-huh.
Yeah.
And see, like, from a completely wrong view,
they kind of arrived
at the outside of what I'm talking about.
When you realize,
because basically matter,
or not matter,
the only way you can know matter is through your experience.
Now with the scientists, they deny
the personal experience, they generally project it outside as,
it's a matter.
It's a genuine matter that they are accessing and dealing with,
not their experience, or it.
So then they say, oh, it's a genuine matter that you cannot destroy.
But basically what they're saying is,
even the destruction is another experience for you,
so you can't destroy your experience.
Mm-hmm.
And Buddha goes even further, saying, even death
would not be a destruction of your experience,
because you continue.
So, only Aravan truly destroys the experience,
how, by abandoning it,
but seeing that he could have not,
that he could have not have owned it.
He could have not had owned it.
Well, one or the other.
He could have, I think, he could have not owned it.
I think that's the best thing.
No matter what.
And fully understanding that,
he just, like, he automatically let's go.
No, no, no, you're not.
Automatically, it's abandoned.
So that's what I mean.
You discern, oh, it's arising.
Well, no, sorry.
Through manifestation,
or through something that is present,
you can all, it's arising.
It's increasing that very manifestation,
that's already manifested.
Or it's decreasing that very manifestation,
it's all remembered.
It's just both, oh,
the manifestation isn't using still
of the same thing.
But you don't, like, concern yourself
with moments of it's arising,
moments of his cessation,
because it's a completely wrong view,
and you can't even see those things.
Because all you're seeing is your own experience
of those things.
And that experience is manifested.
So then you're assuming yourself
as, like,
external to it,
and then observing of its linear progression,
linear kind of endurance in time,
whereby it fingerizes, oh, it's still there,
and now it's gone.
But see, you left yourself completely out.
If you wanted to.
It's irrelevant.
And you also fail to see that even now,
the experience of now this thing is gone,
that is present for you.
But your mind is out concerned
with that external object of your senses,
and you generally believe
that now it's gone.
But actually, it's not gone.
For as long as you'd be thinking about it,
and exist in you, like, well,
even for as long as your five aggregates exist
with this intact memory in the mind,
that thing has its form,
it has a form of its presence.
Even if you can't find its material counterpart anymore,
or other material aspects,
it's not exactly counterpart.
Which is how you can still think about people
that are dying,
or they're gone, things that have been destroyed,
they haven't.
That's the thing.
As a phenomenon, those things are still
manifesting in your experience.
The projection of the matter and stuff,
whatever else wrong views people might have,
where you think the world exists
independent of you, or you exist independent of the world,
or both of neither,
or you're confused in regard to it,
then, yeah, you will believe that
this material aspect is the thing,
but then, see,
then you can't account for your thinking of it
when that matter disappears.
But the thing was never in the matter,
nor was never in your mind,
in your consciousness.
So now it's that very absence of that matter,
there stands for the matter
of that thing when you think about it,
a negative matter.
Ah, this, my favourite thing,
is gone.
It used to be right here.
So now the empty space
becomes the material aspect
of the matter you're thinking about,
because it was always name and matter.
But the views that people have,
projects give the priority
to the matter,
which is why you keep looking for the destruction
of the matter to find the proof
for impermanence.
But there's no external proof for impermanence,
because that's another thing that arises,
and the another thing that you can take to be permanent.
So the proof
for impermanence
is in a rising of thing,
or rather, yeah,
the proof for things
in permanence in its nature
would be in the nature of that
manifestation.
So things are impermanent,
now because you can observe the destruction,
things are impermanent
because they have a reason
in the first place.
That's why they will have to cease.
Yeah, beyond your control.
Like inconceivable.
Because you can still concede a formal control.
You say, oh, this is beyond my control.
But you can see a sense of control
in regard to that.
If you really drilled this deep enough,
it becomes inconceivable
even in that remote sense.
Because all you're going to find is
these things manifested.
And then through that manifestation,
you can discern how it's arising,
how it's persisting,
how it's changing.
It's manifesting.
That's the bottom line.
And it's right there where you can see
because it's manifested.
And even the word manifest,
to do with you, just it's there.
For that very reason,
you won't be there.
Not because you can destroy it,
not because others,
simply because it came
uninvited.
That's the whole existence here.
That's the nature of the five aggregates.
To arise and fall.
To be manifested.
Until they break apart.
And that's why in regard to the five aggregates,
you establish that assumption.
That they are used,
that you are theirs,
or whatever they're using control.
Basically, that's how opadana gets involved with,
in regard to the five aggregates.
But you can't really
if the five aggregates are not opadana,
but there's no opadana without the five aggregates.
Let's chew a little bit.
I think.
They are indifferent to you,
the five aggregates.
They go their own course.
But it's interference due to the like,
ignorance.
Not knowing that you cannot interfere.
That lack of knowledge is the form of interference.
And that interference,
in regard to them, can't really change a five aggregates
or do anything with them.
But it can certainly feel the assumption that you are,
that you are in control, that they're used,
that they belong to you, that whatever else.
But all they do is manifest.
And because they manifest, they cease.
So, in terms of...
I know we can go there to suit the 35, isn't it?
Which one?
Imagine me coming in.
I think the 35.
The one with...
Do you see this?
39.
What's this?
I started with the...
I know.
First I'm assuming,
consciousness gets reborn.
And consciousness passes on from life to life to life.
And he says, that's what the Buddha taught.
Well, this is about the venerable astrology.
That's a 35.
Yeah, but 39.
I think...
But it's right after something.
I do remember that.
38.
It's like, do you see?
Because this has got to be.
Yeah.
It's 38.
It's...
It's a big sati.
Is it some of the...
Is it some of the fishmen?
It's some of the fishmen.
So, what about it?
Well, it is...
What started with...
He has the view that consciousness gets reborn.
Yeah.
He thinks it's the same consciousness that runs him on this
through the rounds of rebirths,
but it's not another.
It's the...
inexperience.
Things just are.
And so, to assume that you've...
To explain...
Well, the only way you can think is to assume it.
Because it's inconceivable.
Yes.
It's inconceivable to...
Like, you can't even conceive...
Like, the rebirth.
In a sense of something would be...
Like, ignorant manifestations.
Like, things are manifesting to...
Your five vibrigates.
Try your life and experience.
And you have ignorance in regard to that.
And you base these external assumptions.
And then you think, oh, I must be this.
That's passing to the next life.
But everything, even this.
Even the idea of this.
And the idea of the next life.
And the idea of passing.
All of that is already fully affected.
Like, fundamentals of your own experience.
From the very start.
But he's...
He's used...
This passing point between this life and the next life.
It doesn't exist.
But there's still the passing from this consciousness to that.
Which is a thing in itself.
It's a thing in itself.
The limbo is another realm.
So to speak.
If you pass from this life into limbo.
Well, that's another thing.
Between lives.
Well, that's not life.
So there's always...
So the manifestation of the aggregates continues.
And you can discern it.
That's what the Buddha said.
No matter how many lifetimes somebody can remember.
Whether it's one, five, five hundred, five thousand.
All they're going to remember is a rising and passing.
The manifestation of the five aggregates of one particular among them.
They won't...
They can't imagine...
No, because there's a link between...
That's another thing, yeah.
In between exists only between the two things.
And that in between is the third thing.
As in between.
As a negative of the both things, it's a thing.
That's a meant that even the absence of a material aspect
of a certain thing that you're thinking of,
that absence is a thing.
That's why space is often listed
as one of the... one of the great elements.
With consciousness.
So you have four great elements of what if I...
Space and consciousness.
Because if you look at it,
there's a very little distinction between them.
Because even space, the negative,
the absence of matter,
serves as matter.
And the consciousness is listed within because the consciousness is actually
in that sense external,
with that matter.
So you can't conceive...
Well, you can conceive, sorry, you can conceive matter,
which is more of a reality.
But truly, you can't access the matter.
But in the same sense,
you can't access your own consciousness.
Because it's all your own consciousness.
It's out there with those four great elements.
How outside of your reach?
So what are you going to have?
It's basically Nama Rupa.
That's all that appears.
No matter how remote, how big use,
how distant, how abstract,
it's still within the Nama Rupa.
You can't have the experience of consciousness in itself,
or matter in itself,
or even have its conscious matter,
i.e., the real experience of Nama Rupa.
But both ends of that experience,
i.e. consciousness and the matter
are external to you,
in principle, inaccessible.
Which makes Nama Rupa inaccessible to you.
You can just be witnessing it.
Well, suffering or account of it,
or whatever else.
But you can't access it either.
In its nature,
manifests,
and for those reasons,
it ceases.
Just because it manifests.
Just because it comes from the direction
that it's inaccessible to you.
So, it would be like
you're wearing borrowed clothes,
that's your idea where it came from,
and your idea when it's going to be taken away from you.
That's your life.
That's everyone's life.
Entirely.
Because it's the thing,
oh, well, like, you know,
I can still enjoy borrowed stuff.
You could, if you were to know,
when the person is going to come and take it away.
Oh, I still have two months to go.
But you don't.
It can be, after the next in breath.
And that's it.
And you realize, oh, okay,
I better adjust my plans accordingly.
But no people adjust their plans accordingly,
or what if you do.
So, when things are taken away from you,
they're always in the, like,
in the stress.
But if you were, there's nothing based on
if you don't plan,
like to simplify it a bit.
If you don't plan anything on a kind of borrowed things,
and those things are taken away,
you will remain completely unaffected.
So, basically, when death comes,
you will be completely unaffected
if you don't plan anything on a kind of life.
Because life is a thing,
that's borrowed.
Well, that's kind of in front of you,
and then you decided to borrow it.
But you have no idea who owns it
and who takes it away at what time.
And the Buddha did say something similar.
He said,
Mara can do with people what he wants
because they come to his territory
and use his things.
So, it's like a bait.
On the kind of that, he's in charge of them.
And then what are those things?
And you might think,
oh, I'm awesome behavior.
There is those things or something.
It's much more than that.
Those things are your eyes,
your ears, your nose, your tongue,
your whole sense base.
And it's kind of like that's all Mara.
So, you realize,
okay, so whatever appears in some line.
Oh, funny enough, we're going to say,
whatever appears,
and everything that you know of,
everything that you think of,
everything that you might see or hear
and think of,
it will have that in common
that it will appear.
And for that reason, it will not be yours
or other it cannot be yours.
Well, you might take it, sir.
Who says,
everything becomes like a piece of wood.
Yes, it does.
Oh, yeah, when he has the monks in the forest.
Yeah.
Would you, like, well,
some of you would probably be,
how do you say?
Well, it was basically talking about the,
you know, people being upset
on a kind of sickness or death,
something happening to your body.
And he said, he asked monks, would you be upset
if somebody comes in this woods now?
And starts collecting these dried up twigs
and branches that fell off the trees.
And I'm like, no, we wouldn't, of course.
There's nothing to do with us.
That's how you should regard yourself
because it has nothing to do with you.
But that also requires giving up the pleasures
that you gain through that body.
Which is why it's so intoxicating.
And again, there's another suit, I was about to say it,
but there is another suit that says it better.
If this human will only be consisting of pain,
people wouldn't need much of prompting
to go for liberation.
But it doesn't.
It consists of that pleasure as well.
Which is why people get intoxicated
and blinded in regard to that,
which is hurting them.
You just don't see it.
Because you're intoxicated with little pleasure
you get from it.
But both.
Or within the nature of the borrowed goods.
Did you know permission to borrow?
And you certainly know control how long you can use it.
So basically, it's even worse.
And then you think you own it.
So imagine your surprise.
And Mara does come and collect what he is.
Well, it always was he is.
That's why they're not like all the other suitors
who often talk about their puppet on the strings.
So all the things you borrow are basically the strings
that Mara uses then to pull you.
Because you hold onto those strings.
So the puppet is going with the strings
that are yanking it.
But also even that self.
Even that person that holds onto things,
experience, or that self that is manifest.
That must also be seen.
Same.
You just see everything with the same right view.
So even that sense of self.
It's a reason.
It's manifest.
You can designate.
It's real.
So the Buddha never said there is no self.
He said, well, basically, there is not self.
So that which you take to be a self,
that sense of self, doesn't belong to you.
Is that a stop being able to see your own view?
Both the right view.
Yeah.
You have it.
You have that wrong view.
And that sense of self is actually, well,
as the Buddha said,
it can often be just a sense of an individual sense
of a particularly unique set of five aggregates.
That you take to be like the most personal aspect
of your experience,
so you take to be the yourself.
But no matter what sense of self it is,
how strong it is,
leave it for what it is.
Don't try to deny it when you get it,
because there will be again,
denying the things that you can't even deny.
They manifest on their own.
So you're trying to cover up the contradiction in terms
that's where people end up being very frustrated.
But the point is, no,
allow your sense of self,
actually see your sense of self as a phenomenon.
Like, basically,
these other words saying,
see your sense of self as manifested,
because it is manifested.
In very ambiguous terms,
but it's still manifested as such.
So see it like that,
and then don't regard it as belonging to you.
Yeah, because even your self,
it's just, yeah.
Yeah, nothing,
nothing in an experience you could have created.
Which means everything you can abandon everything.
All of it can be abandoned.
It's just the idea that something,
that something can create things
without being a thing itself.
And then you feel like,
all you need to undo certain processes or whatever,
in order for it to stop,
and then you can really
abandon self as, no,
that's already the act of yourself.
You just have to see,
and that's why at any time,
you can see the right view.
No matter what situation,
go to bed.
If you look through the whole thing,
including your sense of self,
and not only.
Like, I recognize that you can't only
in your sense of self,
which is why it's not yours.
So there is not self.
There is that which you take to be self,
but it's not yourself.
Resultate,
this sort of debt,
so you just abandon it.
When it continues about,
do you see this?
Well, yeah,
it comes like to the very fundamental age.
Do you see this has manifested?
Yes, when there was a,
do you see it manifested
with this as a condition?
Yes, when there was a,
do you see it with the disappearance
of that condition?
What has come,
what is manifested has come to cessation?
Like this deep domain standing.
So you need to introduce that,
like, a determination.
I do see this as a condition
of the manifested thing.
While you're seeing the manifested thing,
so it's not an explanation
of a linear causality.
Oh, this A creates B,
and I'm watching both,
thus I'm not myself.
Like, that's just complete magical thinking.
Will you project?
Well, all of the things are impermanent.
They constantly change in the scientists,
say the atoms, the atoms are molecules.
They're never,
in one electrons,
they're never in the same spot,
etc.
So,
I still suffer
when I kind of
fulfill these eyes,
and I kind of being paper people
and I'll be prepared,
being separate from people
and I'll be separated from.
No matter what scientific view
I might talk,
it doesn't pertain to you.
But,
if you see as all those things
as manifested,
when I say manifested
by themselves on their own,
it means determined by something
other than you.
Yet,
like the entire manifestation
is completely out of your hands.
And if that's
the direction where they came from,
that determination,
disappears,
they can't possibly stay,
which means
you're gone,
your experience is taken away.
So, it says,
do you see it as determined by
something else?
Well, in this particular suit,
that he uses the
element.
Do you see it as
neutralment?
Yeah.
And it's neutral
into something that you don't
necessarily see particularly.
No, because there wouldn't be a
neutralment,
it would be another thing.
That's now
neutral, but something else.
So,
that's why I say,
while you're aware
of the manifesto thing,
within that manifesto thing,
you can discern
its neutralment.
But not by
looking away
from the manifesto thing,
and then,
why?
Because then you will be
looking at another
manifested thing,
which you will think is
the neutralment
of the previous manifesto thing.
So, see how you
kind of squeezed yourself out,
and made this whole
relationship external.
If it's external,
it won't be the right view.
Needs to arise internally.
So, needs to arise
within the manifested thing,
the neutralment
would be then
the real neutralment
because you have an
abandoned manifesto thing.
To me,
it's all about this.
So, it's not
A
and B.
It's
A
and smaller A.
Within
that A.
So,
the general experience,
in particular,
things inside it?
Sure.
But that's a very
general thing to put,
to put it in a way,
it's just like,
two general.
Well, no,
when you say,
it's just general,
in particular,
it's an explanation.
No.
It's an experience.
Well, again,
general thing can become
particular if you
forget about it as
general,
and then you
rather experience it
more generally than you
got to it.
And you still think
you think of general
thing.
Means,
whatever is manifested,
any of the
aggregates,
whatever is manifested.
Or you can just go
as we spoke before,
the presence of your body,
the presence of your mind,
two simultaneous things,
inseparable from it.
But you can see,
when you think about a
body, well,
that's a mental
image.
You don't worry about it.
So everything
shares the nature
of a mental
image.
And what does it mean?
Everything is
manifested.
Because everything
manifests on the
level of a mental
image.
So, why do you
have the mental
image of that certain
thing?
You discern its
new treatment within
that.
And discerning its
new treatment means
discerning it as
coming from something
other than
the presence of
self.
That's what you
said.
Like, you need to see a
thing depending upon
something else that
cannot be yours.
And then that
thing that is yours will
be disowned.
Because you just
actually, I can't
own this.
Because if that thing
that I cannot own
disappears, this thing
will not stand.
So actually,
that thing belongs
to the other.
It belongs to
its new treatment.
It cannot
belong to me.
Because I
have no say in its
appearance.
I have no say in its
So this, yeah.
This has appeared
because of that
because of which
has appeared.
Because
like, this
experience, this
mental experience, this
experience of
normal
root.
Its
new treatment is
well, we can
speak about it.
We can say the
experience of
self.
That I said
self is a
manifested phenomenon.
That you
confused to, well, that
you conceived to belong
to you.
But it's on the
earth.
So you can take your
sense of self.
Then a bigger sense of
self.
And it's manifested.
So you need to discern
its manifestation
whether it through
increasing its presence,
decreasing its presence,
or simply
persisting either way.
So when you
become skilled in
like discerning
manifestation, picking
up the signs of
things.
That's the picking of
the signs of your
mind.
Chitanivita.
Within that, then,
when you think about,
okay, what is this
thing inseparable
from?
What is a necessary
condition?
What is a new
treatment?
What is a basis for
these sense of self to
be here?
But then you have to,
like, you only
summon a secret
root.
The womb
attention means exactly
that.
Goes to the root of the
present thing.
Not to the root of
another thing.
Of another experience.
So that's why you need
that proper attention to
discern within the
present manifestation to
discern its
conditions.
Or formations.
Or determinations.
Or
sancaro, whatever you
want to translate it.
So with our
abandoning, the
manifest sense of
self that you're
mindful of.
You need to discern
within that
what is that sense of
self inseparable
from?
And then whatever you
find would
will most likely be a
determination that, I
think, unless you
over-intended, or rather
over-attended, that
manifestation in looking
for its
new treatment and then
found other things that
then became
manifestations.
And they themselves
had their own
new treatments within
themselves that you
have not seen.
Because you have to
consider that
you have to consider
that you have to
consider that
you have to consider
that you have to
consider that
you have to consider
that you have to
consider that
you have to consider
that you have to consider
that you are
mindful of
its insignificant
Yes.
The
my statement
of this
I was very
sensing
You know counting deep with the probe and then pulling this thing out everything else is the same
Just that one big there one misunderstanding of the very good
colors and sort of poses everything else
Curious so back on the sense of self
What is it? What is it inseparable from while that sense of self is present within that sense of self discern
What is inseparable from
Could you have sense of self present without being able to think
Without having any mental images whatsoever would you be able to descend at the biggest sense of self and me?
You wouldn't so would you be able to think if there is no living body that it's still operating and paid with conscious and so they are in the world
You wouldn't
So then is that living body paid because you wouldn't be able to think you wouldn't be able to have sense of self
So then there wouldn't be a sense of self in that sense that would belong to you because if something would happen to that body
If something would happen to that consciousness if something to happen to that ability to think
That sense of self goes cannot possibly remain standing
You see me while it's in there see you can see all that like on a board
You can write it down as a chart and it will make good sense explanation
But it will not be open I go and you certainly not
Feel from suffering or bring you closer to it. Why because you're not seeing it in the right order and by the right order
I mean you don't you're seeing it literally you don't see
One within the other
Not next to a while
One while the other is still present
So you're seeing it left and right or down
But you're not seeing it within that thing
You take the self
That's where the whole the whole I'll be done in the commentaries. That's where the entire attitude the entire way of looking is completely wrong
You all the stuff from the suitors are there rich and linear like packed in lists and stuff
But it's all in there. It's all out there that you can observe
That's why there's always a reason the order of things the Buddha would he wouldn't just list things out to you
You'll be like well like this. Do you see this has come to be yes now that you see that this has come to be
That sense of self I'm talking about right now that it's manifested that you see it for what it is
Yeah, do you see it inseparable from certain nutrients?
Like he would not be able to he would not be able to even be conceived without those nutrients present
Yes, Lord, we see that
So would you see that with the cessation of those nutrients?
This will not remain standing even for a split second inconceivable like the two sticks holding each other
You move on the other one goes down
Yes, Lord, we see and then he refers to that because this this view is the purified and bright view as it is
Basically, that's the right that just just that principle is the right view
Nothing else and that's why they're like the kind of generic
Thermal like so sort of party for the right views like, oh, whatever has the nature of rising has the nature of ceasing
Whatever it's manifested will have to see basically because it's manifested
And then he said even that view as pure as bright like
Your band don't even that
By using that view you abandon all the wrong views, and then you just let go even of that view and then the dharma is truly told as
Like as a simile of the raft and so
Yeah, so it's a
Take a sense of self again. Why is this manifest good is
Some of like you keep that in front yeah, but then you look at the whole the two sides at the same time
But they start distinguishing the sides as within that front you're keeping
Yeah, I can't explain. I know because it's not spatial. Yeah, it doesn't pretend to space
But I know what you mean. I'm just saying to the same
That's why it's so easy to confuse what comes first what comes second
It's
kind of the same on the same level, but there is first there is second depending on what you attend
So as I said you can over attend and then start attending those
Supposed in utriments of your sense of self as as separate senses of self as separate things that you just do to be yours
But no, you want to have that thing in front of you
Sense of self
Within this very present sense of self you discern things
Without abandoning so while you're mindful of the sense of self within that mindfulness of the sense of self
You discern things that this sense of self isn't separable from as sense of self
And
Like see that there will be all over doing it. You can call it later
That's why like in your set up. Well, like somebody might not necessarily use the 12 factored
Explanation, but it's about because all they see is with this this is and that's it
That's what I'm talking about with this this is so with these nutrients this is, but you see it in reverse order
Then later you can start discerning more and more where you become proficient in that
Principle as when they were under the ins and off. This is so easy. You've seen all the time. You said no
Don't say that because like before for the very reason people don't see that which you find easy now
They remain bound for some sort of for like
Well, in total amounts of times
Yeah, I can legal it my sense of self now
What is it with the sense of self?
What is this?
You can simplify it, but as long as you do it right according to well as long as you do the principle right you can
As simplified as you want in terms of designation you can just say with this this
But in your mind see thing within I think
Nothing next to the thing nothing before the thing nothing after the thing
Think within the present thing and that's why it's a callica. It's time less
Does not pertain to time because it's one within the other simultaneously present
That's why I'm learning the pastor I remember using saying like when it feels like a thought a thought closes upon itself
Because you don't go left. You don't go right. You don't go to another thought. You have a thought present
Whatever shape of form and within that
You sort of well, let it go in a sense
Seat impossible to own like you you have no it like we notice you have no idea where it came from
Which is the direction of its origin is just in Brazil. So you just have a thing arisen and
For that very reason you recognize a thing will cease
Does a swing is in public?