Now you have specific questions?
Well there's a few things I'm excited about.
There's one about assuming the senses, assuming the senses.
If one assumes the senses then on account of their feelings grow
and the mind becomes damaged with covetousness and cruelty.
And acts and...
Yeah this is just a heaping up of suffering.
No one is said to be far from the banner.
So when seeing a sight, mindfulness becomes confused if attention is focused on the pleasant aspect.
Doing this one remains assuming.
Well basically mindfulness gets confused if one attends the pleasant aspect
which is the feelings that have a rose based on the assumed senses.
So through simply attending that pleasure that's the result of that assumption
you're actually maintaining that assumption through that pleasure.
So yes there is...
You can say the assumption comes first but not temporarily first but structurally first.
So it's simultaneous presence of the assumption and the feelings of the result.
It's not an account of that assumption but it's simultaneous.
It's not like you're assuming without feeling and then the feeling comes.
And because it's simultaneous simply through attending feelings you're maintaining
that which sort of determines those feelings which is that assumption.
And at the same time your mind...
Well they suffer.
Or the result of that whole picture suffering is present.
Even that is again the same principle of that simultaneous presence.
So then you can say assumption results in feelings or assumption results in suffering
or assumption results in craving or craving results.
It's just simultaneously presence is just maintaining each other
because you're attending a new bit in that sense.
So the principle gets maintained.
Yeah well mind seems being confused equals the whole system.
Within what is assuming the sense it means?
Well assuming the senses means...
Well literally assuming those senses to be yours or to be...
Well assuming a sense to be yours and then assuming that which you gather
through those senses to be for you.
So you assume that the sights you see are the sights that your eyes see.
The sights that you look for you they're yours.
Even if you're looking at things that are not necessarily yours,
the further you're looking with your eyes it's like your sight.
So then sight is for me any sight of anything.
So you have to start seeing the dead phenomenon of senses,
of my senses.
It's kind of always a negative.
You can't actually see your eye with the same eye in the same sense.
So you can... you end up assuming...
Well you end up assuming because the senses are ambiguous.
You don't really know it's like a big kind of dark vague cloud of all senses.
But then all you have is sight sounds, mouth taste,
I just for you.
So then you just take it for granted.
But if you discern long enough through that repetition that...
Whatever notion of your senses you might have,
that those senses are...
Oh I think my senses are visitor.
If you discern that whatever notion you might have,
those senses will never ever be anything more
and certainly will never be anything separable from a
flashy organ of eye, skin, tongue.
But literally these organs, random objects in the world,
that are put together in the unit of this body.
So you don't examine the organ like a doctor would impersonally,
because then it doesn't work.
Then you don't see that connection.
You don't see that dependence.
So you have to see your own organs.
And the only way you can see it is in that external sense of...
Oh, a lump of flesh, which is my eye,
tongue, ears, ear drums, it's just organs.
Literally just...
Just as you have this, this bin,
broom, stone, tree, eye,
liquid, matter, brain,
brain, brain, basically four elements.
But these particular material organs are that
because of which there are sites that you can discern in the world.
But it's not in you nor is it for you.
Those organs are external, as external,
as the external objects are on you.
You just...
You don't see the connection.
And that connection literally needs to be fabricated.
Like you will never see the connection naturally.
It's a secondary.
Because natural...
Natural way is the way of ignorance.
Natural way is the way that goes with the grain.
So you have to go against the grain.
And basically,
but if you were to dwell on it long enough,
like a fabricating contemplation that your senses
are inseparable, like when I say my senses,
whatever vague thought you might have about it,
take it as vague.
You have to define it.
Take it as a whole phenomenon, as an entity,
that vague thought of my senses,
and then see the presence of that
is directly determined inseparable
from the flesh eye, the tongue, the skin,
the nose, ears, brain, whatever.
You literally, like, no matter what vague thought
I might have about my senses,
the fact that I can even think that,
ambiguously, absolutely is because
this living matter of my body
of this sixth sense base is present
in that material form.
Because when again gets destroyed,
I can't be handed.
It's inconceivable.
So no matter how much you...
your mind, your thoughts,
your idea of senses might feel
different from the material objects,
fundamentally, it can never
like escape it.
So destruction of matter will bring an end to this.
So that's why I'm realizing that,
no matter how much you
volitionally, reflexively developed,
you know, your thoughts,
and your disturbance, and your abstractions,
and your reflect, whatever, whatever you want,
it's all there possible
because there is a living sixth sense
body present in the world,
as a matter.
When that matter gets destroyed,
and the material is disintegrated,
you can't be conceiving and abstracting
in regard to it.
You can't know any mental phenomena.
So no matter what intentionality,
you can have with your mind,
it's subordinate to the presence of
that gratuitous matter
that is living, which is your body,
life. When that's taken away,
nothing can be left.
Nothing can remain.
You're just inconceivable.
But it's like contemplating,
like drilling, literally drilling,
that connection, because it's not,
you're not going to, it's not obvious.
It seems fabricated, it seems abstract.
And it is, for Kutuzina,
it is completely abstract.
But it's a right abstraction.
It's the abstraction that,
if repeated sufficient number of times,
it will,
like take root,
it will correspond to how things actually are.
And then you can see how things actually are.
Which is that, yes,
your senses cannot even be conceived to be yours.
It's impossible.
Let alone that which you acquire
for your senses to be for you.
Come here.
So you see what I mean?
Like if you think now,
or if it's very good, I think it's like,
like my eyes, what is my,
my eyes, my senses.
You immediately assume as,
inside of you, as in turn,
as part of you.
But actually, that's a thought.
And you can have just
the another thought, which is,
well, another way of seeing,
which is seen as objects as external,
as a thought.
Well, that's the thing. You're always going to have a thought.
Not perhaps.
So when I said, oh, that's a thought.
It doesn't mean that I'm dismissing it.
I just meant that that big is.
That you think is the senses.
You have to see, no, that's a thought.
That obviously for me stands for that which I think senses are.
So when you start recognizing that all you're going to have is a phenomenon of thought
in regard to your senses,
then you realize, well,
then thinking these external organs,
it's nothing less real than this thought.
Because that's also a thought.
But it's the right thought.
Well, exactly.
And then somebody tells you, somebody else,
like the Buddha and the Sutras,
tells you that that's the right thought.
And if you keep repeating it,
it will correspond to how things are,
because it's right.
And then you can see how things are.
But not without the sufficient amount of repetition.
Because that's what I think we spoke about it before.
Well, that's why you can't stumble upon
RNA chip or any other sort of,
but sort of by accident.
And oh, yeah, I got it.
Just testing, you know, wow.
Instant training is like doing this,
and then this happened.
It doesn't happen.
You develop it.
Literally through training and drilling.
So like in this instance,
the Buddha tells you, this is the right thought.
Obviously, experience of protrusion is top to bottom, is completely rock.
Effective ignorance.
So you don't have a criteria of what is right thought,
what it isn't.
So then you have the faith in the Buddha,
and the Buddha tells this is the right thought.
And you can think that by thought.
But thinking it once,
won't make a difference,
because you have this whole ocean of ignorance
that needs to be drained away.
But then thinking it twice won't make a difference.
Thinking it three times won't make a difference.
A thousand times,
then it will be draining away.
And eventually, when it's officially drained,
you will recognize all ignorance is drained.
So the point is,
that drilling,
that in the beginning, yeah, you have to do an account of faith,
in a sense that, okay,
you believe the Buddha knew what he was talking about,
you have faith, so that's why you're applying that.
But that's why you can't do that.
You can sometimes accidentally
stumble, like,
do the right thing, engage in the right thought.
But if you don't know,
that that is the right thought,
if nobody told you, you will not know,
that that was the right thought,
and you will certainly not repeat it,
a thousand times,
without any apparent result.
So that's why it's impossible,
like by chance, you know, you can roll a dice
and you can get it once and twice and five times.
But you can't get it, it's just impossible,
inconceivable to, like, always get the right result.
Unless you know that that is the right result,
and you always go for that.
So that's why that utterance of another
is one of the, like,
fundamental factors for the right view.
So you cannot possibly, as I said,
you might have been doing things rightly,
attending things rightly,
but if nobody externally told you
that that is the right thing,
it's simply inconceivable
that you would have stuck
to repeating those things rightly,
thousands of times for years,
because there is no apparent result,
right away.
It's not like you do it,
and you immediately see it.
You just have to keep doing it,
and doing it, and doing it,
and doing it,
and you accept it intellectually
as the right thing,
like reason, as the Buddha said,
oh, the man who wants to be free from suffering
goes and, like,
frequents the wise man, he listens to what they say.
He ponders, makes sense,
measures the task,
and he does it.
So you accept it through reasoning,
through discernment,
on that level,
but then you keep repeating it,
and repeating,
and because you had faith,
in what the Buddha said,
to be right,
you stick to it,
and you repeat it,
ten thousands of times,
and because it was right,
you become an out of hand.
But if you didn't know,
if you didn't have faith,
then it was right.
You wouldn't have possibly stuck to it.
For that long,
because there is no,
there is no confirmation of it.
But always,
until much, much later.
Yes, no confirmation.
You might have different results.
Yes.
You might have pleasant results.
You might have a lessening of suffering,
or more of an understanding.
What, what, what,
what gives you,
the motivation to continue,
if you haven't had the end,
you don't have the end result,
but you,
it makes sense,
what the Buddha says,
so you follow the teaching.
Then,
but you're not getting great results.
Well, that's,
that's for somebody who has heard the teaching.
Yes.
I mean, that can be an inspiration for them to continue,
even without the apparent results.
Yes.
Because it makes sense.
But imagine how impossible
is for somebody to continue,
who hasn't even heard,
or accepted,
through reasoning,
and develop faith,
that what the Buddha said was right.
It's impossible for them to continue,
because there is no,
there is absolutely nothing changes,
through these drillings,
through you don't see nothing,
nothing better,
no worse,
you just,
you won't even notice it.
And let alone stick to it,
and repeat it thousands of times,
the right intention,
the avoidant,
the wrong intention,
and so on and so forth,
then need to things rightly.
Now, you need to be told,
when you're told,
you can discern it,
when you discern it,
then you can do it.
Because as you,
as it's,
something makes sense to you,
so you do it.
And then, say, for example,
with strength,
just, you know,
and keep a strength,
and then,
you reflex,
as you,
as you do,
and he looks,
and you see that,
there is,
so,
the pleasure of being blindness.
So,
there's much,
he's an arahant,
he's not a so-to-funner.
But,
then,
there are ways of developing wisdom,
without Buddha's aid,
but obviously,
it will never lead to the,
the final abandoning
of the assumption of self,
and self-view,
and arahant.
Yeah.
But I mean that,
once you've actually heard,
the Buddha's teaching.
Oh, yeah.
And you do follow,
you do the strain yourself,
but,
you don't,
you don't go that far,
you don't know if you understand it,
but you keep the precepts,
you get the joy,
they come from that,
then you can,
maybe be a little bit more confident,
you think,
oh, yeah.
There might be something more to this,
what he says,
after being restrained,
and the rest of it,
might also be true,
so I'll continue on.
Well, there's,
on top of that,
also,
as I said,
like,
you might be doing things rightly,
or not,
you don't know,
and because,
you haven't been told externally,
through, like,
through the sutras,
and through the Buddha's instruction,
why you should be doing,
you don't really have,
even the external criteria
of what kind of corresponds
to what,
what might be right.
So,
but then,
if you were to develop that criteria,
then you can look back
at the stuff
you used to do,
and you can,
actually,
yeah, back then,
this,
such and such things,
such and such way of attending,
that I was doing,
that was actually right,
it corresponds
to the print number principle,
so to speak,
it corresponds to how things,
obviously,
back then,
you didn't know,
what those principles were,
so you couldn't have stuck to it,
and repeated it long enough,
you can't,
you can do it by chance,
once, twice,
ten times,
but not ten thousands of times,
by chance,
impossible.
You need to have an anchor,
to bring you back,
which would be the discernment.
And then,
you can also look back and see,
oh,
when I thought I was right,
and practicing,
it was completely wrong.
Because now,
you've got the criteria
that you can also see,
things in the past,
you used to do,
your attempts at practice,
and so on,
and you can see,
oh, actually, no,
that was not that wrong.
But obviously, back then,
you didn't know,
if somebody told you back then,
you would have stuck to it,
but nobody told you,
so it took you longer,
or not,
it depends.
But that's why it's,
it's not optional,
after and after another.
But then, obviously,
that's why it also,
it needs,
needs to have that initial step,
first step of faith,
that you have faith,
there is other,
the Buddha,
the Sutras,
the Arun,
the Sothmana,
might be,
the Buddha,
the Sutra,
the Arun,
the Sothmana,
might know what they're talking about,
but again,
it's not that that faith needs to stay,
till the end,
that faith is the initial push,
and then, you know,
if you do it rightly,
you'll come to recognize,
and then you won't need faith,
or rather,
you'll replace the faith
with confidence,
because now you know,
and that's the surface.
Confirm confidence,
in the Buddha,
the Dhamma,
the Sangha,
it replaces that faith
in the Buddha,
now you know,
I don't need to believe in it,
because I know it.
It's like,
it's similar to,
something makes sense.
You don't know,
it makes the most sense,
and then,
you understand.
But always,
always in the back of your mind,
have a little bit of reserve,
because,
as a Patugina,
you don't have a criteria
of what really makes,
or rather,
what makes sense
to you as a Patugina,
does not necessarily mean
is the right thing.
So,
because often,
yeah,
it feels right,
when people are like,
oh, I know,
I'm not a certain one,
but it feels right,
it's like, well,
that's a big mistake,
right there.
You know,
you don't know,
yet,
you're happy to follow
what you think you know,
while you,
at the same time say,
I don't know.
So, you're just like,
undermining yourself
within the same sentence.
Oh, it's okay.
There's somebody there
that is,
there's a connection
with the,
and the Buddha says,
the Dhamma
is leading onwards.
Mm-hmm.
Obviously,
anyone can read that,
and is that,
maybe not a,
something that you,
like a criteria,
is what they look for, isn't it?
But then, again,
you need to discern,
because, like,
I'm sure that people who think,
uh, Dhamma leading,
like,
open eye,
means leading onwards,
or leading onwards,
or, uh,
I'm sure that they're,
they're convinced
that that is what it means.
So, you need to be
completely self-transparent
and see.
Okay.
So, do I really hold on to
this belief,
just because it's pleasing to me?
Mm-hmm.
Just because it suits my other beliefs?
Or it's because you really,
really make sense after,
like, deep,
profound, repetitive,
tedious,
drilling,
investigation,
and contemplation?
When you know,
that you have not,
kind of,
just covered it up,
oh, no, no,
I believe in this,
it's fine,
but you really drilled into it,
and there was nothing left unturned,
then, okay,
it's least likely
to be wrong,
because you really drilled through it,
through the whole thing.
And then,
the answer should
you always have to have.
But most often,
people just maintain beliefs,
because,
it helps them maintain their
previous beliefs,
helps them maintain their previous beliefs,
and then,
so it's just, like,
maintenance of their beliefs.
And,
they all do that,
for one reason,
it's pleasing to me.
Has this said the same?
Well,
what is leading on this?
leading onwards is exactly that.
Like,
if you were to understand,
for example,
what down there is,
that understanding
will be taking you further,
and further,
and further till the orange,
so it's leading you onwards
through that understanding.
So it's not a theory,
it's not as
abstraction,
it's not something you can accept
or reject.
It's something whereby,
through understanding,
you are going further.
So then,
you realize there is more.
There is more.
Through that understanding,
through that criteria,
there is more,
there is more.
Until,
as I answer,
or,
or
and,
or,
or.
Or,
or,
or...
And I think I told you that the other day,
he never, like, no matter what approach he would take on
in expanding the amount to a person or to a group of people,
he would follow that approach through
to define a point of orange, if you're from suffering,
whatever, even if those people don't necessarily achieve it,
his instruction would go all the way.
He wouldn't stop halfway through his approach
that through understanding of number up by and the all,
you can become an arrogant and so on.
He wouldn't stop halfway through and then say,
well, as a matter of fact, number up,
also corresponds to the five aggregates,
and then start comparing it linearly,
always right, you can, it does correspond.
This is experienced as a whole,
whether you take it as five aggregates,
or number up,
vinyana, vinyana,
number up,
but this and that, literally,
but if you start comparing it,
it thesis to be that open icon, like leading on,
which means it thesis to be dama,
because dama is dama only when it leads you out of suffering,
when it leads you towards enlightenment.
So we can be talking the dama,
like dama terms and stuff,
the fact that it's not leading on,
it's not the dama.
And that's why,
like, you can't even by accident teach dama
to somebody else,
without you yourself understanding it,
because that open icon element,
it's something you can't,
it's something you can understand and know,
and then convey to another person in the writer,
knowing what, like,
basically knowing what to say for them to understand,
not sort of comparing dama and comparing the principles
and the terminology for the sake,
like for the scholarly sake by itself, in itself,
and then presented as a kind of, okay,
here is a theory, here is my explanation,
and it's like, okay, sure, I accept that,
and that's it, you leave it at that.
So a person who understood,
I can run into the Buddha,
would know that,
because that's what understanding is.
So then they wouldn't be teaching as a form of explanation,
and that's the difference,
when you're explaining something,
ah, okay, it makes sense, that's it,
or when you're leading somebody onwards
in their understanding.
So sure, I could compare,
like if Nama Rupa, Vinyalna, with Foward,
it's if, as a whole,
that approach is leading you onwards.
But if we're just doing it for the sake of debate,
like abstractively reasoning,
or whatever, just theory,
or just because it's pleasing to me,
there's just pointless.
Even if we actually talk about them all the time,
we're not, because there is no leading onwards element.
But again, you can see leading onwards,
like when I said about the assumption of the senses,
I could have said,
well, see, that's because you think your senses are yours,
and that's it.
Okay, so I should think my senses are not mine,
But it, that's just linear,
and there is absolutely no lead,
but if I tell you, well actually you have to stop.
You have to see that your senses,
the thought of what you think your senses are,
is inseparable from that material thought, again,
of the flesh, eye, and all of the other other sense bases.
So you have to keep drilling that connection on and on and on.
Not just once, okay, that this is not mine,
but you have to discern it and see dependent upon that.
And then you will have, like if you abandon your senses,
means that the feelings won't be generated,
which means that the mindfulness will not be clouded,
which means the suffering won't arise, and you will feel that,
you will feel the absence of suffering.
So you know, like sure, I could say to myself,
senses are not mine,
but it doesn't make sense,
it makes any no difference to the suffering
that you experience, or that you might experience.
Suffering that you might be liable to, makes no difference.
And if it makes no difference, it means it's not a dharma.
Even if you're actually reading the sutra,
but it's not a dharma.
But if you attempt to things rightly,
and you undo the assumption of your senses,
so through that undoing, you are actually not liable
to that suffering anymore, and you can know that, you know.
This is dharma, because it's directly freeing it from suffering.
But in order to be able to see that, to discern that,
you need to be completely self-transparent
and not act out of this use, simply pleasing to me,
that's why I'm holding it.
So you have to be ready to have some very displeased new views,
some views that will fill you with anxiety
and everything else that follows,
because you're undoing, like your own assumption
of your own very existence, of your own sense of self,
of your own confidence as a person, as a whatever else,
you're undoing all of that,
and using only criteria of absence of suffering.
And you can see like, oh well, this actually,
I'm not just acting because it's pleasing,
this is really the real thing.
And then look at that.
If you were to find out the next moment,
that that is not a real thing,
would you be filled with terror and anxiety?
You would, means it's not a real thing.
No, you'll think.
No, the real thing.
Like, as I said, the approach that you took,
like, oh, I'm gonna hold this view,
because it's pleasing to me.
That's like, okay, that's not good, that's not awesome.
So I'm gonna hold this view,
but I'm not doing it because it's pleasing to me.
Fine?
I might be true, but then look at that.
Look whereby, if that view is taken away from you,
or if you find out that it's wrong,
would you be affected personally?
Like thoroughly, and you realize, yes, I would.
Okay, so that view might not be wrong,
but I'm certainly holding on to it,
because if that view is gone,
I'll experience this anxiety and terror,
which means I need to take it further.
So, in a way, you are still holding
because it's pleasing to you,
even if it's the right view.
But if you're holding a view,
regardless of it giving you pleasure,
or giving you pain.
But yet, it just, you can't see it in the other way,
it just, you know, it's...
Well, first of all, you can, but not hold on, you've used,
because it's not, you can only go beyond it
as an arahant.
But before that, you can only hold the right views
on a kind of wrong views.
Or you can hold the wrong views
and not have any right views.
But, you know, the whole notion of,
oh, I don't hold any views, that's a view.
And that there was that sort of,
that I'm actually referring to, when you said,
oh, he said, you could ask him,
like, so what views do you have?
He said, ah, Master Gautama, I have, what is he saying?
Oh, yeah, I have no, I have no,
he said, he asked me, well, views are pleasing to you,
like, no, Master Gautama, I don't accept any views,
I have no views, no views are pleasing to me.
And he said, well, surely, that view is pleasing to you,
you know, not holding ten of views, it's also a view.
So you had to discern that, in the same sense of,
just stop thinking, I'm not thinking,
well, that's a thought, you're just contradicting yourself
right there and then.
So in the same sense, if you're believing
you're not holding ten of views,
you're kind of in limbo hovering over,
that's a view that you have clearly not aware of.
And for as long as you don't become aware of,
you can't abandon it.
So you have to recognize, you have no choice
but to hold the views.
What you can't use is develop the right views
at the expense of wrong views.
And then hold the right views, then because they're right,
they will take you eventually beyond the views.
And then you become an Arahant,
but even then, I'm not holding any views, no,
I won't be on the views.
So holding, we're not holding, we're both holding,
and now they're holding, they're not holding,
simply doesn't apply anymore, you've dropped it all.
You know, that's another suit, a 38.
Not humanly kind, you know.
Which is, this right view,
as pleasing as it is, as pure as bright.
If you were holding, yeah.
If you were to hold onto this view,
you would not be...
Practicing, placing it, yeah.
You would not understand the damage to be a wrath,
yeah, yeah, it's a wrath, yeah.
See, yes.
And that's what would happen to Aryasavakas
who were not, who didn't reach Arahant,
who kind of got complacent,
like so to say, in the suit,
because basically, they got, you know,
and yeah, the great master's sovereignty
has been destroyed, and so on.
And then please do that, which means they won't be pushing
that view further, they'll just hold onto it,
because they're satisfied with what they got,
basically, they got complacent.
So that's what will happen.
So yes, even the right view.
But yeah, oh, so that's not a bad thing.
I mean, it's a bad thing,
from a rather, it's not fully adequate thing
from the point of view of an Arahant,
but from Pratujana.
Yes, please, by all means,
everybody should try and get the right view
and hold onto it daily, rather than the wrong view.
Because actually, holding onto the right view,
it's, well, you can, because it's a right view,
because you have the right view,
you have the right criteria,
you can see that you're holding onto it.
So you can, like not exert yourself in practice further,
but you know, as Pratujana, the danger is,
you don't know that.
You don't know that you're holding onto those views.
And for as long as you don't know,
there's absolutely no way you can abandon them.
So it's much more dangerous.
It's absolutely, you know,
you're going back to something making sense.
I would have, you know, you have faith, I'd get that makes sense.
But there's always your own effort, you have to,
there's always this, your own effort.
So even though it makes sense,
you're also going to be authentic enough to see it.
I'm, there is no, even though it's pleasant,
this idea, this view, this monk says,
and I really believe what he says.
But you know, I don't really experience what he says,
because I would, I would make that effort.
I would make that effort, so how can I really know?
Making that effort is when I say,
ah, you need, you need to do the drilling on and on and on.
Drilling of the right contemplation, right attending,
drilling of not tolerating unwholesome states,
not tolerating essential flows, not all of those are drilling,
all of these hard work, internal work.
And yeah, that's basically 99%.
You need to do that.
And in the same sense, well,
what this, such and such monk said, it makes sense.
Then you start drilling it, you start applying it,
and then you actually know it's wrong,
and then you will know why it's wrong,
and where it's wrong, and how it's wrong.
This is also this kind of, you can actually see what to do.
So this not only makes sense,
but you, you're able to see what you have to do,
but I guess, like, you're leading on with this.
Oh, yeah, that's the other bit in the suit,
it says he measures the task.
You know exactly how much what needs to be done,
what needs the task that he's mentioned,
it makes sense.
Yeah, you know.
That's it.
Oh, he listen, he hears this, okay.
This, this sounds promising.
Then he ponders on it, he gets some understanding
through reasoning and acceptance.
Okay, and by having the understanding,
that's already like almost like a beginning of wisdom.
By having that discernment, then he can, okay,
so this is what needs to be done.
Because most of the people today, like monks or laypeople,
when he comes to practice,
it's just this vast and biggest blur of everything
and nothing, what needs to be done well,
you just, you know, be here, now, yesterday, tomorrow.
Like, as if you have a choice, but to be here now,
where else can you be?
You make marriage.
So it's just this is a big,
it's weird, mystical, why?
Because they haven't measured the task,
but you did as soon as the Buddha would clearly say,
and people would clearly say,
this needs to be done, so you,
and so knowing what needs to be done,
even as protrusion requires some development of wisdom.
So measuring the task is actually quite a significant stage,
so to speak, no, okay, if I do this,
like I could expect that.
So you know, if I were to apply myself in such a manner,
for certain period of time, I don't know exactly for how long,
but if I keep applying myself in this manner to that extent,
I might be on the way to be free from suffering,
and then you do it.
And having it like that, measure the task,
you won't need any external inspiration,
you won't need, like, download talks and poetry
to kind of make you feel energised to practice, no.
You measure the task, you see the end goal, you do it,
and that's why you do it.
And then you can't blame it, you can't actually,
if you aren't blaming your circumstances or...
Oh yeah, no, it becomes personal.
It becomes, like the said, to be known
in the personal individually by the wise,
by those who are developing wisdom,
to measure the task, to apply themselves,
and then to reach the goal.
It's like seeing, you see what's going on.
Oh, there's nothing to be attained,
there is nothing to be done, there is nothing that,
find me the suited, it says that.
You want?
Cause I don't know.
I mean, you find it in other schools of Buddhism and stuff,
and why?
Because they themselves haven't measured the task,
haven't developed discernment to be able
to have the tools to measure the task.
And all that's because they haven't been transparent
from the beginning, self-transparent.
If you were transparent, you would always be coming
from the place of I want to be free from suffering,
which means you'll never cover it up,
so no matter how pleasing the view is,
how pleasing the teacher is,
how is this freeing you from suffering?
I don't know, I'll give it a bit more, more time, more time.
So you're applying yourself,
and if it's still not making any difference to suffering,
you will drop it, you will move on.
Because that criteria is the fundamental,
and that is the criteria that, yes,
the pathogen I can trust,
like full transparent freedom from suffering.
So you're not, okay, this might be freeing you from suffering,
then you stop and think.
If somebody's to take away this particular practice
that I started engaging in, that I think is freeing
from suffering, would I suffer on a kind of that?
And then I would.
So then you practice on that level even further,
and then you'll see what you were doing was actually freeing
from suffering, all you were just holding onto it,
because it was pleasing to you.
But what if you, what if you, you,
do you want to check on that?
Are these going to, I have to bring.
What if you have a view that if you have no one can take away,
that's the right view, that no matter what way you think of it?
Well, you can't actually reverse it,
you can't see things in a different way.
If you, you could try, you would have to come back.
Come, the axis by doubt.
Yeah.
And that is the right view,
when the feather of doubt disappears.
So you can reach the right view
by fully, transparently, doubting any views that you hold.
Like, don't hold back, don't leave anything unturned.
And then that, which is left, cannot be accessed
by that full-on, cultivated doubt.
Yeah.
And you can see, like, you know, you can doubt this,
you can doubt that, but you can doubt the presence of doubt,
which means there is a, there is a thing present,
which means there is a nature of that thing.
And be doubt or something else,
you can doubt the presence of the thing.
And that's what now it pertains to, that's the beginning.
If you think that calls,
and then you'll be just kind of going further or further away
from any doubt, in that sense.
Yes, sir.
Because, well, there is happiness present.
Oh, there is resistance present.
Oh, there is sensuality present.
Oh, there is doubt present.
Well, all those things have become a thing present.
Yeah.
And there's no doubt about that.
And there is no doubt that can even access that.
Like, you can doubt particular aspects,
often a reason thing, but you can doubt the arising of the thing,
which is why the inside of Sotapana comes from the very bottom.
Whatever has the nature of arising has the nature of seeing.
Doesn't say this, which has the, no, whatever,
be doubt, be sensuality, be happiness, being sent,
whatever has the nature of arising for that reason has the nature of seeing.
Or, rather, for that reason, it's impermanent.
And that's another topic I'm about.
It's spoken about it in different talks as well,
but things are not impermanent because you watch their destruction,
watch their disappearance.
They're impermanent because they are rose.
They came to be.
That's why they're impermanent.
One could have that view, or not doubt that view.
One could see it, but it is impossible to not have...
You don't necessarily release it from Tukka.
Oh, yes.
You won't be.
He takes now repetition of that right view on and on and on,
until it kind of saturates your experience as a whole
and flushes out all the ignorance and origin.
But you can still have no doubt, in a way.
You think that, like, no, you can have?
Well, you can have no doubt, but, like, that's just the first step.
Now, you have to keep applying that view, which is inaccessible to doubt.
But if you're not applying it, you're just holding that view
and you're not doing anything else.
Yeah, sure.
You go to the great view of that beyond the doubt.
But I'm not saying it's a good one.
Well, it's not a sin. And that's why you have even those, like,
Dhamma Nusari and Sadhana Nusari, this kind of contusion is,
they will attain to the path, but they will not sub one as yet.
Is this...
Dhamma Nusari and Sadhana Nusari, whether they came through faith,
or they came through the Dhamma investigation and reasoning.
They will arrive at the path, eventually.
So, yeah, you can get the view, but again, as I said,
it's a gradual drilling repetition that it's sort of, like,
bit by bit, by bit, by bit, undoing your ignorance.
And as the Buddha said, you can't say,
oh, today, my ignorance has been undone this much.
Yesterday, that much, tomorrow, it will be this much.
No, it's like the carpenter using the axe every day for years.
Every day, he grabs that axe, that the handle is wearing thin.
But he can't say, yes, they're different today.
Oh, this is how much it wore off.
But after a year of using it, he can come and wonder, he can look.
Oh, my goodness.
My axe handle is very thin.
Look, completely worn out.
Because, as I said, a person who is, who is gone beyond doubt,
but that person would see, then, that it's, you can't doubt his view,
but he's not getting any further on account of his own effort
that he's making or not making.
That might have strengthened his putting into the practice
or furthering that view, or developing that view.
You know what I mean?
So, not only is you, beyond doubt, but you're also
beyond doubt that any further development is due to my own effort.
Yeah, yeah.
That's why, like, whatever it was to be obtained
by the male and the half of the man in Australia, I've obtained,
basically, it's completely on you.
You know, you can't, you know, it's just others,
like people, and even Alacada's circles,
and anything, it's irrelevant.
For as long as you have the living functioning mind,
as you say, once you get the right view,
there is nothing standing in between you and other handship
except your lack of effort.
Nothing else.
There is nothing else that can come in the way,
which is why it can't be taken away
because it wasn't given to you externally either.
It's something you develop fully, and it's like a one-way,
one-way development.
You can't undo it.
But nothing except yourself stands in the way you get to know this.
I don't know if you remember this quote.
The story says a guard is made free from all troubles
on account of nature.
So we, but the sage is free from all troubles.
On account of his own effort.
So he's better.
He's even stronger than a guard.
Because he's not, well, exactly, he's stronger than a guard
because gold was not strong because they were given.
Yeah, it was just given to him.
You were given, huh?
You think you were granted?
You didn't have to develop anything.
Absolutely.
We've seen the sensors again as external things.
Because if I think about my eye,
I see that as an external thought by my facial eye.
The problem there is that in regard to that thought,
you're having like a tacit, implicit assumption
that the eye is something more internally.
So you can think of those things.
Why do you at the same time assume to find your eye
in the direction of internal inside of you or whatever.
But if you look at yourself in the mirror,
that eye that you see in the mirror,
that is that eye because of which you're able
to look at that eye in the mirror in the first place.
That very reflection there of that flesh-y organ
is that object.
So you're saying it doesn't go further than what?
There is no further than that.
It closes upon itself.
The assumption takes you further into infinity whereby
you would see the reflection of yourself
seeing the reflection of yourself seeing the reflection
and think, wow.
But actually, all the whole thing would be swept in a second
if you remove the flesh-y eye, if you destroy it.
So that whole infinity of your perception
or whatever else, it's impermanent.
It might be infinite, but it doesn't last forever.
Why? Because if flesh-y eyes gone.
Excellent death, sickness, aging, whatever.
Gone.
The whole infinity is gone.
Your sight is gone.
Why? Because that flesh-y eye was that because of which
the whole domain of sight was present.
So that's why that's it.
And you'll never see like a one, two, three, four, five
a linear connection.
So you have to contemplate.
You have to fabricate it in the beginning.
It's abstract, but that's only because it doesn't apply
to your experience.
But you have to make it apply to your experience.
We're going to drill in on and on and on.
Drill in a throat, literally.
Establet, define it, think it, and then establish it.
The thought that those flesh-y organs are that
because of which I am alive here thinking, intending,
looking, smelling, touching.
Those flesh-y organs disappear.
All of this cannot remain standing even for a split-second longer.
And in the beginning, it's an abstract thought.
But you keep drilling it.
Then it will stay longer and longer and longer.
And then when it stays longer enough,
you start seeing things through that thought.
You start seeing things through the right view.
When it takes root.
When you say those senses, those senses of
nothing more than what I experienced now.
That is the senses.
What I say, the flesh organ, that worth.
I think that is it.
That's something you also see through your senses.
But that you can know that is that because of which
your senses are there in the first place.
Turning.
Well, it's here.
Yeah, it's like kind of closes upon itself.
It doesn't go, it's not anywhere else, out of there.
Right there, right now.
You can look yourself in the mirror.
Look at your eyes in the mirror.
And you'll see how you assume,
like as if you were behind them inside somewhere,
left or right.
But if you then don't let your thought
or rather if you anchor your thought
in that reflection of that flesh organ
as the original determination.
Yeah, that's our solution.
Yeah.
So if you look yourself in the mirror
and you see your eyes,
and then you can okay this whole like the face
and the reflection, the nose and stuff,
you can kind of see that,
okay, that's just organ.
But pin it down to the eyes in your eyes
and you kind of think the life is behind that
eye, your sense of self, you are.
But if you look at it,
and what you see,
you see a black circle,
a blind dot.
In the center of the flesh,
you all know.
And you realize,
that's it.
It stops there.
It starts there, it doesn't go beyond there.
It's that flesh that I'm looking at,
is that because of which I'm able to look.
So there are two dimensions,
simultaneous pleasant.
One is this material dimension of the flesh eye,
and the one is like simultaneously present dimension
of awareness in regard to it.
But there is not a collinear that behind the eyes
it goes and you look in eyes
at whether the window is a soul.
And they're just a flat wall.
And it's so cool.
The soul is in front of it.
The thoughts are in front of it.
They can't access that measure.
They can't enter it.
They separate the main.
But it's that assumption of that quick eye movement
that makes you,
well, it makes you maintain that assumption.
Sorry, it's not assumption of quick eyes move fast.
It helps you maintain that assumption easily.
Because your intentionality is measured by the movement.
Things you do.
Things you intend with your body,
your body, your speech, your mind.
Say your whole body is paralyzed.
You can always like move the eyes.
It's basically when the eyes are motionless,
well, it's dead.
Like eyes are dead.
But even those eyes,
the quickest movement,
it's still just a flesh yoga.
In the same sense, your hand is,
your nails are, your hair is.
Your spectacles are, your robes are.
Flesh, material, matter,
rupa.
But this matter is that because of which
there is that awareness in regard to it anyway.
In the first place.
So it's just like two completely separate
domains of matter
and then awareness in regard to the matter
is separable from each other.
You can't have one without your inconceivable.
You can't just think of matter because in a sense,
you're thinking of matter
which means there's awareness in regard to matter.
No, can you just have pure awareness,
which is ridiculous.
Can you have pure awareness
if your matter is destroyed?
You can't.
You can assume that there is a pure awareness
that divine and whatever else,
there isn't.
But you see yourself in regard to your body?
Yes, certainly.
It will always remain an assumption
because you can never find out.
That there is an assumption,
an assumption,
a sorry, an awareness
free from your
free from the material
aspect of life
of your body.
There isn't.
Not in good faith,
that is,
because you can't,
if you look at it,
if you look at your experience as a whole
and even if you conceive it,
no matter how pleasing that conception is,
that your awareness can be separate,
the very reality of your practice
of the present moment shows you that,
well,
I'm thinking that my awareness is separate
while I'm all determined,
but this matter,
thus, I'm not separate.
So you can only assume it,
in the same sense,
you can only assume the matter
as independent of you.
Because that's a thought,
which is you,
in that sense.
So that's why a matter
finds footing.
It finds footing,
basically, in your experience.
Because you provided,
you assumed it.
But if you see,
the flesh-y eye,
he's saying pure matter.
Well, the four great elements find footing,
which is how you conceive
the existence of matter.
So you assume the eyes are yours,
means those eyes have found the foot,
those flesh-y lumps,
organs have found the footing,
they exist for you,
their mind.
But as I said,
all you're going to see,
flesh-y eyes,
moving left or right,
whatever,
with a black iris
in the center.
But all of that is out there.
There is nothing,
like if you go through
that black iris,
you just find, you know,
blood and liquid,
whatever else,
eyes have.
So there is no,
there is that direction of matter,
and that's it.
If you drill further,
you'll find a matter,
more matter,
or same matter,
depending on how generally
you look at it.
So what you have to do
is stop assuming
that you are behind that matter.
And you can stop assuming
that you are behind that matter,
if you drill long enough
thought that you are not
behind that matter,
where you have to keep drilling it,
and drilling it,
and drilling it
until it takes the root.
And when it does,
then see you're unized,
your own movement,
your own senses will not
reduce the assumption
of self behind those senses.
So there is both of that.
It's not descending into the mouth.
That's a whole.
Not descending into your eyes.
Not descending into eyes.
Not descending into matter.
Not taking up matter.
Not assuming it.
But in more practical terms,
being mindful of your body as a whole
means your mind won't descend into it.
So to speak,
whereby you end up acting
performing bodily acts
carelessly.
Not descending into your mouth.
Literally, your mind
not descending into your mouth,
will make you aware of what you're saying
and what is coming out of your mouth.
So you won't make you act carelessly.
And then not having your
chip that descends
like in your own mind.
Not getting complacent there,
which means that even your thoughts
you'll be aware of
and you won't be thinking carelessly.
Because if you don't descend
or mindful in a proper way
of your mind as an external
seeing it externally,
in a proper way,
just holding that way of seeing.
Then you start really
talking about giants.
So that's...
Yeah, yeah.
Like if you make a practice out of it
out of establishing your mind
well upon those certain things,
like thinking and pondering,
overcoming the speech determination
and so on, then yeah.
But there are many different ways
of establishing your mind.
Janas are just one of them.
Like you know, establishing your mind
upon the perception of forest.
So when you're going to town,
none of the perceptions
that come from the town
can access you,
or bother you,
or cause you harm,
because your mind is
establishing upon the
great perception of forest.
Then you recognize,
okay, so I'm free from the disturbances
that come based on the perceptions
from the town.
But if there are perceptions
that if there are disturbances
coming on a kind of perception
in the forest,
I will be disturbed.
So why don't I develop my mind
and establish my mind
upon something even greater?
So that then even forest
cannot disturb me.
So then you can establish your mind
upon the perception of Earth.
Very establishing your mind
on the perception of Earth.
Does it mean actually
holding the perception of Earth
infantibly, personally?
No.
It's basically finding it,
like discerning it in things.
So then you don't need to hold it
because it's already implied
in those things.
You're not fabricating anything.
You're not creating it.
The most obvious,
maybe a bit crude example,
would be, well,
what is town
and forest
and the mountains
and the oceans
for that matter
having common.
Yes.
Well, it's in the reason thing.
Right.
What is there the reason thing?
Those are the reason things.
What are they having common?
Well, they do having common the fact
that they're on Earth.
They're part of Earth.
They have the solid aspect.
That phenomenon of solidity
or immobility
or Earth,
you want to call it,
you establish your mind upon that.
It's an abstraction now
because your mind is unestablished.
But if you have it at the background
of your mind,
like anchored in the notion of solid
in everything,
even the runny water,
your mind will get established.
That's how the casinos work,
in the same sense.
That's what casinos are.
So you would establish your mind
in something that comes
on a particular level
can disturb you
because your mind
has been established
to that much greater
element of solidity
in everything
particular that you're experiencing.
So you literally surpassed
the whole domain of particular things,
which is everything,
or whatever.
But if you
have had a thought
like the other,
well, you establish your mind
on a thought-general thought.
So any thought that you have,
or you establish your mind
on mind.
Well, there would be the casinos consciousness,
which is the most refined of all of them
and they would come kind of last.
The thing is,
you can just establish your mind
upon the general experience
as a whole right here right now.
But make sure that it's not divorced
from that material aspect.
The material end of it,
so to speak.
So that's why,
if you come from the material end of it,
you'll make sure you don't overlook it.
So you are here now.
If there is any disturbance to arise,
it would be on account of your presence here.
On the head,
or in the central street,
I'm going this area,
or whatever.
Obviously,
now you have, like,
phones,
emails,
stuff like that.
So disturbance can arise.
But again,
even that would arise
through your current situation here.
Basically,
on account of your senses,
on account of things
that can actually be through your senses.
You can abandon your senses.
But then nothing that enters your senses
will pertain to you,
it will pertain to the abandoned senses.
So it's not yours,
not your problem,
not your suffering.
So that's why there are many different ways
of establishing your mind,
but it's the same principle
of establishing your mind.
That's why the Buddha,
when he spoke about the casinos,
he would go out,
otherwise,
manage to establish
his mind upon the great element of earth,
on account of that,
he abandoned everything in failure to it.
And what is inferior
to the phenomenon of earth,
that thought of earth,
gender of earth,
you basically,
anything more particular
than that is inferior
to that phenomenon of earth.
And then he said,
but obviously,
he can be still
liable to disturbance
on account of that,
gender of phenomenon,
obviously,
it's much less disturbance
than the particular.
This disturbance,
as they can arise,
if you're not
established upon the element of earth.
But then,
that thought that has seen
the gratification,
the tension,
this cave,
in regard to the casinos of earth,
seen that he knew it,
and he won't be on through that knowledge,
so he's not bothered
by the either.
So, yeah,
there is establishing mind upon a casina,
or whatever,
and then there is no event,
as well.
So in time,
it's very just not descending into a thing.
Well, not, yeah,
not collapsing,
mindfulness,
or like,
and collapsing mindfulness,
doesn't mean that, you know,
you need to constantly keep your mind in front of you.
No, it means you need to anchor your mind.
So, you can,
whether you're talking now,
sit,
standing,
walking,
anybody posture,
means the body is there,
means,
the earth element is there,
the water element is there,
means,
the fire element is there,
the air element is there.
You can take any of it.
They're kind of slightly more defined,
but,
you can just be,
sorry,
you know,
you don't even take any of them,
it's just take the body,
the body is there.
That's enough.
You don't even have to take the body,
just take this kind of posture is there,
when that posture changes,
take that posture is there,
because that's the thing.
Whatever these step-onses
can enter you,
right now,
you would be,
while you're sitting.
It would be,
while your body is seated,
the senses are liable to such and such.
So, you anchor your mind,
in the seated position of your body.
When you get up,
you anchor your mind.
Or,
you anchor your mind
in the notion of the body is there.
And obviously,
if you are thinking it in front of you,
you're not anchored.
You're anchored when you stop thinking it,
when you're just discerning it,
when you're just seeing it
in the background of your mind.
Then,
that's what means being anchored.
Literally,
you throw an anchor,
and then you forget about it,
because you're anchored.
But you know that it's there.
You don't have to keep pulling it out and throwing it.
You don't have to keep holding onto it,
because it's anchored.
Okay, leave.
Let the boat float,
left and right,
whatever it wants to go.
If it goes too far,
it starts dragging the anchor,
I,
if it's easy to be anchored,
then restart it.
Reestablish your mind.
And I'm not talking about
four, like sitting, you know, cross-legged,
and I'm talking about
daily life,
anchoring your mind,
because that's what establishing your mind is.
Like, he enters and abides,
the first genre.
He enters and abides this.
He establishes his mind,
like, enters and abides the perceptions of forest,
and then he goes to the town
for picked up out of whatever else,
and he's not bothered by anything in that town,
because his mind is still fully anchored
in the perceptions of the forest.
So it's no question
of acting and doing stuff
while you're establishing,
because that's how it works.
That's what establishment means.
Now, it's like,
oh, I can establish my mind only
when I don't do anything,
clock the door,
and just sit and stare at the wall.
Because it's discerning,
the more general.
So whether you're here
or there or here and there,
that means your body has to be there.
Have a notion of your body.
Let it be as remote as it wants to be,
but have it present in the back of your mind,
what are you doing other things?
And that's the important bit,
while.
Because that's how you can discern
this principle of simultaneous presence.
Now, but I'll stop this
because I'm doing that.
You stop only on wholesome stuff.
Because that obviously
undermines the whole picture.
But then,
while you're anchored,
or even if you don't do anything,
that's a form of doing.
Okay.
I am refraining from activity,
which is my current activity.
So while my mind is anchored,
established in the presence of the body there,
I'm refraining from any particular activity.
Fine.
As long as you're mindful.
In that correct sense.
Not mindful like in a,
like modern psychology sense,
or whatever new age sense,
or just be mindful.
Mindfulness needs to be understood.
The principle of anchoring needs to be
a bit sati-patanas.
And for that, you need the right view.
So while you're sitting here,
thinking trying to formulate the next question,
or the same more to glorification,
you can still have a vague distance
and the biggest notion of your body present
at the back of your mind.
And that's practice of anchoring.
Because that doesn't require the direct effort.
Because if it's a direct effort,
it means it's not anchoring.
So yeah, you start with the direct effort,
only to leave it
and kind of seep in the background
with our losing sight of it.
And eventually it becomes effortless
because you can't lose the sight of it.
Because the particular instances of this body
are maintaining the nature of
bodies there.
So it's right there in front of you.
Anyhow.
The earth element is right there
for as long as you're alive.
So you have to keep thinking about it.
But you need to let it go in the background
and then just certainly there.
And when it's certainly there,
then well, that kind of becomes a foreground almost.
Your mind is established.
You see the boundary.
If something is present,
you see the boundary, I think.
What do you mean?
You see the body.
Everything else is happening.
But what do you mean by boundary?
I guess the extent.
Ah, the extent of it.
Well, whatever is happening,
whatever is happening,
whatever might happen,
it will happen for as long as
or on account of the presence of the body right here right there.
Right now.
So you don't just say,
you don't have to chase after it.
You don't have to, oh,
how did this happen in the past?
How did you move this head?
No, you know.
For as long as,
that's what an other hand
would kind of completely remove the ignorance whatsoever.
He said,
any disturbance that is left
are on account of this
like leaking body right here
until that body breaks apart
and then even that won't be.
But that disturbance for him
is just the disturbance of, you know,
pain, enduring, and so on.
Not disturbance in terms of causing him,
suffering and duke,
he's beyond that.
He's just a nuisance.
Any nuisance that was left
is on account of this body
for as long as it's functioning.
And that breaks apart.
That's it.
There won't be another body taking up.
Does it?
Yeah, things like,
if one does practice correctly,
well, there's no assumption.
There's no assuming.
The senses.
You're practicing in a way.
So, mindfulness is not becoming confused.
You could experience nibbana.
Yeah.
But it's not about experience nibbana.
But it's not established.
It's not established in exactly.
Yeah.
That's why,
putugenus can experience nibbana.
It's nibbana.
But because the putugenus
there won't be a nibbana.
But in terms of experience,
it is that which nibbana is.
That's that.
Imagine my hundred.
Oh, I forgot.
Long time ago.
Hundred and something.
Hundred and twenty.
Twenty, maybe.
When he said that,
when he talks about different,
different establishments
that putugenus can have,
but because he conceives them
to be his, for him,
he assumes them.
So, he goes to the point,
where he says,
he thinks,
I am, this is nibbana.
I am nibbana.
I am entering nibbana.
This nibbana is mine.
And the Buddha said,
although,
that is actually nibbana,
what he's talking about.
He is not established in it.
Not descending,
nor having it developed,
because he's still thinking,
I am.
So, nibbana is just basically
experienced without read-aversion delusion.
Imagine if you establish yourself
in that twenty-four-seven.
Until it takes its roots
and then it just takes,
it goes off on its own.
And you can drop the whole thing.
And there is absolutely no cracks
in the wall anymore
that nothing can enter you.
It's just dumb.
And that's what nibbana is.
That's why sometimes
all the Buddha
would give would be the general instruction,
oh, I'm staying from anything unwholesome.
Cultivate wholesome.
Thank you, Lord.
I'm going to retreat now
for three months
and practice this profound teaching
just gave me,
and then they come out,
and they're all hands.
Just that.
Because fundamentally,
it is just that,
but you have to stick to it.
I stick to it to the point
of complete self-transparency,
no maintaining of beliefs
and views on a kind of
being pleasant to you,
no maintaining on a kind of
protection of anxiety
because you're afraid,
no maintaining it,
no maintaining on a kind of
form,
well,
sensuality,
fear,
anything.
You have to really
open up internally
for it,
and stick to it.
And it will not do things,
and then you will see
it and do it,
and then you know that it's working.
But yeah, understanding
what nibbana is,
like, not just all this,
but knowing,
rightly, what nibbana is,
are in not appropriating it,
as putuginana.
It means to become
a solid one.
Now establishing yourself
in that nibbana eventually,
means becoming another one.
Because you're not
assuming the senses
as there is a
restraining the senses,
guiding the senses in a way.
Well, guiding the senses in
a restraining will prevent
the proliferation of that assumption.
But obviously, just restraint
for somebody who doesn't know
what else to look for,
you want to mind too much more.
Yeah, guiding the senses in a sense.
Guiding so you prevent the kind of
heaviest that you know,
you should know a wrongly
based upon the wrong assumptions,
preventing them from spreading
and being establishing
and just harassing you.
And obviously, when you are not
leaking left and right,
then you'll address what's
there contained.
So yeah, that's what is
strained.
CLI has to come first.
And if I read the translation,
I'm dying calm.
I'm dying.
Because things are not
wavy, you know,
pushed around in the bushes.
You see the extent of things.
And that's not going to
jump in over there,
assuming more than there is.
Yeah, the proliferation.
From left and right,
up and down.
Fueled by design and craving
and confusion and doubt.
And all the other features.