So, what was your question, can you repeat it?
Meditation.
So, my question was that I didn't practice in meditation and I was here about meditations
and I've done two different techniques but when you say meditation I don't really know
like when then I do it, I don't know I just do it but if it's the proper way I'm doing
it, if I'm just looking myself, it's just, um, my technique.
One thing to get out of the way is only so-to-poin and can meditate properly so there is no
samasama, without samadhi, so coming from that point of view you can see how silly the
idea of a technique is that you can teach to others whereby they just emulate and mechanic
properly repeat it, kind of leads automatically to wisdom or something.
It doesn't, it leads to an experience of novelty or for kind and again, in connection
to what I said half an hour ago, previous recording was repeating something thousands
of times, right, based on your discernment, based on your faith, you know that these
attending things like this is most likely right so you repeat, repeat, repeat, repeat, repeat,
repeat thousands of times and then you get a confirmation, you get wisdom.
You discern, oh it is right, what I've been doing.
So getting a template technique that can sometimes somehow lead you to that right state
is a rather, well it's obvious that it's kind of impossible because if I tell you a technique
that works for everyone and everything, it doesn't mean it doesn't require you to be
discerning anything, it just requires you to repeat these observances and these procedures
that I prescribed for you, observe the nostrils when this happens, you do that, when you
do that.
So it's not about like understanding, it's not about doing certain things, I'll tell
you, you will understand, you will get knowledge, if you are mindful of your shoulders and
you watch your breath in and you watch your breath out, how would it bring any understanding?
At most that will make you experience certain things, oh a novelty experience of your body
in this shape or that form or whatever else, but that is nothing to do with discerning
and understanding because in order to discern and understand you need to know what you're
supposed to discern and understand.
If I tell you observe your act of breathing, seeing it as impermanent, seeing it as close
of suffering, well that's a different thing, but that's not really a technique, isn't it?
You can't say somebody, oh we'll try to understand things being given beforehand, which is
the reason for you not being able to own them in the first place, you can't present that
as a technique.
I can say it, it can make sense to you, you can attend things like that, but that's
the most that it can be and it doesn't need to be anything more than that.
So you know, I know for a fact lots of people get upset when you dismiss the techniques
or whatever they are, all the techniques have been helping me or whatever, what you as
a protrusion, they have no criteria of what health is, your criteria is, it feels good,
feels better.
So the absolutely the first step is to get a right view, then you'll know how to meditate.
So if you don't have a right view, then your meditation should be about gaffing the right
view, because when you say that meditation is dwelling on the view that you have attained,
dwelling on your right view, is meditation.
Yeah, yeah, exactly.
So, but there is other meditation.
There are many kinds of meditation, yeah, but only this one is the right one, as the Buddha
said himself, I think we'll have spoke that well, I'll look at that and I said, you premeditated,
overmeditated, undermeditated, mismeditated and so on, but he doesn't meditate and then
he compares it to a dog waiting for a hair or a jackal or a cat waiting for a mouse praying
upon something, that's usually what people's meditation is.
And you realize, if you look at all these techniques that have been to, that is actually
in common.
It's all about by observing, observing, looking as close as possible, praying, waiting,
waiting, and then it happens.
So it's all about getting an experience of a novelty kind, anything.
And no doubt you will sooner or later, why?
Because all the efforts you're putting in, all the efforts are close observation, but all
you're going to get is something you get when you look at things closer.
But if that's all that's required for wisdom and niban and understanding, he wouldn't
need the Buddha to tell you how to do it and the whole formulation of the dharma in like
a great, great detail and so on, none of that would be necessary then for anyone.
Because all you have to do is just look at things closer, if you look at things closer
as a pathogener, with your ignorance, all you're doing is looking closer at your ignorance.
And no knowledge can arise from that, because people are not going to think, you just need
to chop everything, just sit and be like a baby, steal or whatever else.
And don't judge, just go back to do whatever, promote the old state and that will teach you
what you need to know.
That's ridiculous.
True and true, experience we talked about in being affected by a Vija means whatever you
choose to stay with in your experience will be affected by that a Vija.
Everything is corrupted for the Tujana.
That's why I said, you can't accidentally step outside of your ignorance, why?
Because a repetition is required.
And in order to know that a repetition of something is the right thing, you get each other
ignorance, you need to be told, then you need to do it.
And doing is not just sitting and staring and waiting for things to teach you, because
things are affected with ignorance as much as you are, why?
Because they are part of your experience.
So everything top to bottom is affected with a Vija.
So even when you sit and meditate like that, all you're going to do is the meditate around
your Vija.
Which is not accidental that those people who are very much in technique will get upset
if somebody dismisses their techniques.
How would you get upset?
So the Tujana can't get upset if somebody disparages the Dhamma or whatever it was at all.
He will clearly know that person doesn't know what they're talking about, but he wouldn't
upset him.
It's just impossible to take it personally.
We said that also that the only, like if you're not assertive on it, during all sorts
of techniques, the best thing you can do, which is a kind of meditation in a way, it's
like trying to understand, to dwell on the suitors and go through them and to understand
each point so thoroughly.
That's an meditation in a proper sense of what?
You're reflecting with your own experience, because again, like even the first jhana which
is part of that meditation, it's thinking and pondering, or it's not an anomaly that
is actually thinking and exploration of the right things.
So it's just basically being whether you meditate or not, it's whether, when I say meditate,
whether you sit down cross leg or whatever posture you prefer, you're doing the same thing.
You're pursuing the right view and then the principles of the right view of the right
insight.
So you can do it more actively or more passively, but it's still the same thing.
So when you get the right view, then you can sit in the summer and practice the summer
tab.
But it doesn't mean forgetting about your right view and observing your kneecaps and shoulders
and top of your head and roof or your mouth and nostrils and your lungs.
It's just ridiculous.
Well, you can observe those things correctly from the salayatuna point of view and then
see how your body is just the composure of equal external element elements as the objects
around you are, upon which you directly stand as a your mind, your personality, and everything
else, and then disown it.
Why?
Because eyes, roof, your mouth, shoulder, kneecaps, is all given beforehand, what I was
saying before, yet your life, as you know it, your past, your future, is inconceivable
to be inseparable, to be independent of this living body.
So this living body, less than two meters tall, full of organs, like a, like a, you know,
a sack of, sack of beans tied at the top, which is different types inside, that is the
reason.
That is the necessary cause, necessary condition for your whole life, for early emotions,
everything you've been through, everything you would go through, and you can't conceive
it if there's no, not, not, not, not a living body.
Thus, if that body comes to die, everything comes to an end, in that sense.
To recognize that you have no input over that body, no say, no control over it.
Any control you can exhibit is like what I spoke before, it's a movement along the given
lines, before, they were given beforehand.
So then you realize your whole life, whatever you've done, whatever you chose to do, your
volition, it all determined by this external thing, it's because of it, over which you
have no say, and now you can't ask for better meditation in that.
Get that inside, get that thought, and then dwell on it, dwell on it, dwell on it.
That's the repetition I was talking about, that's meditation, when meditation leads to wisdom,
not when meditation leads to some mystical novelty states, oh, I fell this trembling,
when I fell so peaceful, I fell this, I fell that, yeah, teach you get understanding
at the end of your meditation.
Lots of people don't have that kind of armor, I might give myself that, if you're sitting
and to go and go watch your thought or think about a subject, what it seems to be better
for a person, is writing it out and actually writing things, not for publication, but actually
writing it out, describing it as I see it.
In a way that's what I think I should be doing, obviously with my, because as I'm doing
that writing, I have to bring most of that.
You have to dwell on it.
You have to dwell on it until it crystallizes to the extent that you're able to put it
in the words.
You don't just let it skim all of it, because you don't stop to kind of clarify anything
for yourself.
It is clarifying, but it's difficult, because you're mind skipping this way that way.
Exactly, because not used to clarifying the nature of things, so your meditation should
enable you to do that, so it's not accidental that meditation results in the stillness
of the mind.
It means clarity increases, the mind is jumpy less, so you look at things more clearly.
Again it's the same things you're trying to understand.
People have this notion whereby, okay, you're trying to study, you contemplate, you reflect,
and now it's a time for formal meditation.
When you don't do that, you do formal meditation.
What is formal meditation sitting down with your robot?
What is formal meditation, following a technique, what is formal, like watching your breath
or whatever?
But why do you do all of that in the first place?
Because you're going to be free from suffering.
And who knows the way that leads you out of suffering, it's at least a certain point.
So why don't you spend all of your time trying to become a certain person?
And you will know how to meditate and what to do and how to do it.
But I notice as well, like I struggle to do breath meditation, that's, you know, I try
to do it, but then I don't mind one is off whatever, but if I write about it, I end up
being calm.
You know, because then I bring it, you do it in the end, that's the way I'm holding
it all the time, so then, so it actually, I'm doing it without doing it the traditional
way, you know, by writing about it.
Tradition of way is a dignified way, because the tradition is written by people, by
protugionists, by people who are not on the way to become out of house.
And that's not just an empty dismissal, it's just that if you look at it, people who
compile, compile commentaries and everything, they themselves said they were protugionists,
famous commentaries and so on.
You read the sutras, if the techniques were such a crucial factor, why would they never
talk about it, why there is not a single technique?
There's something I've got to notice as well, like the reason, what I can understand
or what I can intellectually comprehend, is that the reason the arahats later on, doing
write in the commentaries or they didn't do anything, it's just the putridionist that
kept on writing things and adding things, is that they notice that they don't need
for anything more than the sutras.
More than enough, yeah, yeah, everything, all of the stuff that's been written later on,
the preaching is now obscuring those things, because it's been written so long ago that
now people take it to be the same.
But you read the sutras and all the Buddha talks about all the time, he's understanding,
developing, understanding, but he full understanding, he always results in full understanding, whatever
approach of the practice you take, full understanding, what full understanding you get from having
a mystical experience that overwhelms you, he's absolutely no understanding there, not
even mindfulness often.
So discernment, knowing the cause of suffering, like knowing the gratification, knowing the
escape in regard to sensuality, in regard to various mental states, knowing the origin,
knowing the gratification, knowing the escape, like knowing, like really, fully understanding,
not analyzing, not getting all the facts, but fully understanding, penetrating with your
mind, knowing it.
And that's all, that's what it's all about, understanding the nature of things, understanding
the nature of things, results in freedom from suffering.
So I'm going back to my earlier question that, if I say, for the current state of mind
if I'm being reflective about my thoughts and my actions, and if I'm trying to be as
mindful as possible, is that meditation for my current state of mind?
Yes, you can say that, but obviously be mindful as possible, again, the better you know
what mindfulness is, the more established in mindfulness you are.
So it's not just a state you emulate, you also want to understand what is presence of
mind, what is the nature of it, what else appears there when I think I'm mindful.
Well, mainly you're unsure, ignorance of what, what is, you see directly, you're not.
You want to be, you want to be like investigating at the same time, not just kind of, when you
sit and meditate, again, you want to meditate together as you.
You can't get the right view accidentally, so you can't just sit and be mindful of here
now, present moment, and then learn from it.
The only way you can learn from it is if you know why you're supposed to learn, if you
know why you're supposed to look for in things, otherwise you're just staying with your
ignorance, and you'll be as ignorant on the thousand day as you were on a day one.
So reading the sutras, and then if you want to sit and meditate the sutras, and then
there will be parts that will kind of make sense to an extent, or at least seem promising
that you might go, there is something to this, I could, what is in mind, I could perhaps
understand is better, and then take that to your meditation, and then dwell on it in
that sense that the Tanya was saying, don't just let it, you know, slip or slide, if you
need to, you write it down or whatever, but you want to plurify it.
And that's the thing, you know, I remember when I was doing work in meditation, and I got
into a lot, and you kind of just, in a pondering on the sutras and various things, and I might
have said this many times before, and you know, like the five aggregates, and then you
just think about the five aggregates, but then it occurred to me, well, when I read the
sutras that say consciousness or they talk about matter or feelings, why do I think
did I understood by the thought, what consciousness refers to, what feelings refer to, whatever
I, other aggregated with the mentions, why, why do I, why did I assume that I know what
they're refers to?
And then, then I started thinking, okay, so what is matter then, can I explain to myself
what Rupa is in my experience right here, right now, while I'm explaining it?
And then I went like that for every aggregate, and you realize that you don't really have
a clear idea, you just assumed, you just picked up and you have a vague kind of ambiguous
concocted concept of it, but if you stop and think, okay, when I say consciousness, consciousness
or if I say feeling, feeling, what does that exactly stand for, is there a clarity that
you don't know, and then you realize, well, that's what the practice is, undoing all these
wrong views and wrong concepts and misconceptions and misconceiving the things, that you just
stood for granted now, so now when even you come, even when you come to practice, the
stuff you did in the sort of, well, you approach it with same polluted concepts, tools,
not understood things, that you never question, you just start building on top of them, your
practice of Dhamma, so it's no wonder you end up following weird, various intense techniques
searching after praying upon like those animals in the sutras that the Buddha says, pray upon
its prey, wait for it, for novelty states, for mystical experiences, take you over, as
a form of validation or confirmation of what you've been doing, so your whole spiritual
life would be misdirected, because you never actually re-evaluated the very kind of basics,
and when you did, if you did, if you were, then you would realize, oh, the practice is
actually in a completely different direction, it's the direction of undoing, so that things
can be recognized correctly, not in finding out and rediscovering or something, like something
has been obscured, and you just, no, it's, well, it was obscured, you can say it was obscured,
by your own misconceiving, so you want to be able, that when you say to yourself, feeling
feeling, that statement, that designation stands directly, for that which feeling is
in your experience right there, and then, if there is no that clarity, that, well, there
you go, there's a work laid out for you, and you can specifically take feelings, because
craving is regard to feelings, and that's the whole point, learning how to feel and overcome
the feeling, thus, never ever again, experiencing suffering, the Buddha said, my teaching is, for
the one who feels, and he teaches only two things, suffering and fear for me.
I actually find a bit of an advantage, personally, for me, that when I approach it, with both
languages, it gives two different descriptions to each individual of the phrase, or it can
be, yeah, we get closer, closer to the meaning, in a sense, when you kind of, you look at
the parli, you learn the parli, then you look at different translations, different angles,
that all becomes necessary, but not for a scholastic purpose, but for the purpose of
clarifying, because you see, it's not about, again, finding out some, some, some, some divine
providence, mystical light, it's about undoing, your wrong views, so that you recognize
what the right view is, and when it comes to undoing, that's the whole point, you need
to have as clear as possible, instruction, so you know what to look for, like the utterance
of another, well, the Buddha's not around anymore, and, actually, even when he was, he referred
to a miracle of instruction, so being able to convey the dhamma to somebody, and they
fully understand it, and then become Arachandra Khandrava, equals to miracle, why bad will
you see yourself, because we all take things in terminology, to mean, you know, sometimes
completely, sometimes slightly different things, but even a slight variation in what it means
for me, when I uttered it for him, can be quite a lot at the end of the line, like you
imagine a boat or a ship is setting on a course, and in the beginning, you know, it doesn't
matter if it's a meter to the left, a meter to the right, but after, you know, thousands
of miles of journey, that tiny little kind of variation will result in missing a whole
continent, so that's where you want to get as much, because you don't have a criteria
about right or wrong, so you want to try to clarify for yourself as much as you can,
so that then you kind of decrease the chances of being wrong, later on, or at least not
go too far off, I like to, let's come to a mind from this, and I think in a mind from
what that is, because this is thinking about it, clarifying that, which is quite helpful,
because then you can look at things better, you can try to do certain things better once
you know how to be mindful, because most people must be, must be, oh, I can be mindful,
I've just been being here and now present, but then you kind of, then how do you, well
exactly, because when you realize, yeah, you can be mindful, but if you have lots of wrong
view, you'll be mindful with your wrong views, and it's actually quite true, when you
take an average person sort of being mindful, if you were to us and to describe it, well,
first of all, they probably wouldn't be able to, the second, it would all revolve around
the wrong views of, as if I'm in the present moment, as if the present moment is sort
of, in a constant change, constant flux that I step into, just to remind myself of mindfulness,
then also another belief comes that, well, if I just have enough, a sufficient amount
of mindful mind moments, then I'll be, I'll reach nibbana automatically or whatever else,
but you realize, well, mindfulness is obviously the absolute necessity, but if you're not
knowing where to, how to do your avidja, what you're going to be mindful is, or rather
whatever you're mindful of, will be mindful of with your avidja, will be ignorant in regard
to it.
So mindfulness needs to, well, mindfulness and authenticity, like self-transparency, being
honest to yourself, is the first step, feeds on the other, but if you're genuinely mindful,
the first thing you're going to recognize is, I don't know, the second thing you can
come to sort of recognize is, well, okay, what do I need to know then?
And then you sort of start to narrow it down, you don't need to know everything, you just
need to know suffering and freedom from it, so that's why your mindfulness should also
be concerned there, with your feeling, what feeling is present, then it will become
apparent that actually, well, for example, as I mentioned, the idea of the, the idea of
the flock, the idea of, everything is constantly changing, it doesn't make sense because
if everything is constantly changing, they wouldn't be any change at all, so when you're
mindful, there is something, your experience is present as such, it's mindful, it's enduring,
which means if you were to then say, oh, it's constantly changing or any other wrong
view of that kind, that would mean you're adopting an external explanation to your present
experience, that it's not validated by your mindfulness, your mindfulness tells you
the contrary, which means you then ignore your mindfulness to explain it based on the
views that you accepted beforehand, so then you want to stop doing that really and then
develop mindfulness and then the views that come from what's evident in your mindfulness,
there was a whole idea of phenomenology, like the philosophical movement of essential
is basically describing only what's evident in a phenomenological art of which is the
mindful art of mindfulness, and then if anything else would fall off, no matter how plausible
it was, they would recognize, well, that's an explanation, and if it's an explanation means
it's not actually coming from the direct mindfulness, direct description, direct understanding,
as such it can be accepted, obviously, feminologists and essential philosophers couldn't arrive
at greater conclusions, but it's a valid method, because in that case, if you were to do
it, you can't, like, you know, you can go off the tracks a bit, left or right, but you
can't go off too far, because this principle of being based upon mindfulness is not abandoned,
so it will always bring you back and restart, but that means person will have to be willing
to completely let go, challenge, abandon his own most personal views, let alone not
get angry over it, or upset, or argumentative, but really genuinely whenever he approaches
to the new view, or to the view that sort of challenges his own view, he approaches
it with a sense as something that might be right, and it might has to be accepted, which
means that what he has now, even if it's years of practice invested, are always in question,
because that's what mindfulness is, but if you do it like that, then the solid core
will actually remain, and you will be abandoning everything unnecessary, everything wrong,
while the right things will stay there, why, because they were right, but it's not easy,
I mean, it comes to a point where you experience fear by reading different views, by reading
views that are challenging yours, by talking to people that are saying you're wrong,
like genuine existential anxiety, fear, it's not, it's not optional, holding views, it's
not optional, like views are what you are, it's kind of your own foundation, so challenging
them feels like you're really shaking your own foundation, well that's what most people
get angry, exactly, if you say I'm a meditation technician nonsense, how dare you say that,
I've been meditating for 20 years, well good for you, why do you get angry on a kind of
it, meditation is supposed to free you from greed, aversion, delusion, why are you getting
angry now, because of your meditation, that's a contradiction in terms, so you either
haven't been meditating rightly since you're not free from anger, or the Buddha was wrong,
so which one it is, we all know which one it is, so if I recognize that I don't have
any mindfulness, and in order to develop it, if I keep reflecting as much as I can, like
as the moment passes, oh, see there you go, what moment passes, not the moment passes,
nothing like, more like the moment that I pass, reflect, keep reflecting like on my actions,
as passes I can, no, see again, as fast, what, you're chasing something, are things moving
out, like if you don't see them immediately, are they gone, how can you think of them
then, even as gone, if they were gone, well if I can only, like I can't, we recognize
it as being a rising, but just, what do you mean, well exactly, so if you can't see the
point of origin, I think, if you can only find it as originated, what is that chase, why
why do you have to be fast, in any way, it's already there, and it's still there, and
it's persisting there, can I call that a mindfulness, or is that just a reflection, well that's
mindful reflection, that's mind, it's inseparable, sati recollected, sati sampajana, mindfulness
and awareness, sati is the same word used for memory, so that's the whole, this whole
misconception of kind of observing the external moment, chasing them, being fast, quick,
fast, the completely misguided view, if it's truly past, it's inconceivable, you can't
even think about it, you can't even speak about it in a past tense, it's gone, but the
fact that you can, means it's not gone, means it still persists, while it's changing on
some level, so you recognize that, you recognize the stillness within the particular movement,
you stay with the stillness, you're mindful of the movement, but if you go after the movement,
well, you're pulverated, you're done, and again, the symbol in the suit is a man who needs
to keep an eye on, I don't know, 20, 30, I don't know, 5,000 of children, he can't possibly
go around chasing after every one of them, if he does, he'll exhaust himself, even if
he doesn't, he can see only one at the time, the one that he is chasing, which means the
other 49 children are not, he's not mindful of, so he recognizes that instead of chasing
individually, he finds a slightly elevated ground from which he can see them all at once,
so he's not particularly involved with any one of them, but he can see them, so if one
of them goes too far, he calls them back, and that's like the basic practice of mindfulness
which is the practice of meditation, there is no, some other, there is no meditation of
any kind, without mindfulness as a foundation, he's basically sitting down, you can, I don't
know, be mindful of your breathing if you want, but don't sweat it, so to speak, but be
mindful of what you're thinking while you're sitting down, while you're seated, to be
more precise, but then don't try to be kind of chasing your thoughts of grower, or seeing
where they originate, or look for every moment of your thoughts, because they will assume
you being external to your own thoughts, or your thoughts external to it, but you are
your thoughts, so once you're mindful of them as what has a reason, or these thoughts are
present, leave it, just don't, don't, don't, don't, try kind of holding it tightly, trying
to see every like microscopic moment, because there is no such thing, that's an assumption,
what you have is such thought is present, then another thought is present, so you don't
want to interfere with it directly, but you don't want to lose sight of it completely,
again, you don't want to be chasing all those children all the time, you want to step
back so that you can see them more, more of them, without, so you're not chasing directly,
but you're not, not looking at them either, so that's the attitude you want to have with
your own mind, your own thoughts, when you sit down and meditate, let things arise, don't
interfere with it, because it's nothing to do with you in the first place, but then don't
lose the sight of it completely, and that's a practice in itself, practice of mindfulness,
practice of meditation, practice that can bring the discernment, thus, although even as
a protusion, you can be emulating things rightly, and if you emulate it long enough, it will
lead to the right results, so keeping a peripheral sight, keeping a corner of your eye on
your thoughts, is basically how you establish yourself in mindfulness, that allows other
things to arise, as this will change, in front of you directly, but at the back of your
mind, there is still a corner of your eye looking at it, so peripheral vision, you don't
stare at things that I can only see them, you need an example of a, like a dancer, you
stand by the gate, yeah, yeah, there we go, yeah, there is a certain, yeah, and you don't
, you don't shift the person and check, because you know what, you know, you figure out,
you understand, you discern beforehand, if whoever comes in, whoever goes out to have
to come to here, and that's all you have to do, just stay there, whoever came in, you
don't go after them, you know, they're in, that's all I need to know, whoever goes out,
you know, they're out, that's all I need to know, if something, there is a temptation,
it pulls you once you go in, you resist that, why, because you know, well, I leave this
entry point, this door, this sole entry point, I will lose a sight of everything else, so
you don't leave that, so it's like mindfulness of the feelings, or mindfulness of the nature
of your thoughts, which means you don't have to be mindful and concerned with every particular
thought, for as long as you're mindful of the thought is there, in the same sense with
the body, you know, to be mindful of the body internally, externally, internally, externally,
mindfulness, mindfulness, all, he's mindful of the body is there, to be extended, necessarily
for the final knowledge, so you know, such a general thought, ah,
body is there, he sees that always peripherally, because the body is always there, whatever situation
you're in, good or bad, neutral, left or right, up or down, your body is there, peripherally,
you know, you, you, 99% of your attention can be taken by whatever else, but in that
distance, peripheral distance, there is still a reclamation, there is still knowledge
of all is there, and that's your anchor of your mindfulness, which means that these 99%
cannot actually take you away, cannot overwhelm you, why? because there is still that 1% anchor,
proper, and that's what anchor is, you throw an anchor, you let it sink, and then you forget
about it, in a sense that you're not constantly pulling it up and throwing it in, pulling it
up, because that's pointless, and that's what meditation does, I end up doing it, I'll
just get back to the moment, get back to the moment, get back to the present moment, why?
You get back to the present moment, when you completely forgot about it, you get back
to it so that you can let it go, let it take its course, while you remain slightly
anchored in it, I peripherally keep an eye on it, so you throw an anchor, and then you
let the boat float away, and when an anchor is established properly, the boat will not float
away too far, or it will float away as far as the anchor allows it to, but the common
contemporary techniques basically will translate into throwing an anchor, and pulling it up,
and throwing it in for the sake of doing it, so you can never ever get a concept of mindfulness,
concept of things enduring, persisting while changing, movement within thing that is still,
why? Because you're constantly just joking left and right, just throwing it, throwing it,
throwing it, throwing it, throwing it, throwing it, what's the best tool point, you know,
because even trying to think about what the body is, you can't lose ground, but you know,
different times are different, that's why there's so many, like different foundations of
mindfulness, but what you're saying, like also what you're saying, experience as a whole,
you don't, you don't, you don't come across that term in the sutras, you've got the feeling
of mind, but when I hear experience as a whole, and I see that God, we experience as a whole,
it's happening now, that phenomenon, my experience as a whole, it seems to be easier to come on.
Again, I think that just depends on the person, yeah, but even within the same person, sometimes
you'll need to, you'll need to do different things, because sometimes, you know, like the
habit of ignorance, we still prevail, and then you'll end up just like not, not, not
getting the same mind, so you have to, that's why there's so many different approaches,
different types, sometimes just to refresh your mind, you would, you would take a different
approach, sometimes different approach will make more sense than the previous approach.
The point is, the principles of those approaches remain the same, the principle of mindfulness,
the principle of understanding, the principle of determinations, all of those remains the
same, but it doesn't really matter what particular manifestation of the principle you're
engaging in, or as long as you're aiming at the principle, it's all contributing towards
the same understanding, because why I like that experience as well, because I can't
doubt that I'm experiencing, but I can doubt, is this my body, is that my body, you know
it, but the body is there, you can't doubt, because all of these movements in regard to
that body, is this, is this, is that, is that possible, because that body is a reason?
Yeah, sure, once you get it, once you come, because yeah, as it, as it, experience the whole
watching that, nothing else, nothing's going to happen without, it happening within that
experience, so it's guarding experience, you, and once you get used to guarding it, then
you can start making the effort within that and discerning it, so within that experience
as a whole, what is feeling, when I say feeling feeling, what does that stand within that
experience as a whole that I'm already mindful of, so you're creating like a ground on
which you can start doing the work, because it has to be something, and you're referring
to feeling feeling what does that designation stand for, what does it aim at, what does
it signify, and you want to clarify that, does that mean I'm, again, paying attention
to one child, though, well that means you're doubting what's also, what's an also, if you're
paying attention to feel like it's also my also, and if you don't know if it's also my
also, so what you want to do is develop criteria, all of your mindfulness whereby recognizing
being mindful of something will already know if what you're mindful of is also my own
also, what's the criteria, well the criteria would be the right view, so reflection of an
action to be holding on, holding has to happen at a different time, well it can happen
through that, for as long as you don't deceive yourself into thinking that you already
know what's awesome, what's some awesome, only a person with the right view knows
this wholesome as wholesome, unwholesome as unwholesome, there's a tutor again, a two time
to thought, and he devised, the Buddha did, well, previous, before, he's not the Buddha
yet, but he devised his thoughts into two cards, that was his thought connected with
him, he'll go through the version, the version Alice, and then thought connected to non-heal
will, non-culti and renunciation, but then he reflects, is this what I'm doing, good for
me, good for another, does it bring about wisdom, and then it all, is it not good for me,
not good for another, I wouldn't be, I wouldn't be sure, very flexible, through those questions
that kind of, then he knows that this is, this is wholesome, this doesn't disturb me,
it doesn't disturb anyone else, and I'm, my understanding is developing wisdom, so he,
but that's the criteria you can trust, even in the potusion, and you can see that none
of the techniques you would be doing in terms of meditation would come under that, always
than you're developing by watching a nostril, makes you feel good, makes you feel good,
so really it comes down to discernment, mental discernment, something that you cannot
put into a method, so you need to cause, oh, is what I'm doing, what I'm thinking, would
that be harm, would that imply, is that connected, harming others, harming me, harming both,
harming neither, okay, it doesn't seem this harming neither, but then is it also making me
discern things, is it making things clearer, so when I say feeling, feeling or when I say
perception, perception, doing no, what those things stand for clearer, and there is one
thing in these things out, is because those things are the five aggregates, and the five aggregates
are the ones affected with assumptions, with the wrong views, you do padana, so even in
your speech in designation, that's all form of, of, of, of, of padana, can be, if it stands
for wrong things, it expresses the wrong things, the wrong assumptions, so you want to have
things clear for you, not explained, not laid out, like, like, as a, as a nice little tidy
chart, a map of things, oh, this is what it is, this is what it is, you know, you want to
know exactly when you use after a designation, you know what it stands for, phenomenologically.
That's why I reckon, so that's what means like developing the sermon, developing wisdom,
that's what it's necessary, and you have to keep thinking like that, because if you are,
well, you will at least be striving in the right direction, but if you don't see that
as a criteria, developing that kind of wisdom, then exactly, then you can, yeah, what,
watching, watching my nostrils, doesn't harm anyone, doesn't harm me, doesn't harm others,
so it's great, well, exactly, it doesn't, and when it comes to developing wisdom and understanding,
there is no method you can engage in, as I said before, it just doesn't work like that.
It's, it's, it's to each individual, and it's also understanding in this sermon of
the nature of things precedes the designation, the nature of designation, so you can hear
the instruction, but then you understand what it pretends to, it precedes it, that's
why the Buddha referred to it as miracle, so that connection is something through your own
efforts can become apparent, and you're so responsible for that, which means even the
instruction utterance of another can go only so far, but then me designating you a set
of, set of methods and observances you go through, and then you just adhering to it, that
can that somehow magically lead you onto that connection, that you, your self-responsive
connection understanding, that doesn't, doesn't work, which is why it's wrong, it's a
fetter, seal about the Paramasa, holding onto virtue and duty, like people translate that
seal about the Paramasa is holding onto rights and rituals, whereby it means rights and rituals,
and that that's kind of obvious, we all know that, you know, piling to the random stone
shrines doesn't mean anything, so we all abandon that fetter, we just do it for whatever
reasons, but we know it's not the practice, but actually the, the pali is seal about the
Paramasa, seal is the virtue and duty, seal about the Paramasa means holding onto the
sense of virtue and duty, and basically holding onto thinking, your seal, your purity,
your valid, genuine purity is what practice is, holding onto, onto your sense of duty as
somebody who practices the Buddhist teaching, or I should be doing this, I should be meditating,
I should be holding onto that to be the practice, all of that is a fetter, why, because that's
not the practice, and it did say, there is no dhamma without vinaya, but vinaya is not
dhamma, and dhamma is not vinaya, but obviously you need vinaya in order to be able to practice
dhamma correctly, but dhamma is not vinaya, dhamma is not seal, so even your preset,
you need to be pure, you need to be kept, and nothing to do with dhamma, you can ignore
that, dhamma is elsewhere, and if you look at it, why, well it's obvious, because
presets are something you do, you observe techniques are something you do, you perform, but understanding
of the nature of things is something you cannot do, you cannot perform, this is completely
different domain, obviously the understanding of the nature of things cannot happen, if
your behavior has not be purifying externally to keep in the presets and not engaging in
maintaining and wholesome things through those bad habits, but that purification through
that behavior is not the understanding, because you can be as pure as, you know, anything
that comes, but still not understand things, so there is no guarantee of understanding
through following methods or observances or duties, why, because that's not what understanding
is, it obviously like, you know, that does not mean that, oh I can do whatever I want
and get in the standing, well if you didn't understand things, when things were favourable
for you, when you were keeping the presets, where you are not increasing the greater version
of the illusion, well then you are certainly not going to understand when your behavior
is increasing the greater version of the illusion, hence it's a necessary prerequisite,
but it's not it, so you can see why then like thinking, oh certain prescribed technique
or can you, Ajahn, can you give me a technique or something I can do that will lead me to,
you know, magical place of Arhantji, it's actually a very serious, wrong view because
it becomes an impediment, because you think that you are actually practicing by observing
this mechanical technique, which means that's where your effort stopped, you don't stop
and then start reflecting on that, the nature of what you're doing, which is what understanding
is, no you're just doing it, just doing it, I just repeating, budo, budo, budo, budo,
like a robot and that brings me full understanding of stuff, yeah right, if that brings you
into understanding then the whole tipitaka would be just budo, budo, budo, budo, budo,
budo, budo, budo, wherever you're opening or whatever you're paying to open it, but
it's not, not even once, never the budo say you just repeat this mantra and it will establish
you in mindfulness, many other followers and the emptyages of different sects and religions
said that, and they were all mentioned as wrong, right, because nothing may happen,
any mechanical such as repeating, budo, budo, or watching the tip of your nose or can
bring understanding, the only thing that can bring understanding is your attitude that's
trying to understand, and that attitude can be in regard to anything that is established
upon wholesome, hence the meditation techniques, well they're wrong because people think
them, take them to be right, but in themselves they're not even wrong, they're absolutely
pointless, you can be watching your nostrils or not, what's the point, you can watch tips
of your ears, like the budo, when he's teaching, he's talking about these things, certain
things, you know, five days with the followers, he's talking about these things, and people
understand, they get people from something, because they're understanding the designations
that he's using when he says, he's not ringing a bell, yeah, yeah, yeah, exactly, and
they will become our hands, right there and then by listening to them with a speak, not
by watching their nose for three hours, and then we go walking, yeah, understanding what
he's talking about, isn't it, actually paying attention, paying attention to designations
that he's using, and then seeing them for what they are in their own experience, they
have the right attitude, trying to understand, and the designations that himself were operating
were not as polluted as most of other people today's designations are, so then it's nothing
magical about people becoming our hands upon listening to budo speak, oh, well, you know,
the budo knew their mind, yeah, sure, but that's not the reason why they became our hands,
they became our hands because they understood what he was saying, right, so if now you don't
understand what the budo is saying in the sutras is because you just have so many obstructions
and assumptions of your own doing, which you're fully responsible, obscuring the meaning
of the sutras, so undo your own assumptions, undo your own designations to the extent necessary
whereby you read the sutras and it's directly describing your experience, when that's
the case, 100% you'll be an arah, because every sutra describes experience of an arah
or how to be humble.
If you read a sutra and it seems like common sense, oh, that means you have some serious
work to do, and yellow to people say, well, this is just common sense, it's just repetition.
If you think of it just in terms that I said, imagine if every designation of the budo
would use stands for direct description of your experience, then him repeating it through
different aspects of it would be bringing it in your experience, one aspect within the
other, within the other, within, so you can see it's almost like a natural progression
of understanding, like fortifying it in regard to this, in regard to this, within that,
within this, you realize the sutras are far from just repetitive kind of tautological
folklore descriptions of something, it's actually direct phenomenological instruction
and like leading on further and further and further in developing of your understanding
and your purification of your own designations, they were carrying around assumptions.
So if you approach it directly, rather correctly, if you approach it correctly, we derive
view and phenomenological mindfulness establish reading the sutras would be like directly
purifying your own experience while you're reading them, because that's what they are.
Hence repeating it for 20 times would be 20 repetitions of purifications, 6 times, 12
times, 18 times, no matter how many times it will be, you would read it and each time it
would be a purified image of a correct designation, things standing correctly for what they are.
So reading the sutras becomes the direct practice, the direct insight.
Which is how it was when the Buddha was speaking, to those who became sotapanas or arahants
upon listening.
So that's why repetition in the sutras, because it's not explaining, it's a direct description
of your experience and if you repeat it 6 times in regard to every sense, that's how
it needs to be seen, repetitively in regard to every sense.
Why?
Because if you leave a sense and turn, ignorance will stay there.
Yeah, far from, okay, we're talking about the other day, but John has been, you know,
by thinking and pondering in the correct way, one enters the John's, because you know,
he secluded from unhulsing states, you guiding your mind, so you notice I'm secluded from
awesome states, anything has to come through, has to come through here, I'm really straining
my senses, my senses are guarded, and then you enter, well, they've become joy and so
on.
So it's just, there is no blanking out ever.
No, no, no, no, no, you know, the sutra one by one, I think it was 109, am I doing
that?
About Sadi Puthas going through different sort of establishments of his mind, the first
John, the second John, the third John and so on, all the way up to station perception
field, and every of those states had mindfulness, first John, the second mindfulness there,
fully established, just fortifying that same mindfulness, which is not like completely the opposite
of what people expect to achieve through various meditation techniques, when you're just
not aware of anything, is it sorry, I went to the state, I went to the state of neither
perception or perception, because I don't, just the state I entered, and the next thing
I know, it was five o'clock in the morning, it's like, yeah, we heard you're neither perception
or perception snoring, or like, oh yeah, well, I go into this state when I don't hear
or see anything, or whatever, that's a good meditation, not according to the sutras,
I mean there are neither perception or perception of genuine kind, cessation of perception
and feeling, but in order to get there, your mindfulness has to be utterly, completely
unshakable.
A lot of people refer to this mind to, you know, this is a feeling of experience, isn't
it?
Well, yeah, like, you know, I kind of, in the beginning, I was given a benefit of doubt,
and then the more they talk about it, you realize, you were just asleep, mate, or you
know, when you go in a state, when you can't fall asleep, because you're not lying down,
but you're kind of half out, lots of people end up in that state, because they're seated
on the floor, so you can't quite fall asleep, that's why I lie down, that's why I lie
on, which again, that that that that genre is confirmed by kind of external eye of nodding,
you can see them nodding left and right, bobbing and weaving sort of, oh yeah, I have a good
meditation, yeah, we saw that.
So again, it's the lack of a person being authentic, they lie to themselves, and yeah,
you know, quite a few people like that that are met, were very sensitive about a topic of
meditation, they would be implied, they're maybe not meditating rightly, or if somebody else
would be implying indirectly that what they're doing is not right, they give a upset,
you know, well, what's the point of your meditation, if you hold on to it so dearly and personally,
you're getting upset, if somebody criticizes it, and surely you're not doing it right,
if someone else's random video can shake you up so much, you can offend you, you should
be grateful anyway, exactly, like there you go, I just laid it out for you, that's why,
if I read this Roman philosopher's Greek philosopher, they sought out challenges, you know, yes.
You sought out a challenge of your view, not the challenge to prove your seal is good
or something like that, which some of those people do, you want to challenge your views,
absolutely.
So someone says, oh, I tell you your view, that's the attitude you can be sure about, they
can't lead you to wrong, is attitude of challenging every view, no matter how dear to you it is,
and that's it, the views are dear to you, but they said, oh, surely you're holding to
the view because it pleases you, it's dear to you, you know, when that man said to the
Buddha, I don't hold to any views, no views are pleasing to me, and he said, well, surely
that view is pleasing to you, and he said, oh, okay, yeah, you have a point there, but
when you have a view, that no view will be dear to you, including that view, in a sense,
that whatever view you have, you recognize you always have to have a view, you can't
have a state of no view, because that's a view, which means if you believe it's not the
view you're contradicting yourself, thus you're even more wrong, so it's not about not having
any views, which is impossible, it's about finding the right view, and then going beyond
even the right view, which is possible, which is our answer, but in order to get the right
view, you must not hold to any view for the sake of pleasing you, oh, this view is pleasing
to me, you can't help having a view being pleasing to you, but where you can't help is
not leaving it unturned, not taking for granted, not leaving it unquestioned, so you get a view,
then you find the views that are opposing to the view, and if you think, oh, this is a
wrong view, well, you need to fully understand why, how, and where that view is wrong, not
just decide this is wrong because somebody else said, even the Buddha, or the Buddha said
that, well, sure, but do you understand it for yourself? Do you understand why wrong views
are wrong, if you do, you have the right view? Yes, it's dangerous, so I think it's probably
useful if someone, you know, someone who can challenge you, you know, if you don't have
any good challenging, then open any book, because you're bound to think, oh, these views
are wrong, well, open those books, read them, and try to see for yourself why, how, and
where those views are wrong, not just assume they're wrong, and same, oh, the Buddha's
right, okay, open the suitors and understand where, how, and why, it's right, and if you're
doing it correctly, you'll see, you'll be fearful, you'll be like anxious, to read other
stuff that you think it's wrong because you might not see, it is wrong, thus, you're
not as right as you think you are, but that's inevitable, you have to go through that.
Yeah, it feels like the thing that you think is wrong, because if there is anything right,
it's that which cannot be taken personally, and it will stay, it will stay on, you won't
drop off. Yeah, it can't be, no one can challenge it, yeah, no one can take it, you can't
challenge it, you've been challenging it, you've been like, like attacking it without, and
whatever was susceptible to doubt, was affected by it, except those things that were beyond
doubt, so you go beyond doubt by basically reaching a point where the doubt cannot enter,
not because you were shying away from doubting it, but because you were doubting full on,
you fully became doubt, and then you recognize that their points, the doubt cannot enter,
and that's doubt free, it's beyond doubt, beyond doubt means inaccessible to doubt, doesn't
mean, oh, I never doubt this because, yeah, I fear, I fear that if I doubt, I might change
my mind, re-evaluate everything, and 30 years that I invest in this, down the drain, yeah,
from the day one, full on doubt, very unpleasant, but, you know, relatively quick way of progressing
if you do it right, because you know, oh, this is beyond doubt, not because I'm not doubting
it, because it's nature, it's impenetrable to doubt.