But can you explain the practice of samadhai, the basanam?
Sure. Well, you can start by sort of applying a blanket.
Or maybe I just, I will start with some idea which I do.
Okay, so yeah, you can do that.
So it was after you know talking with you about this phenomenological approach,
in the pafero, I was still considering that actually to practice just simple,
and upon a meditation as I used to do it, you know, just relax,
staying in the present is your briefing.
It's actually still a good thing to do in your spare time.
But seems that you have something to say about it.
I think what I say is that, yeah, yeah, well basically most,
more often than not, it won't be a good thing because you won't do it mindfully.
Like if you go into an object of meditation, whatever that might be,
and if you want to do it just to sort of calm down and well not,
yeah, you can do it, but on the basis of mindfulness.
And the basis of mindfulness as we've been discussing all these previous talks
is the basis of the awareness of the paerifero.
So as I said yesterday, sure, you can't possibly sustain,
although you could, surprise yourself,
but your amount of energy you can invest in sort of repetition of this discernment
of the paerifero in regard to actual and actual in regard to paerifero
so that you fully sort of keep drilling that in,
training and drilling and training and drilling.
So, but say you're tired of it, so then yes, you stop actively pursuing the discernment of that principle,
but you don't then turn completely away and then become unmindful,
become unaware of the principle.
Because that means you're not mindful.
That means when you go to meditate, if you meditate without being aware of the principle,
you meditate without mindfulness, which means that's not meditation at all.
But it can be still awesome activity.
You know, you are not engaged.
Well, I'm sure desire is between something unholy, something...
Well, it's also in a very relative manner.
It's awesome because only because you don't engage in sensual desire.
But it remains very much on wholesome,
because you won't take you out of the putugena status.
Nor will it take you out of the wrong view.
On the contrary, it will probably keep perpetuating the wrong view.
That's why the Buddha said those meditators,
summoners and Brahmins without the right view,
they end up meditating...
They think they meditate by the end of premeditating,
overmeditating, mismeditating, undermeditating,
and all of those kind of permutations.
Because why?
The mind is still bound with sensuality,
with the notions of self, with all the wrong assumptions,
and they meditate with that.
So a putugena cannot meditate with a pure mind,
because he doesn't have such a thing.
He doesn't even have a concept of what phenomenon of the mind is.
But he could purify his mind by practicing jhanas.
Yes, and jhanas are nothing other,
than fully established upon the principle of mindfulness,
which is the principle we've been discussing,
which I think maybe was even recorded.
I explained to you that extending the same awareness
of the peripheral legato,
you can go as far as to their casinos.
The four great elements,
the element of consciousness,
which is the most refined one,
told the jhanas to the immaterial,
and mindful establishments.
It's the extending the mind along the same principle.
That's why the sari puting, one by one,
that's the imaginary kaya,
goes to the first jhana,
and then he kind of,
oh, the recognize the factors that are there,
and says this is all kind of being held by mindfulness,
and then he's there beyond,
and then following the same principle says,
yeah, there is beyond.
So then he goes, hi, hi, hi, hi, hi,
until obviously with his right view,
he reaches to the cessation of perception and feeling,
which is obviously that there is not beyond that,
when things cease.
But that's just to see how far this great structure,
kind of structures itself,
is there beyond this?
Yes, yes, yes, yes,
up to the infinite space,
the infinite consciousness,
now the perception and not perception.
All those things in the regard to mind
being developed in regard to the peripheral,
because when you're able to sort of reach,
and it's not like it's abstract now,
because the mind is not developed,
but for the developed mind,
reaching the verges of the phenomenon of space,
goes into the infinite space.
The verges of the perception,
surmounting the perceptions of unity and diversity,
doesn't matter in particular,
general nature of perceptions,
surmounted, you reach a base of neither perception
nor perception.
So Janus, that's why the good phrase is Janus,
because even, sure,
you don't need necessarily the right view,
but in order to do them,
you're doing them along the right view,
along the right principle,
along the principle of partition part,
along the principles of semantics,
sensuality, semantics,
the master, I am of the experience,
many sort of say that,
I am cannot be present in the Janus,
it ceases beforehand,
that's where the monetized Janus and so on.
So that's why the good phrase is that,
because if you were to develop Janus as protagonists,
then you would need very, very little instruction
to put it all together
and become probably not right away,
because the mind is already developed
to such an extent
that has amounted the domain of sensuality,
has fully understood the nature of Salatina,
and it's impermanent and so on.
So it's very important to recognize that,
the tutuja cannot meditate rightly,
unless he is a sotpan.
Oh, that's a strong statement.
Yeah, well, you don't need to go further
than some of it is so fancy,
that right view makes everything right.
Yes.
Yeah, so it's not my statement,
it's the whole suit about it.
So how can you meditate rightly if you have no review?
And the story.
But it can mean it without you knowing
that you are meditating rightly,
you just meditate and prepare your mind
for a crying effect.
Well, if you don't know it,
well, if right view is about the knowledge,
if liberation is about the knowledge,
how can you be knowing while not knowing?
How can you be doing it rightly while not knowing?
If you are not knowing all the instructions of good heart.
Well, the one who understands those instructions
is the sotapana.
Nobody shortens in that,
which means you follow something you haven't understood.
So how can you follow it?
If I give you instruction and you make no sense out of it,
how can you perform it?
Because you just follow instructions.
Well, no, it means some task to do
and I don't understand.
Exactly, I just say you won't do the task rightly.
If the task is based upon you understanding the task,
like the Buddha didn't say,
just perform these mechanical things
and you get to the final result.
He said, understand what I'm teaching you,
and then you will be your own kind of leader,
your own sort of guide to the final task.
So what you are sort of talking about
would be as if the Buddha gave this in person,
in person, sort of set of methods and instructions
that you can just stick to it and you will arrive at it.
But he didn't.
He did give instructions that need to be understood.
Hence the right view comes first.
And he said himself,
in Samadhi Sutra,
why some samadhi right?
It's because of the right view.
So without the right view,
you cannot meditate rightly.
But on the other hand,
I have no say but but but.
we have quite a few examples of people
who had Janas,
and there is the Buddha Janas.
Yeah, that's what I said.
So theoretically, as putugana,
you can develop Janas.
You can develop the full understanding of this principle
and develop your mind.
And not necessarily,
until somebody tells you externally,
turn that to the nature of the sense of self.
That's why putugana can be free
from all the other rupadanas,
except the rupadana of the self.
There is a sutra,
but I think it's Imaginika,
or maybe Angutra.
Not sure.
But putugana can be free from sensuality,
can be free from silabat paramasa.
He cannot be free
from the self-view.
Because for that,
you need utterance of another.
I see.
But he will have very much of Ayurveda,
Manasikara,
if he had Janas.
That's why, like say Janas,
they are the four Janas,
but then you have even,
kind of, more refined immaterial attainments.
That's why when the Buddha became the Buddha,
when the Brahma pleaded to him to go and teach,
he generated,
who should I teach?
So there are putuganas,
but which ones had the least dust in their eyes?
So he turned to his previous teacher,
not out of some traditional gratitude,
or anything like that.
No, because he had the least dust in his eyes,
he was the basis of neither perception
or perception.
So you realize,
as a putugana,
he was really, really,
he had done 99.9% of work
that Arahana needs to do.
All he needed is just that
1, 0.1% to set everything right.
He already had.
So when they told him,
the day was told him he died,
he said, why,
it's a really great loss for him.
I mean,
unimaginable loss,
because he actually was so, so close
to this very thing.
Then he went down the next one,
which is the base of infinite space,
wherever it was,
all for the purpose,
because they had
did done all the work mostly.
And that's why when they do have people in the suit
as they heard,
just one line from the Buddha
and became Arahana,
it's because they've done all the work,
rightly.
So they developed the whole understanding
that resulted in the whole freedom of
Upadana and everything.
They just needed the last drop.
So they did a lot of right understanding.
Really?
Yes, of course.
Well,
Buddha comes to you and tells you
in seeing, let there be the scene,
in herd, let there only be the herd.
And you understand that, right there and then.
You won't be able to understand that
if you have many wrong views blocking it,
covering it up.
But if you clear all the wrong views,
but you're not still quite there yet,
and then somebody tells you that,
and you understand it as clear as a day,
as they tell to you.
You can only do that if the mind is able to
sort of reach it at that level.
And it can reach it at that level,
if it made the right effort.
That's why again,
you should keep trying to meditate
and keep trying to sort of understand
along the lines of understanding,
not along the lines of mechanical technique
that you hope is purifying your mind
somewhere down the line.
Because even if we were,
you have no right criteria.
You don't have right view to recognize
what the actual purity is.
So even if it sits in your face,
you won't recognize it.
Yeah, yeah.
It seems that I can't agree with this statement
that last one you said about.
I will show you my other thing,
which I used to,
or which I have.
I was thinking that you purify your mind
so never enough,
and by purifying your mind
you will remove your obstacles.
And then you can,
well,
sure, that's not wrong statement to make,
but purifying your mind
of never enough is done
by understanding what never enough is.
But fully understanding the nature,
you're surmounted.
That's why Mahamogalana entered the first jhana
by understanding what the first jhana was.
Not by doing this or that.
Or going on a retreat,
or watching souls of his feet.
By understanding the nature of the first jhana,
he entered the first jhana.
So can he say that actually overcoming,
you overcoming by understanding what nivarana is,
means that you don't overcome them by technique,
by just practicing some meditation.
Exactly.
You overcome by understanding them.
That's how the mind develops in regard to it.
And understanding can take place only on the basis
of principle of the Titsamapara,
the basis of principle of understanding
that a reason phenomena as it has a reason,
which means on the basis of mindfulness,
which means on the basis of
discerning peripheral in regard to the actual,
or actually in regard to peripheral.
Because nivaranas are also phenomena
that are manifested in your visit experience as a whole.
So if you understand it there,
on the basis of the experience as a whole,
you remove the ownership of it.
You remove sort of their influence over you,
but not only in them.
Yes.
Because you give them power by taking possession of them.
Or I'm involved about sotapana
and then separately in regard to nivaranas.
Yeah.
To an extent.
So you have understood it.
But as I said before,
even with this principle that you can kind of understand,
you still didn't fully understand it, didn't you?
Because you haven't repeated it long enough.
So that's why an Arya,
who is still not an Arhan,
still has work to do.
He still needs to keep re-engaging
in repeating of the same principle of the same understanding
that he has, which is why nobody else can be his guide,
not even Buddha.
He himself.
Because he got a criteria.
He got a principle.
He got a base for it.
He got an understanding.
He just needs to keep drilling it.
So just keep drilling it.
Exactly.
That's why the Buddha we passed see before he became
some of some Buddha.
He discerned,
but it's some part.
And in that deepening kaisuta,
he disclosed,
but it's some part.
And he comes to the point of
Nama Rupa, the term is Vinyana,
and Vinyana, the term is Nama Rupa.
And then he doesn't define,
but it's some part of further.
And then he says,
but understanding that,
he remained contemplating
manifestation,
I arising and ceasing of the five degrees,
of the experience as a whole,
until his mind was purified
from all of the kilesas,
and he became some of some Buddha.
So if you understood the principle,
then just remain drilling it.
And it doesn't say,
he remained drilling,
but it's an opada.
It says,
he understood,
but it's an opada.
Nama Rupa Vinyana Vinyana,
and then he remained just
mindful of arising and falling
of the five arguments.
Yes.
Of the enduring of the five arguments,
of persisting, of changing,
of the five arguments,
being independent of any
sort of notion of mind
and myself,
he fully drilled that
to the extent necessary
for the final knowledge
and then a second,
he was done.
So can we say that,
or basically the essence,
the point is to
understand that structure
of experience,
and then understanding,
that's the point.
That's why, like,
I mean,
it's kind of unfortunate
that this needs to be said,
not like to be particular
about any generally,
because yeah,
many people,
when you read so much in every
certain, just like,
the final knowledge,
the final understanding,
Puthujana can relate
to knowledge.
Just think about the phenomenon
of knowledge,
means when you know something.
So then, you must not
abandon that notion of knowledge,
when you're pursuing
the way out of suffering.
As appealing as it is
to giving to an impersonal
mechanical technique
that sort of numbs you out
for a while,
makes it very peaceful,
it's a very, very dangerous path
to take, because you become
dependent upon it,
in that pleasure,
that forgetfulness,
that oblivion.
So initially,
everything seems painful
because you want to know
everything, but you can't,
but it's on the basis of that,
that you can actually
be certain important
from unimportant,
which is an
description for Puthujana.
Like, I,
what's important knowledge,
what it isn't.
But it's still,
sorry,
but it still is the knowledge.
So,
to answer your original question
about Samatha and Vipassana,
Vipassana is actively
pursuing the discernment
of those principles,
whatever approach you take,
the five aggregates
from Puthujana
or the referral and actual,
anything that's based
on mindfulness,
that's where you can
not have too much of mindfulness
and that's where mindfulness
is always first,
basically,
in whatever list they come up.
So, Vipassana will be actively
pursuing the discernment
while Samatha will be
not actively pursuing
the discernment
containing the basis
for discernment.
So, if you maintain the
basis for discernment,
but not exerting yourself
in understanding,
you will progress a bit slower
in terms of understanding,
but nevertheless,
you eventually start seeing those things,
why? Because you know
where you're supposed to see,
and you keep holding it
in front of you.
Even if you're not necessarily
trying to see,
you still hold all the components
rightly in front of you,
in Samatha.
That's where Samatha carries
Vipassana,
vice versa,
actively pursuing Vipassana
means you composing that
principle and keeping it
in front of you,
means Vipassana is
dragging Samatha with it.
And it's not optional,
if done rightly.
That's where it's like
the two yolks,
yolk to the two,
two lobsters.
So, one might go slightly forward
and another might,
that doesn't matter.
They will both be going forward.
But if you engage in any form
of Samatha,
that is not based on mindfulness,
not based on maintaining
the same principles,
even if you don't necessarily
actively pursue them,
well, you have no basis
for any Vipassana,
which means that's
not Samatha.
That's Patujan Samatha.
That's his premeditation
or meditation under meditation
and so on.
And that cannot possibly
magically sort of transfer you
into the right,
right way of meditating.
You just couldn't.
So, I will just try to
stay in my own words
if I go there.
So, that mindfulness
you are talking about,
is actually the mindfulness
of this principle.
Mindfulness is, yes, mindfulness
is in common to Vipassana
and to Samatha.
That's where every Jhana,
it's not properly,
which is what Jhana is,
when it's not properly,
has mindfulness as its basis.
And you read that,
you read one by one,
sort of you read other,
sort of mindfulness
is present in every Jhana.
So, must be basically
founded upon it.
So, instead of thinking
what kind of
contemporary sort of
Buddhist schools think
and teach,
that meditation
is some sort of concentration,
that makes you focus
upon something
that you forget everything else.
Think about meditation
Samatha literally means
composure.
But if you're composing something,
you need components for that,
something needs to be composed.
Something needs to be kept there,
composed.
And it's your mind,
it's the principally
understanding of mindfulness
that we spoke about before.
So, think of Samatha
or Samatha.
Think of Samatha
or Samatha as unwavering mindfulness.
Not actively engaging
on the basis that mindfulness
is just being mindful.
So, mindfulness enduring.
Mindfulness is the
secret of mindfulness.
Yeah, not like it doesn't
change at all.
Yes.
It changes while remaining
the same.
Because mindfulness
is another phenomena.
It's work.
Mindful of experience
is a whole which is the phenomena
that is present.
Is it not to be
right focused on one particular thing?
But just to
actual and peripheral means
you see basically
from one point of view
you see both ends.
You don't have to
chase them.
Yes.
You don't have to step into
the peripheral
and forget about actual
and chase actual
and forget about peripheral.
Like, the other one,
what was the
that similarly?
Well, think about the other
similarly, basically, which can
serve the purpose
like a gatekeeper.
You don't chase people
outside of the city
or inside the city.
You just stay at one point
from which you know
whoever passes here
is inside,
whoever goes out
is outside.
That's all you need to know.
Yes.
So, in the same sense,
that's how
you establish your mindfulness.
Now, by chasing the
particular sensations
or whatever
perceptions,
but by being mindful
of the basis of them.
And whatever.
And they can change as fast
as they want.
You won't lose your
mindfulness.
Yes.
Because you haven't
based your mindfulness
on such a fleeting,
particular notion.
But, on a more general
of fundamental
recognition of the
experience as a whole,
which is a basis
for these things changing.
So, you don't care
how they change.
You know, they have to
change inside of the city.
Because they have
a reason.
They cease.
They gone.
Now, they're not my concern.
Yes.
And what about
wholesome and unwholesome?
The relationship
between my influence
and wholesome and unwholesome
states.
You know, because that
gatekeeper needs
actually out
words and others.
In order to get
sort of this kind of mindfulness,
they've established,
developed and established.
Unwholesome habits,
unwholesome behavior,
unwholesome engaging
with unwholesome need to
have been already
kept at bay.
Obviously, sometimes,
you sleep, you engage
in unwholesome.
If you have right mindfulness,
it will be quicker for you
to kind of readjust.
And reset.
And start doing things
rightly.
That's the case for an
area.
We can quickly pick back,
pick up the training,
back.
And do it even
after a slip.
So, for Patujan,
he needs to purify
his behavior beforehand.
He needs to have been
engaging in a pure
behavior in a sense
of not getting into
the unwholesome.
And as we spoke,
a few days ago,
there is an unwholesome.
Yeah, there is the obvious
unwholesome.
But often, that unwholesome
is actually determined
by the state of your mind.
Whether it's rooted
in desire,
in craving,
or if it's not rooted
in desire, in craving.
So, that's what you become,
aware of.
Not like, kind of,
oh, well, everybody says
this is fine,
and I'll do it.
Yeah.
No, you know you'll be doing
it for the wrong reasons.
Yes.
The reasons of pursuing
distraction,
carelessness,
whatever,
and feeling justified about it.
No, no, no, no.
That needs to go.
Yeah.
And then these things
can take root,
if you,
if you obviously apply,
apply the effort.
That's why the suitors
say that he practiced
restraint,
by the rules of Patujan,
he sees the danger
in the slightest fault.
Yes.
Which means, basically,
even the slightest
danger in the slightest
giving into the desire.
Yes, actually,
that you are not
able to do anything.
It doesn't mean you don't
do anything.
It means you just do
things that are not
rooted in your
unhulsing desire.
Yeah.
So if you want to go
for a walk,
because, well,
because you are
basically feel too lazy
to read the suitors
or maybe all you can,
they run in front of you,
you want to go for a walk
and then,
that's okay.
It is a compromise,
you can see.
Going for a walk,
depending,
like you want to go
into the wilderness,
well, that's not necessarily,
you're not going to
have any kind of
sensual distractions there.
So, you could sort of
do that compromise,
because it's quite
likely in the wilderness,
your mind will go back
to the dharma.
But, say, you go
for a walk and you
choose to go to the village.
And then, you realize,
well, you will be
meeting people,
you will be engaging
with it.
So, you might not
give rise to any
seriously unhulsing desire,
or an offense,
or something like that.
But nevertheless,
you're going for the purpose
of socializing,
turning your mind away
from the practice,
giving in
to distraction of others.
So, that's unhulsing.
If, for example,
you want to go to the
wilderness because you want
to practice further,
then it's same.
Again, you go for a
same walk,
but now it's
based in wholesome.
It's done for good
reason.
So, you become
responsible for
rooting it.
Or, like, you live in
the monastery.
You live in a big temple.
Most, like, the
temples that have
a library,
Buddhist libraries
every book you want.
So, you are in your
boredom, the pressure,
the dread starts to
come up anxiety.
You're a bit tired.
You can't keep making
the effort.
So, well, you know,
it's obvious you'll feel
too guilty if you just
go to the
salon or reception
room where people are.
But, no, you go to the
library to get the book.
But, deep down,
or not even that deep down,
just underneath that,
you hope that you will
meet people in library
to get somebody to talk
to and get your mind
off things.
Now, if you say that,
you're going to
library to take some
practice.
Nobody will criticise
that.
Everyone will say,
yeah, very well.
He's really making the
effort.
But, you know, that actually
you're doing it for
completely wrong reasons.
So, then you shouldn't
do it.
Because there will be a
fault.
But, sometimes, you don't
know actually because you
don't know.
Well, you have to know.
It's not necessarily
you don't need a great
wisdom of a
sort of an
argument to discern that.
You just need to be
honest to yourself.
That's why that,
the mundane right view
is required for any
other right for you to
take place.
That recognition,
that kind of
admitting things to
yourself,
being transparent to
yourself, or as a
university, being authentic.
So, you recognize why
am I going to library?
What is the main
reason?
Yeah.
And that's why, like, once
you say,
develop in the transparency,
that's where, you know,
the contemplation of the
food.
Like, you can't help,
but eat.
You have to eat,
because otherwise you'll
die.
And then, you can eat
for unwholesome reasons,
or you can make the effort
and re-root the reasons
for your eating,
that are necessary.
Root them forcefully
if you have to,
in wholesome.
Don't give rights
to the desire,
and root them in wholesome.
Root them in the purpose
of your practice,
purpose of this life,
purpose of your commitment.
That's why you eat.
So, to remain healthy,
affliction-free,
so that you can practice.
So, it's not like,
or eating is bad,
or eating is good.
You make it so.
If you remain mindful of,
and if you're mindful of these,
more general vague reasons,
why you eat,
like, or to be coming out
hunting, to do this,
and to be able to practice,
and to be able to
apply myself,
then the desire can creep in.
If you become mindful,
goes back to the default,
which is with the grain,
which is with the flood,
which is with the desire,
with the taste,
with the thirst.
So, in the same sense,
sometimes you might
actually have to go
to the library.
You really want to get these
sutras,
but you've been carefully
attending to that,
unmindfully,
and the real reason
becomes meeting other people.
So, then you have to re-roach it.
Then you have to keep bringing back
the other reason for getting
the sutra books,
and then go to the library,
and if you do meet other people,
you may therefore know engaging
with them, avoiding them,
taking the books,
and getting out.
Is this Sila Mata Paramasabh?
Well, it's within this.
Yeah.
If you fully develop this
principle of transparency,
paired with understanding of the
base of mindfulness,
there would reveal the sign of the mind,
the notion of the phenomenon
of the mind.
Then you would recognize exactly
where the purpose of
Sila, the virtue,
and the butter,
the duties, is.
You would recognize it,
and you wouldn't need to hold on to it,
because it took responsibility
for the whole thing.
But if you don't recognize it,
that's when people say,
no, no, no.
But it's always good to go
and take the sutra.
It's always good to be virtues.
Yes.
It is always good to be virtues.
It is always good to read the sutras.
But the putugin as a mind can make
even that unwholesome.
If it doesn't know that fundamentally,
wholesome unwholesome is rooted in desire.
So unwholesome is always rooted in desire.
And then in hindsight,
you can recognize it.
Oh, yes, of course.
A sensuality of any kind,
anger,
ill will of any kind,
cruelty of any kind.
It's always rooted in desire.
You cannot re-root the reasons for that.
That's why you stop doing them beforehand.
You take that on trust,
so that you can develop that understanding.
Not just so that you can blindly
adhere to it for the rest of your life.
Yes.
Because they will not serve as a basis for wisdom
and knowledge.
They will talk about it.
So in that sense,
the behavior needs to be purified beforehand,
and then obviously the practice of the
disseminate the principle,
the composure of the principle,
and the kind of the knowledge of the principle
eventually can take the place.