So I thought we could just about celibacy, sexuality, since it's quite an important point
for most people who are practicing most monastics anyway.
And I'll be reading from the Anguitori Nikaia, the numerical discourses of the Buddha.
The Buddha, he says in the beginning, the book of the One, actually.
Because I do not see even one other form that sort of obsesses the mind of a man as the
form of a woman, the form of a woman obsesses the mind of a man.
Likewise vice versa for a woman, to the form of a woman, the smell, the whole experience
of a woman obsesses one's every sense base, the form, the smell, the fact that it is,
he says those who are bound by the sense of touch, are thoroughly bound.
So once you can have the image of the see the woman, but once you have the touch, they
had experienced that behind you thoroughly.
The last drop.
Yes, the last thing.
And then he goes, another suitor goes on to say, because there are three things that
give no sayation or are insatiable by indulging in them, what's three?
By indulging in sleep, by indulging in alcohol, and by indulging in sexual intercourse.
These are three things that give no sayation by indulging in them.
There's no ending to the desire, to the desire and more specifically in regard to those
three things.
You can never have enough of it.
Well, most people would feel like they already know that, and the desires are not, cannot
be really satisfied and so on, but if you were, obviously if you really understand it,
if you were to generally understand it, that it's insatiable, then you would actually lose
an interest in it, then all this is, this is inherently structurally, countless, impossible
to, the promise that it has, whatever satisfaction, getting pleasure is just, it is hollow, then
it's fact, so it cannot be satisfied, which means, okay, so given in one's means, then
it will be hard for you to not give in another time, and you give in another time, then
it will be hard for you to not give in again, and so it will develop a habit of giving
in to something that you know, it's utterly pointless.
So that's what, like even somebody who doesn't necessarily want one aims at all, and she
bests a goal, or on a cambio, or whatever, it will be better off like being celibate,
even as a layman, it will be much better off for the mind, for the general wisdom, for
general wholesomeness of life, and obviously for rebirth, because you spend your mind,
you spend your human life not engaging in animal-like, carnal activities, yeah, you're
going to have a better destination as a result of that, because what is it for, like getting
drunk?
There's absolutely no fulfilment, no goal, nothing, it's basically knowing that scratching
a ditch, want to remove the ditch, or you just enjoy the scratch, knowing that that scratch
is actually making the ditch even worse, it's the next time, it's going to reach you
even more, but you know, it's not even a temporary end to this comfort, it's just oblivion
through itching, that's making things worse, and then you depend on the ditch even more,
it means you depend on the living more, which means you're making things worse even
more, that's like the vicious circle and the downward spiral of sensuality, but some
would say that it's, it's only natural, it's actually only natural, and nature is what
is natural, nature keeps you bound to river, so yeah, it is very natural, it's very natural
to be reborn, it's very natural, someone said it's natural, but not necessary, sexual
intercourse, there's no, yeah, of course, which is the same, but again, I don't know what
context they meant, natural, some of these people, well people, when they say it's natural,
nature, the design, it's kind of a whole great, a good thing, but it's not, ultimately, it
is the very nature, even the nature of things, and your ignorance in regard to it, it keeps
you bound, obviously you're responsible for that, you can't blame the nature of things,
but nature is set up as a trap, as a deceit, so that then you give in voluntarily, almost,
it's just easy, it's normal to take things at face value, it's normal to entertain ignorance
as you go to it, so that's what nature is, yeah, very much so, yeah, when people say
natural, then it's bad faith, it's not my fault, it's just, exactly, yeah, it's dismissing
on the responsibility, oh, it's natural, that's, it's not really up to me, it's just, it's
just natural to eat, they need the natural satisfaction, I guess, and there is also natural
rebirth, a natural ignorance, a natural samsara, natural suffering, yeah, but there's, there's
three things, sleep, drugs, alcohol, sexual intercourse, yeah, it's just, they just, they
love each other, kind of thing, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, that's all they're having,
so there's another sutra we'll read, it's called, it's from the Ingoodric Nikai as well,
and it's called Mother and Son, that's quite a intense sutra, yeah, yeah, yeah, another one,
one occasion, the blessed one was dwelling in Sarvati and Jators Grove, now on that occasion,
a mother and son, being respectively a Bikuni and a Biku, had entered the reigns residence
at Sarvati, they often wanted to see one another, the mother often wanted to see her son
and the son, his mother, because they often saw one another, a bond was formed, because
a bond formed intimacy arose, because there was intimacy lost in the old and open, with
their minds in the grip of lust, without having given up the training and declared their weakness,
they engaged in sexual intercourse, then a number of Bikus approached the blessed one, paid
homage to him, sat down to one side and reported what had happened, the blessed one said,
Bikus, the dead foolish man think, a mother does not fall in love with her son or a son
with his mother, because I do not see even one other form that is as tantalizing, sensuous
and intoxicating, captivating, infatuating, and as much of an obstacle to achieving the
unsurpassed security from bondage as the form of a woman, beings who are lustful for the
form of a woman, ravenous, tied to it, infatuated and blindly absorbed in it, sorrow for a long
time under the control of a woman's form, with the experience of a woman, because they
sound, they smell, they taste, they touch, Bikus, while walking, a woman obsesses the mind
of a man, while standing, while sitting, while laying down, while laughing, while speaking,
while singing, while crying, a woman obsesses the mind of a man, when swollen, too, a woman
obsesses the mind of a man, even when dead, a woman obsesses the mind of a man.
If Bikus, one could rightly say of anything, entirely a snare of mara, it is precisely
of a woman that one could say this, one might talk with a murderous foe, one might talk
with an evil spirit, one might even approach a viper, whose bite means certain death, but
was the woman, one to one, one should never talk, they bind one whose mind is muddled with
a glance and a smile, with their dress in disarray and with their gentle speech.
She is not safe to approach such a person, though she is swollen and dead.
These five objects of central pleasure are seen in a woman's body, form, sounds, tastes,
and odors, and also delightful touches, those swept up by the flood of sensuality, who
do not fully understand sensual pleasures, are plunged headlong into some sorrow, into
time, destination and existence upon existence.
For those who have fully understood sensual pleasures, live without fear from any quarter,
having attained the destruction of the taints, while in the world they have gone beyond.
And just to be said, it works the same way, for a woman, it is the form of a man, the
sex, you can just replace it, and I don't know when I have to address it, but I think some
people might, when they read things like that, obviously they read it with no wisdom or
not even enough transparency to see what they refer to, and then they take it personally,
and think the Buddha was blaming women, or the Buddha was blaming men, it wasn't.
So the nature of things is that you, with the mind affected with ignorance, will be snared
by a form of a woman.
Woman's mind, affected with ignorance, will be snared by a form of a man.
But that doesn't actually mean that that particular woman or that particular man are responsible
for that snare, they just carried this form.
Now they are responsible for their own ignorance in regard to their own form, they were given
to them, circumstantially.
So it kind of, it's not, it's not on the level of a full on clear volition that every woman
is out to get every man, or that every man is out to seduce an every woman.
No, simply by taking a masculine form, by assuming it, that's basically that masculine aspect
of it, which you yourself had nothing to do with, it was just given to you.
So in a way, a man is a victim of his own masculinity, as much as a woman is, that is being affected
by it.
Another woman is also a victim of her own femininity, as much as the man is snared by it.
And that's another subject that the Buddha says, by giving in to the notions of your own
masculinity.
And make yourself liable to be, basically, to be snared by the opposite, by the female,
by the feminine notions and feminine forms.
And same for a woman, by entertaining, by delighting in her femininity, she maintains herself
liable to a snare of a male form of the opposite.
It's one's own, doing one's own delighting, exactly, yeah, yeah.
The lust is found in your own mind, yeah, yeah.
So that, you can say that, but in this particular suit, that female form that snares a man, it's
the same female form that traps a woman.
And you can say that the male form that snares a woman, the masculinity, that snares a woman,
it's the same masculinity that traps a man.
So that's why, again, in another suit, you should look at your own body, at your own,
not delight in your masculinity as a man or a feminine, as a woman, and look at it as
with a disgust that you would look on a pile of feces on the road, you would avoid it,
you wouldn't step in it.
So you actually, in order to not be snared by a form of a woman, a man needs to actually
abandon the light and holding on to his masculinity.
It doesn't mean he needs to become feminine, which means he needs to not regard the given
masculinity as belonging to him.
He was given to no one, he has just a reason, and he will cease when the argument is
break apart.
There is no need for him to take it up and interfere with it, and the same goes for a woman.
Her femininity is a reason, it's a potential, it was given, whatever, determined by chance,
by elements, by previous lives, whatever, it's just how it is, and she's fully responsible
for taking it, and she will be fully responsible for freeing herself from it.
If she doesn't take it, it doesn't mean she has a sex change and becomes a man or something
like no, it just simply means whatever has a reason, you leave it as it is.
So then that femininity for a woman will not entrap her, and by not being entraped into
that, that is liable, basically, to be snared by the opposite, by the masculinity.
She won't be, she won't be snared by neither.
So you're responsible, a man is responsible for dwelling, for entertaining, for delighting,
for holding onto his masculinity, because of that, he's liable to snare, that sort of
comes and covers up that field of masculinity where he abides, carelessly.
If he were to withdraw his mind from that notion of masculinity, he can be very masculine externally,
but his mind is not taking it to be his.
He doesn't need to go to like a, I don't know, a retraining of his speech or behavior
and become refined and soft spoken and stuff, that's just management of external circumstances
which will never a problem in itself, which means that management is completely misguided.
So whatever, like, you know, if your habits are a course, whatever, if your habits are
a course, or whatever, it doesn't matter, what matters is you don't actually appropriate
the pictures a whole for a man that pictures him, he's a masculine, it's a man.
So he can, he can, he can stay masculine, as long as that masculinity doesn't belong
to him, that's all it takes, except for a woman, obviously they will limit the amount
of your interaction, so to speak, the amount of actions you will do an account of that
masculinity, like somebody who is entertaining that masculinity will obviously be revolving
on a woman who, who, who delights in her femininity, will obviously be putting that forward,
her feminine side, she'll be indulging it, taking it step further, developing it, refining
it, whatever else.
So that won't be done by the person who has abandoned either masculine and femininity
respectively, but it doesn't mean that they have to undo whatever has a reason on its
side, because you're a man, it's a fact, you're born in a male gender, you're born in female
gender, that's it, you don't need to deny it, you know, because whatever, you don't know
the escape from it, which is usually when people try to do it, how it's genderless, it's
beyond gender, it's not, gender is given, it's a fact, it's your world, your body is your
world, it determines it, determines the intentionality behind it, determines all the desire, but
you don't have to take it to belong to you, and that's what Aranji is, so a woman can
stay a woman, she'll stay a woman, and she can be an Aranth, obviously she won't be
doing anything else in reality, or anything else in a kind of appropriation of the body,
which she has completely free herself from, so her mind goes beyond it, but it doesn't
mean that you deny it, she still knows the fact that this is a female body, and same
for a man, because what about the, she could, when he could make the other, by entertaining
his masculinity, he knows what he's doing as well, he has a track team, yes, of course,
that's a female, of course, yeah, no it can be, it can be done intentionally, there's
no doubt about that, it's a seduction, no matter who does it to who, but then that would
be impossible if a man, like a man wouldn't be able to seduce a woman if he's not giving
notions and appropriating and delighting in his masculinity, and same, a woman who is
given up her femininity, wouldn't be out trying to seduce men, nor would she be out, or
even delighting in the notions of being liked by men, or being disliked by men, does
it even matter to her, and same, it even matters to a man, if every, like, like, like, when
they were on the ruler, they had a hand, he was apparently in the suit, as he was still
very handsome, so lots of women, just, you know, when they were not, when they were
doing this, and when they tried to seduce him, and you know, number of our rules evolved
around that, like, not to belong because the stories that had happened to him, I mean, he
was all avoiding it, I mean, he was in that round, but then the Buddha said, well, somebody
who's not in that round, he ends up in that position, they might quite likely give
in, so then all the rules, they evolved around, in secluded with a woman, and so on, to
be avoided, he was around the stories when he, you know, and they're quite a few times
he's not able to come up, because he was clearly still attractive to the, to fit, to
the woman, but he was in that round, so he wasn't entertaining it, nor was he all trying
to seduce it, he's just, obviously, the other minds, they were still in kind of trapped
by their own femininity, would find this form that comes in their range, a form of
Wanderblum, or attractive, yeah, and then she tried to seduce that innkeeper, the woman
yes, yeah, when she got rid of me, no, I'll don't say this crowded, I'll give you a secluded
innkeeper, yeah, and then she got into special, but then she, when he did not respond to
her advances, then she felt, oh, a bit ashamed, and then, well, actually impressed, because
she said, oh, she was also good looking, according to her own account, because she said,
many people tried to, you know, pay her wealth just to spend the night with her loads of,
but here, look, I'm offering myself to this, this, this, this reckless, and he's not
even looking at me, and then she dressed herself up, I apologize, and took a refuge in within
a month, because she was inspired by it, doesn't know what a boy done with it, so, because
there's this, let's suit, let's suit her about, a teleporter, the actor, yes, and yeah,
he asked the Buddha, where will I be reborn, as an actor, the Buddha says, don't ask me that,
he was the actor comedian, yeah, a comedian, yeah, you don't ask, so I think comedians,
you know, asked the Buddha three times, and the Buddha said, no, no, no, you don't know
this, and then he said, and the, he said, the other, other actors say that, because he's
an actor comedian, he will be reborn, yeah, in the, in the realm of the laughing devours,
and the Buddha said, I'm afraid not, you'll be born in the laughing hell, in the realm of
the laughing hell, and he's like crying, because he was actually happy, yeah, now he found
the right way that he shouldn't be, yeah, the Buddha thought he was crying, and he said,
see, I told you don't ask me, because I knew, like, you know, he said, he said, no, no,
no, no, I'm not crying, because I'm upset, I'm crying, because I'm not, I've been told
the truth, finally, and like, I've been lied all this time, that by being a comedian,
I'm going to be reborn in this comedic heaven, but, but now I know the truth, and that's
when he went for, okay, and that's the Buddha said, you encourage others, agree, take
the illusion, yeah, like basically, the minds of others, they're not free from greed
aversion delusion, they come to watch you, and then you, with your mind, who's not free
from greed aversion delusion, perform actions, they make them laugh, and make the greed aversion
delusion increase, thus, like, basically, audience is full of greed aversion delusion,
actor is full of greed aversion delusion, and the old result of it is more, increasing
greed aversion delusion, like you're four or whatever, and that's just making things much
worse, that they actually are, because, because people's happiness revolves around sensuality,
more, more, you know, more adopted, so even comedy or whatever, just making happy, laughing
through, through, basically, through distraction, through, through carelessness and so on,
just bringing all the, all the assas, they're, they're already there to increase, all the
tense, all the tense, yeah, good, let's think with this, let in keep a woman, okay,
sure she went, she changed her ways, but encouraging, lasting others, oh yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah,
yeah, that is your responsibility, exactly, yeah, in the, yeah, exactly, yeah, you're developing
your masculinity, in order to seduce it, to infect minds of others with more lust and
aversion delusion, oh yeah, yeah, in that, in that way, yeah, oh yeah, that is, that, you
know, because that is the content, that's intentional action, somebody setting on, seduce a woman,
a woman, seduce a man, and then that results in their mind, being infected by lust, a
version or delusion, that's all basically, well, there is a good deal of shared responsibility
in that, yeah, I mean, their response of being ignorant in the first place, sure, for being
in the main of lust, for keeping themselves in the main of lust, for giving into lust, because
you can always say no, but obviously, the seduce has his own take, take of that, that, if
you think of, like this actor, now you think, pornography, or pornography, well, that is
like the course, yeah, yeah, that's the course, because that is just purely, solely based
and aimed at, just lust, just fire of lust, yeah, so yeah, movies, music, no matter how meaningful
it might be, the first facility is entertaining, purposefully this is basically fiction, taking
my way, romance, romance, yeah, and also, you know, it's done selectively, you know,
either romantic movie, you basically, you show the romantic things, romantic build up drama
or whatever else, you don't actually show everything in a human life, because people
probably gross by it, getting up, you know, having diarrhea, and then going meeting your
loved one for coffee, and still having to run to a toilet, yeah, you show that in a movie,
it would not be a romantic movie, but you only show the point of it, and that's not what
life is, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah,
I've heard it before, you've heard it as well, that to overcome these sexual desire, everyone
should tease the defilements, tease the defilements, go near, you know, go visit woman, go, that is
beyond stupid, that I would not even talk about it, give me something warm in, yeah, good,
good, because I think some people think, to entertain those sexual energies is, you become
stronger, basically, like, for example, the whole tantric practice in verticals, basically,
people try to overcome it, one way or the other, and they can't, they have absolutely no
idea how to, and then what did you, well, then they make a practice out of it, why, because
then they will feel like no, no, this is the way, they will feel like they're overcoming
it, overcoming the coarseness of sensuality, while still remaining very much engaging it,
so they just end up the whole purpose of the whole thing, it's just to lie to yourself,
to mask responsibility, to mask the failure, you're not able to send out your desire, you're
not able to overcome the sensual domain, and say, no, it's not about overcoming, it's
about whatever, engaging with it, teasing it, adding to it, you must not deny that energy,
you know, only a person who cannot overcome it will say that, because otherwise, you'd
have to admit to this of their weak, and they're not worthy, obviously, worthy of the goal
that they themselves set forward, without declaring their weakness, exactly, without declaring
it, and it would be actually much better if they would be authentic enough, transparent
enough, to admit that their weak, no matter how bad it feels, why, because that bad feeling
will, it might actually make them make proper effort further down the line, if they give
in and cover it up and say, no, no, no, it's not about, this is not weakness, this is
the strength, what, no, it's not, strength is giving up, you're not giving up, well,
you're not supposed to give up, you're supposed to entertain it, well, that's only a weak
person who would say that, a person who doesn't know how to give it up, and the only choice
for him is to entertain it, so what he ends up doing is basically just say more before,
entertain the sensuality, just kind of developing a different excuse for it, or a more elaborate,
or a more meaningful background, like on a spiritual practice, otherwise, because he's just
going to be very, very cold, you say the sense of shame disappears there, well it would,
yeah, yeah, you got, become stronger than me, you cover it up, you cover the sense of shame,
when you decide to cover the feeling of guilt for not being able to say no, and your sense
of shame goes with it, when you cover it, you cover it, that's right, yeah, well that's
taking to be a problem, yeah, sure, sure, yeah, we need not embarrass anymore, oh yeah,
there is that practice, yeah, yeah, when you don't feel such a shame, doing shameful things,
yeah, but you know, all this, all this sense of shame basically, it's no natural, it's
the product of society, and you really going to be empowered if you ignore it, that it's
shameful, and then just go ahead and do it, nobody's starting hard to live your life,
so, and that is what, what, you know, modest society kind of encourages one way or the other,
because again, the sense of shame bothers you, feeling of guilt bothers you, and then you
blame others for it, you don't recognize it, there is a natural aspect to
sense of shame, and feeling of guilt, sure, if the whole society is repressed, yeah, it's
delusional, repressed, whatever else, but that doesn't mean you should deny the entire
sense of shame on a personal level, because it is quite natural, and it would have said
these are the natural protectors of the world, without the natural sense of shame, well,
men would be like dogs, brothers would sleep with sisters, sisters with fathers, mothers
with sons, just, just, they would be complete, complete disarray, but it bothers people,
they don't know how to deal with it, they don't have any wisdom in regard to it, to recognize
it, yeah, there is an overflow of like, shaming and guilt by the society, certain societies
in some, I don't know, repressed countries or whatever else, but that doesn't mean that
is the entire thing, there is the personal aspect of that sense of shame, because yeah, it's
a shameful thing, it's a private thing, so, and people can't draw their line, they can
sit there, so, when they rebel against it, they rebel against the whole thing, and they
become utterly shameless, utterly shameless, oh, and you feel liberated, that's it, that's
another world we've all liberated, because suddenly you feel free, it's basically like
a liberation of, of just giving, opening the floodgains of the desire even more, or there's
now, there's nothing stopping you, before you actually had that sense of shame, then
you mistook it to be something that it isn't, you denied it, you made the effort to cover
it, to destroy it, to ignore it, to rebel against it, and you feel liberated, it's a liberation
of just outpour, which means, sure, it feels a relief when you open the gates, but you
wouldn't feel a relief if you were to know what these floods are taking you, if they're
taking you down the messy waterfall, you're gonna crash at the bottom, you will not feel
a relief if somebody opens the gate, you will feel life threatening, and on the contrary,
you would feel relieved if the gates stay closed, so you don't flow down the waterfall
where you're gonna crash into death, but not knowing that, yeah, oh yeah, it's a joyous
ride, until, oh, it's too late now, to swim back, because that's one approach, trying
to escape such things, sensuality, he's, take tantric, he's tantric, Buddhism, tantric,
you know, find some contradiction in terms, take it in terms of contradictions, and meditation,
sensual celibacy, tantric Buddhism, Buddha, he goes on to carry, eat, carry a celibacy
from a chariot, and there's a sutra on that, where he describes what that is, and someone
would say this is the other extreme, like, completes the suppression, all these things
aren't, you know, it's just not the strict, it is, absolutely, you're beating yourself
out, you're not supposed to press the desires, because you see them, pointless, meaningless,
insatiable, and only resulting in harm, in a long run, so yeah, by all means, suppress
it, because through that suppression, wisdom might arise, one thing for sure, wisdom
will not arise from giving it, so wisdom will not necessarily arise through somebody
who is practicing full-on restraint, so wisdom will not necessarily arise just on that,
but it can, and one thing for sure, it cannot arise if there is no basis of restraint,
that's another sutra that we said, even if somebody spends the whole life without kind
of developing any wisdom, just through sheer restraint and saying no to desires, and even
if they go through extreme pains because of that, and spend the whole life in tears for
the rest of their life, it's still much better than giving in, like just once, because
in a long run, again, you spend years, forcefully, for somebody who is no wisdom, keeping
the mind away from giving into centrality, and that's making lots of merit, because
you know, people think merit for the future life is just through giving, no, that was
the lowest aspect, because they said yeah, through giving to one person, to the Buddha,
to the Buddha, to the other hand, to the Sangha, give more, but none of that would equal
the amount of merit, the streams of merit, you would make it like if you develop a finger
snap of a right view, a finger snap of freedom from centrality, a finger snap of non-cruelty,
finger snap of loving kind, a finger snap, so somebody for a whole lifetime, that's
what meant when I said in the beginning, it's actually, even if somebody doesn't want
to, in the Arab or whatever, it would be much better if they would practice celibacy,
they would say no to sexual desire, the mind would already grow by itself, just through
that, let alone if they make extra effort to gain wisdom, and they are, yeah, even if
it's painful for the rest of your life, so what, this is what means in the 50, 60 years,
how many years have you been reborn, how many years you will be reborn on account of
that, 50 years of crying your eyes out because of the pain and restring, nothing, they will
up in smoke, no time, yeah, the pain of restraint to the feeble of centrality, yeah, yeah, that's
like, you know, the most of the matter you can imagine, just practicing centrality strength,
non-cruelty towards people, non-identity, you say no to desires for the rest of your life,
what about, yeah, eons of heavenly rebirth, because those are the mental states, they will
take you there, but maybe I'm, if I have children, giving them opportunity to, to hear the
dumb, no, I don't follow that, what, people have children, they want to give, I've heard
it before, that you want to give other beings, no, sorry, so they have children, in order
for those children to later have opportunity to hear the dumb, yeah, well that sounds, sounds
like a terrible excuse, how about, because there is no guarantee you're going to become
an arrogant, even if you hear the dumb, so hearing the dumb in itself can be quite meaningless,
if a person doesn't know how to attend to it or doesn't want to, thus you can say to those
people who want to have children, you know, the children to hear the dumb maybe, it would
be better if they become arrogant themselves, so instead of optional remote possibility
of somebody becoming an arrogant by hearing the dumb in the future, they can become arrogant
themselves, and I mean one less than samsara, and that's the most you can do, but obviously
there is a much harder to do that than to produce a child.
So go and read the sutra on celibacy.
So then a Brahman, Janasuni, approached the blessed one and exchanged, weeding with him,
and said to him, does Master Gautama also claim to be one who lives the celibid life?
In the Buddha replies, if Brahman one could rightly say of anyone, he lives the complete
and pure celibid life, unbroken, flawless, unblemished, unstained, it is precisely of
me that one might say this, for I live the complete and pure celibid life, unbroken,
flawless, unblemished, unstained.
But what Master Gautama is a breached flaw, a blemish and a stain of the celibid life?
He's here, Brahman, some ascetic, or Brahman, claiming to be perfectly celibid, does
not actually engage in intercourse, sexual intercourse with women, but he consents to being rubbed,
massaged, bathed by them.
He relishes this, desires it, and finds satisfaction in it.
This is a breached, a flaw, a blemish and a stain of the celibid life.
He's called one who lives an impure celibid life, one who is feted by the bond of sexuality.
He's not freed from birth, from old age and death, from sorrow, lamentation, pain, grief
and despair, he's not freed from suffering, I say.
Again some ascetic or Brahman claiming to be perfectly celibid, does not actually engage
in intercourse with women, does not, nor does he consent to being rubbed, massaged, but
he jokes with women, plays with them, and amuses himself with them.
Or he does not joke with women, play with them, and amuses himself with them, but he gazes
and stays straight into their eyes, or he does not gaze and stays straight into the woman's
eyes, but he listens to their voices behind a wall, or through a rampart as they laugh,
talk, sing a weep, or he does not listen to their voices, voices of women behind a
wall, but he recollects laughing, talking and playing with them in the past, or he does
not recollect laughing, talking and playing with them in the past, but he looks at a household
order, enjoying himself furnished and endowed with five objects of central pleasure.
Or he does not look at a householder, enjoying himself furnished and endowed with five objects
of central pleasure, but he lives the spiritual life, aspiring for rebirth in a certain
order of David's thinking, by this virtuous behaviour, observance and austerity, or spiritual
life, I will be a David, or one in the retinue of the David's, he relishes this desire and
desires it and finds satisfaction in it.
This too is a breach, a flaw, a blemish, and a stain of the celibate life.
Of the perfect celibate life, that is because now people might think of him and I must
not do anything, but it's actually better to at least be virtuous even if you are desiring
for the sake of rebirth than to be engaging in sexuality, because as that sort of a venerable
nanda was struggling and wanted to disrobe, and the Buddha said, why do you want to disrobe?
He said, well, there was this servant girl, there was quite pretty and she told me when
I come back, she will be waiting for me.
And then he showed him the beauty of the Davas, there was 500 names, whatever it was in
the service, and then he said, which is prettier, the names, or that servant girl, and he said,
well, the names, the servant girl is like a culturalized monkey, with ears bent off,
there's nothing comparison, he said, okay, well I can guarantee you, you're going to
have those names, they were names, if you practice the legacy for the rest of your life,
there will be your rebirth, and then he was like, okay, well, I'll do that, then you
go on motivation, however, sometime later the monks heard that, and then they were basically
looking out upon him and he felt ashamed, and then he actually made the effort properly
and became an adult, but yeah, it is better, even if you're desiring heaven, it is better
than committing the kind of animal-like sexuality in this world, it's not perfect, and the
sutra deals with perfect celebrities, so it's not perfect, so nobody says, oh, it's fine,
but you do need, like a person needs to distinguish, it's not on the same footing as having
sexual integrals, or allowing women to rub you, or you're rubbing them, or listening to
them, or talking to them, or depending on their company, all of this, they fantasizing
about that, if you can't give it all up, when at least do it like the last way, think
about heaven and practice rebirth for that, practice restraint for that sake of better rebirth,
it's still better, not ultimate, but better, because it sounds like repression, if you
really, you know, it is, it is repression, but it's just people, it's repression, yeah,
it is, so what, you are in a position to repress, in the same sense, like giving in, well,
it's, it's, it's, it's, what's the opposite of repression, well, giving in, I don't
do this, I guess it does, yeah, oh, this is just repressing, yes, you're, you're fighting
against some sort, the Buddha said you're going against the grain, yeah, that's exactly
what repression is, there's nothing wrong with it, sure, if you go mad and lose it while
you're too weak, the grain you were trying to resist it, then you just swept you, tough
luck, so you make yourself stronger, but one thing for sure, you never become stronger
if you practice no repression, no restraint, yeah, if you're strained, such, and fear of repression
is really just fear of going against centrality, fear of saying no to yourself, no to your
own mind, because if you say no, it might rebel and basically drive you mad, which kind
of reveals contradiction, which means that mind is not yours, yet you regard it very much
as yours, yet you're afraid to say no to it, but being mind means you're in full control
of it, supposedly, but if you can't say no to yourself, means you're not in full control
of it, thus that's not your mind, thus you should really be afraid when you're giving
into it, yeah, it's a scary man knocking on your door, and you're afraid to leave the
door closed, because he might break it in, but so you open the door, and then you let
him in, and that's even worse, it's absolutely no resistance there, because who knows, he
might not be able to break the door if you don't turn it a bit strong, if you learn how
to fortify before he breaks it, one thing for sure, if you let him in, then you're in his
mercy, or maybe he'll take me to put it the good way, maybe he'll take, maybe he won't
harm me, maybe, maybe, similarly, he will harm you, and that's what we said, was it the
assassins, the sixth, the sixth is like the assassin, the mind, the dearest, like a dearest
friend that you trust with your life, and then he kills you in your sleep, that's like
the nature of a pleasant relationship with that mind, you never question a mind, your
own mind as your own enemy, you don't see it as a dangerous assassin, it's just trying
to get your sort of your friendship, your trust, and then kill you, at the end of that
day, the Buddha still says, but when I did not see even one of these seven bonds of sexuality
that had not been abandoned, then I claimed to have awakened to the unsurpassed perfecting
enlightenment in this world, the knowledge and vision arose in me, unshakable is my
liberation of mind, this is my last birth, now there is no more renewed existence, when
you saw that it was perfectly sober, the mind was completely drawn from it, but again,
those trying to perfect those points, you know, not even looking in a woman's eyes, there's
that time that the Buddha says, if you do, if you have to look, you have to look, again,
all of that, I mean, you know, the Buddha was talking with women and queens and whatever
else would come to me, so you have to understand that this is all these acts are not to be done
if they are rooted in sexuality, so again, don't just deny everything and cover your
eyes and run away if there is just a woman on the other side of the road, that's just
neurotic really, I mean, in the beginning, you should do it if you can't differentiate,
but don't hold that to be the perfect behavior, because one way or the other, you're running
away from it, which means it's bothering you, which means you're not free from it.
So all of this refers to when you're doing it for the sake of basically a sexual desire,
then it doesn't go to the point of sexual intercourse, but then you're like, oh, in touch
for the sexual desire, and maybe you don't let them touch you, but then you could talk
to them, you'd shout them up just for the enjoyment of sexual desire, then you might be talking
to them, then you're listening to them, looking at them, listening to them, fantasizing
about them, but if that's not rooted anymore, you obviously wouldn't be fantasizing about
them, and if you were to talk to them for whatever reason, it wouldn't be rooted in that
like, a sexuality in the design for sex, you just thought it wouldn't be rooted in that.
It might seem a bit rude to people as well.
Well, yeah, and sometimes it might be, and that's, again, you recognize, okay, so I'm
not supposed to, you know, be neurotic about it, but it's better to start a bit neurotic,
that's even not, then to start a bit loose, so if, during your neurotic phase, you might
be rude, it's okay, take, take, you know, on the responsibility for it, but, but recognize
it, okay, well, it's just a side, it's a fact of, of the current behaviour I'm engaging
in, which is like extra slightly neurotic restraint, so it's rude, but it's okay, I can live
with it, better to be rude, with a prospect of enlightenment, then polite, and ignorant.
I'm not just saying rude behaviour, by the way, but I'm just saying, if you recognize,
yeah, some people just rude, because they care less, but this is different.
Yeah, not to encourage it as well, and others, because you can also, it might be coming from
you, but you see the mind of the other is infected, by the loss, yeah, that was the point of
the, of all those, like, I'm rude, it was an art, he wouldn't have, he couldn't have
engaged in any sexual activity with that woman, but would have said, but if any other who
was not an art and was in that circumstances, he most definitely would have, so that's
why you prevent the circumstance, however, again, you must not neglect, and you must
not ignore the fact that it's all for the purpose of developing wisdom, because there is
no end then, to try to, to try to kind of say no to circumstances, and then you just
become ridiculous, and then people justify it all because it's the restraint, not necessarily.
If you're doing it out of, as we spoke before, you know, there is the obviously strength,
but then if you're just going out of this, this is like insane, ridiculous random measures,
like what giants used to do, and you just clearly, just you can see how it evolved,
irrationally, where they would go to arms, arms, and then obviously get the food, but then
you just felt too indulgent, then you take food only out of that, and after every third
house, then you don't take food on the, on the person on the right side of the crossroads,
then you don't take food from a woman, then you don't, no, you don't take food from a
woman, then you don't take food from a woman, then you don't take food, then you take
food every, then you don't take food at all, this is just ridiculous, and yet that's
often the attitude people might have, they might not take it in that regard, but when
it comes to like saying no, and just fear, and then just no to this, no to this, no
reason, then it becomes ridiculous, but it's, it's saying easy, it's completely irrational,
and by giving in, by encouraging that irrational behavior, you forget that your, the response,
well, your responsibility is to develop wisdom on the basis of restraint that you are practicing,
so you forget about that dimension, and all you end up doing is investing more effort
in just restraining your restraint, there is no need to push it further, leave it, because
you are restrained, leave it, and now do the work, now just exactly, now do the work, now
just go back and keep tightening already things that are already tight enough, because
that restraint obviously was not, not fantasizing about sexual behavior, is a world reveal that
craving to go in that direction, that's the need for that pleasure, it will just be revealed
if you're looking for it, it will show you straight away, but if all you're looking for
is the next step for your restraint after this completely restrained, every aspect yet
you then just keep okay, restraint further, and further, you'll never stop and look back
and see what the real problem is, the craving, the desire, the ignorance, you're which
was always the problem, and just to read that suitably, he spoke about in the beginning,
called a union and disengagement, because I will teach you a Dharma exposition on union
and disengagement, listen, and what is a Dharma exposition on union and disengagement?
A woman attends internally to her feminine faculty, her feminine comportment, her feminine
appearance, her feminine aspect, her feminine desire, her feminine voice, her feminine ornaments,
she becomes exited by these and takes delight in them, excited by them, taking delight in
them, she attends externally to a man's masculine faculty, his masculine comportment, his
masculine appearance, his masculine aspect, his masculine desire, his masculine forays, his
masculine ornaments, she becomes excited by these and takes delight in them, excited by
them, take delight in them, she desires union externally, and she also desires the pleasure
pleasure and joy that arise on account of such union.
Beings who are delighted with their femininity enter upon union with men.
It is in this way that a woman does not transcend her femininity and likewise with a man.
And the opposite where she doesn't attend to her femininity, then there's disengagement.
Exactly.
It's not entertaining the basis for all those things, because I delight in the femininity.
So instead of blaming men or men blaming women, just uproot the delight in your own manliness
or in your own femininity, uproot it, you have to deny it.
There was that sort of a monk couldn't free himself from, oh no, I think that was in the rules.
I know, I think it was the suit actually.
When he couldn't free himself from central desire, so he kind of started going mad and he cut his sexual organ off.
And he said foolish, instead of cutting one thing, he cut a wrong thing.
Cutting the ignorance.
Yeah, because that's not your masculine, ignorance in regard to the masculine form, is masculine.
So you can have all the masculine form you want, if you're not ignorant in regard to it, if you're not delighting it, if you see it as impermanent, if you see it as not personal, not dear to it, not yours, not internally held, same for a woman.
Because you're whatever you've born, you'll always be that. Exactly. And it wasn't yours to begin with, actually.
Because if you were to truly own that form, you wouldn't age, you wouldn't get sick, you wouldn't die.
He has its own cause, basically. You're just interfering with it.
And their cause is the cause of impermanent.