Yes, the other day you were talking about experience, you used the example of experiences
looking, experiences like looking into the mirror, remember you were explaining, it's
like a mirror, it's like a mirror, and that.
Well, I do remember the context, no, I forgot the context, it's basically about, ah, no,
not like a mirror, but more, okay, yes, like a mirror, like you can't see or access from
directly, but you can recognize, or you can experience is the appearance of it, which
is basically, ah, like a mirror image of that, which is mirrored, but you can only, whatever
you look, it will be looking at that mirror, in other words, you can't look away from
the mirror, or from that reflection, and see the thing that's been reflected, all you
can get is the reflected of the matter.
So your number, it's basically the reflect, as the only thing that sort of arises, it's
the old, the old, ah, the, the reason thing, ah, basically that's because of which, sorry,
matter is that, because of which this number will arise, which means, it's because of
that matter, but see, when you say that matter, that already belongs to that, that designation
belongs to that number, which means it belongs to that, ah, reflected image.
So you all, the only way to, to, to know, ah, that, ah, matter is there, is to discern,
so you can't see through the senses, it doesn't appear directly, so basically by fully understanding
number, you then discern, the number, it's because of that, which does not appear, but
it's there, as a necessary condition, what appears, that which appears, if anything ever
appears, it will appear within number, which means, there's the only way to appear,
which means that's what appears and sees, ah, but then appearance will not be there, if
there is no matter, to support the appearance, but you can never see the matter, even when
you think about the matter, you think within the realm of designation, which means, you're
thinking is part of that number, but when that's, that one, so it says, ah, as it's about
conceitings, whatever you conceit, it's always other than that, ah, yeah, whatever it is,
but, but, I, I think that Suta, if I remember correctly the context, he was just, ah, just,
he wasn't dealing with these, on the subtle level, these things, he was just basically
saying that, whatever protusion conceives, things end up being differently, but you could
say, what I haven't had, but conceiving, in itself, basically, like, monoperas, it's
already, ah, well, it's already the form of distortion, no matter how subtle the conceiving
is, and that's exactly the point, you conceive, there you go, you have the matter, and then
you have the appeared, well, you have the appearance of the matter, that's what you have,
based on that, you can discern that that appearance, is obviously the appearance of that matter,
but even saying that that matter, that actually, it's part of that appearance, that designation,
so you can't go beyond the appearance, or, or science, like, look sideways, and then
find that, which is the, the, the, the cause for that appearance, because it would, the only
way to know that there is matter behind appearance is, because of that, which appears, so the
matter can never be accessed directly, as appearance can, so you're going to have this appearance,
well, whatever you think about matter, and that's the thing, that's monoperas, so basically,
it's that appearance, that you then conceive to be that matter, you conceive it to be in
that matter, you conceive it to be out of that matter, you, in other words, you conceive
the matter, through not understanding appearance, see, the fact that, like, if you, if you were to,
if you were to, if you were to assume that this appearance is in the matter, you fail to
see that that thought in the matter is already part of that appearance, but no, you, you don't,
you don't take it like that, you take it to stand for that, which that matter is, because
of which this appearance is, so many to replay this, and it's your time, but basically,
it's, it's quite essential, or you conceive to be out, or in and out, or both, or to be
mine, or whatever, whatever permutation you can do, any of those things, it's irrelevant
whether you conceive it in or out, to be mine, to be for me, to be I am, the point is,
you're conceiving relationship, and if you're conceiving relationship, you are putting
the appearance, and the matter, because of which appearance is, you are putting them on
the same footing, you, you, by comparing them, by relating them, not necessarily comparing
them, but by relating them, you are basically conceiving the matter, because even that thought
of, oh, this is from the matter, it's apart from the matter, it's in the matter, it's
out of the matter, it's because of the matter, that thought of that matter, it's part of
that appearance, but you take it to stand for the matter because of which appearance is,
because you conceiving, you gave it life that it doesn't actually have, you gave it being
that it doesn't have, thus you made it exist, just through that, but if you thoroughly understand
appearance, as again, the illustration I gave of the mirror in front of you, and the thing
that appears is behind you, it's obviously not perfect, because in the long as a sumic
you can just turn your head, but you can't, in this case you can't turn your head or look
somewhere where you will access that matter, because all you can ever access will be the
appearance, because that's what appears, that's what accessing is, which, which that means
that this matter is always below your feet, always, and fully discerning that will make you
then completely relinquish any notion of belonging in regards to anything that appears,
and what do you pick, everything appears, five only it's appeared, the nature is to appear,
disappear and persist or change, so you abandon the whole thing, through seeing that it's
fully undermined by the four great elements, for example, in this example, and they can
never, you can never access the four great elements, yet your entire life, your entire existence
is big, it's like directly found in the pond and even you think, oh I can't access the
four great elements, you can be conceiving the four great elements, if you think that
thought stands for that which four great elements is, but it can't stand because that thought
has appeared, thus it's part of the appearance, but the discernment can pertain, the knowledge
can be directed towards that which does not appear, but it's the ultimate determination
of your entire experience as a whole, so you can discern, and that's just basically
changing the direction, so you never arrive at that because of which this appearance is,
because that will make it appear, but you just change the direction, instead of for me
it's opposite, it's not for me, it comes from elsewhere, and that's enough for dispassion,
so any appearance, any experience, yeah it's not for me, so it's the opposite or for me
like towards you, it's the rises for you, whether it take you to leave it, it's up to you
but it's for you, my eyes, my sights, it's all for me, it's mine, well now you take
it completely against that direction, you go the other way, it's not for you, it arises
from that which you cannot even conceive in your thoughts, you can't think of it, but
it is that because of which, and see even when I'm talking about it like this, that's
obviously the limits of the designation, you are talking about it, like you know, like
I said, oh it's inexpressible, but I just expressed it, and this is the nature of designation,
so you should not mystify that because of which your appearance is, you should discern
it, and the Buddha said, when the four great elements change, and the four great elements
they find the footing in your experience through your concealings, through the consciousness
because if I think about earth, yes, that's all you can do about it, but by recognizing
that the appearance is all you have, it will make you stop assuming that you can actually
access the great elements, or access anything so to speak, you can't even access the five
other gates because if you were able to access them in that sense, you would be their owner,
but you are not, you can't be, so you're just constantly maintaining that assumption
that basically feeds the conceivings, and it's because of the conceivings, you just maintain
the vicious circle that's completely different, actually, it's unnecessary in any shape form.
So the recognition of the five other gates, as being inaccessible to you, means okay,
you change the direction, they're not for you anymore because you can't, you can't uphold
them, you can't, you're not in their control, and they're not in your control because they
are determined by that, which you can't even think, let alone see, taste, the touch,
completely behind you, completely underneath, below your feet, you are the reason for, you
are sorry, you are the result, the result of them, yeah, you can say that, you're the
simultaneous presence, your whole life, the simultaneous presence of that means these
things are present because I'm still alive, because my aggregates are still there, means
the elements are still there, the consciousness in regard to them is still there, but all
of that is indirect to you, what you have direct in front of you is Nama in regard to
Lupa, and that's it, and what about the famous, this body and name and form externally,
the around experiences, yeah, that's slightly, slightly different, different approach from
this, but if you were to remove all the assumptions, all the conceivings, and you recognize that
this very body, that you, well, the appearance of this very body is comprised of those four
great elements, and the four great elements can be discerned in regard to that appearance,
and that's absolutely fine, as long as you don't start, well, there wouldn't be a discernment,
basically, as long as you don't start then regarding the discernment, as that, those elements
because of which this body is, because the discernment of the elements, the four great elements,
and the appearance of the body as a result of the four great elements, they're both appearance,
they're on the level of appearance, they share the nature of appearance, they're on different
level of generality, obviously, the body is particular manifestation, the four great elements
and notions of four great elements, but they can accurately stand for the four great elements
if you don't conceive four great elements through those notions, that was in relation
to the other talk we spoke recently about the abstraction, when things cease to be abstract,
they stand for that which they are, and your thought will stand for that element, will
be an accurate representation, because that's all it can be, a representation of four great
elements of a great element, when it doesn't conceal the element through that, so for an
argument with three from conceivings, all that is left is this conscious body here, this
matter paired with consciousness externally, and all the name and forms externally, all
the things that arise, name and form, basically all of the appearance externally, in other
words, the direction of internal mind towards me has changed and now it's all external,
even your utmost personal thoughts, it's just the external appearance, this conscious
point, means basically the arrangement of the consciousness and the elements, it's still
operating, the arrangement that you can't just, you can't even conceive anymore, on a higher
structure, well not on a higher or on a probably more, on a deeper, below your feet, on
your ground, underneath your ground, well in a way it's more general, but no more general
to pertain to things that would appear more generally, it's more immediate, and the way
it appears, this conscious body, when it appears as a thought, that thought doesn't conceive
it to be, that conscious body to be in, that conscious body, from the conscious body,
apart from or for me or mine, it doesn't conceive, it doesn't conceive, you just have a thought
as a mirror representation of the conscious body present, because of which you can still
descend to the conscious body's present day, because of conscious body still present day,
and all of the appearance in regard to it, that's external to you, well not even to you
anymore, because that would imply a certain relationship, all this external to me which
could imply internal, no it's just external, internal becomes external, just less external
than external external, because internal is usually mine, dear, appropriated, so that
internal dimension of putugina stays, it's just not seen as external, and think that
we're external, we're seen as externally external, because we're talking about today
about putting the structure, by the existence, into the right order, so we're talking
when the structure is in the right order, the structure is in the structure, you just
stop conceiving the wrong order, over on top of the existing order of the structure,
and that's doing the same, that's what, well yeah in a way that means not conceiving basically,
because the order of things, yeah, well let's put aside the four great elements, because
that might be the subtle, but back onto the conscious body, right here, the senses, so
you can, as I was telling you today, you can actually touch your eyeball, yeah, close
your eyelids, and you can feel the shape, you can feel everything, and it is that flesh
that you're touching, that bowl, that you're touching, with your fingers, that is that
because of which, there is a whole life of vision, of sights, things you see, desired
and lost in regard to them, fear in regard to things you see, grief in regard to things
you see, anything basically, the whole world in regard to things you see, and same goes
for every sense, yet if you were to touch an apple that had to torch your eyeball, it's
all, it's all shares in nature, it's all material, but it's this particular matter that
pertains to your body, then it's also paired with consciousness, and obviously you can't
see that consciousness, it's just the fact that you can discern that it's paired with
consciousness because you see as a result of that flesh yeah, you don't see as a result
of an apple or a cup or a table, you see as a result of this eye, so that's the only
difference, is the particular arrangement of that matter enables you to see the forms
because the consciousness is there with it, but you, there is no further, like you can't
take this to further to greater analysis to explain because as I said consciousness
doesn't appear, so you can talk about it but most likely you end up conceiving it, you
end up giving it that which doesn't have, but what you can do is recognize that it's
only the passion in regard to eye and forms, lastly in regard to eye and forms, heal well
in regard to eye and forms, delusion in regard, that's only matters, so you have to do,
it's fine with regard, you stop giving possibility for last to arise in regard to eye and forms,
and that's it, when the last is removed then that's all it needs to be done, then what
is left is this conscious body, this fleshy eye, this fleshy nose, this fleshy tongue, there
is still out there below my feet with consciousness, and I know that because things still appear
for me, thus when those aggregates break apart that's it,
to be mindful of the, that which doesn't appear yet is the basis of your appearance, well
no you couldn't be mindful of that which doesn't appear, you can be mindful of the appearance
in regard to that because of which appearance is, and the more accurately mindful you are,
as conceiving as a present, but that which doesn't appear, well you just made it appear
through the statement, it is that which doesn't appear, and that's fine, you can't have
a state, you can't have a designation, you can't have Nama in regard to root by C conceivable,
and that's for people expect to access Rupa, or they assume that they have access to Rupa,
and then my Nama is kind of optional, no it's not, Nama Rupa, Rupa is revealed through
the designation of Nama, that's why it's inseparable, Nama Rupa, so that revelation
is very inaccurate, it's conceived, so all you have to do is sort of make it accurate,
stop conceiving it, purified, but only when I have the Nama Rupa, as the way I said,
this conscious body, a name and form externally, that's what's left for the Nama, so even
other end doesn't remove name in regard to form, or doesn't access form in the name forms
of, it's name and form, it's just discerning properly, through that name, you can then remove
the footing for the form in terms of conceivable, so you can liberate yourself, so mindfulness
in the, let's say mindfulness of the body, and when you think, when you have a thought
of mindfulness of the body, you're not actually directly mindful of those four great elements,
because you can access them, if you're mindful of their appearance, or rather you're mindful
of appearance, because that's what appearance is, it's not their appearance, the appearance
is, and the appearance is because the four great elements are still there standing,
is that the body that should be noticed in the sake of the time now, that's, which,
what do you mean that?
Well, that's what you've got to understand, that's what, that's what the body that you
want to see, we might love it, is the body that appeared, if you're properly mindful,
you'll, you'll, you'll understand mindfulness, you'll understand appearance, you would stop
conceiving, but if you, even through a practice of mindfulness, still think that this is that
the body, no, it's comprised of the four great elements, means the appearance, it's made
of it, but that's all you have, but the mindfulness, if you start being mindful correctly, it's
not mine, not for me, not I am, because that's it, as I said, you come to mindful of the actual
elements behind the body, or underneath it, but you can disown the body, which then will
become an accurate representation of the four great elements, and their ultimate nature
is, they're not yours, they cannot be yours, they're not even possible to be yours, so
you start emulating that in regard to appearance, and eventually it will, it will stand for, for
how things actually are, which means you've been around, then you can't undo it, so as
proper mindfulness has to be paired with that knowledge, absolutely, right view comes
first, even the mindful, this cannot be the right one, there's no right view, no matter
how general that mindfulness is, the right view always comes first, which is why any
makes everything else right, then upon it, it's like this in the Anapanasati Sutra, there's
one section in the beginning, it's always translated, calming the bodily formation, what is the
bodily formation, the breath, breathing, Anapanasati Sutra, Kainasankara, here, while breathing
in the experiences, the whole body, or the whole breath, there are people that have the
breath of the body, but the experiences while breathing, the whole body, and then the
next sentence says, while breathing, you have to, he breathes calming, the body formation,
now if the body formation is breathing, he could have said calming the breath, well, he
could have said that, but then he wouldn't be seen as Sankara, he wouldn't serve for
a student, recognition and cultivation of the simultaneous principle of Sankara and Sankara
to them, and that's the whole point, full understanding of the principle means our
energy, but if he just says, he just can't be breath, you won't be seen, but he depended
upon the action of breathing, that's the point, the point, you take on mindfully an act
of breathing, in the same sense, the will turn, turns the will like this, turns the will
like that, you breathe in like this, you breathe, it's not that you're trying to control it,
in terms of stock it, or force it, the breathing is there, but you kind of, like, imagine
the horses that are already running, but then you join in and you take the reins, but
you don't interfere with the running, but you do take the reins, and you might slow it
down or something, but there's still going the direction and you're not changing that,
so you take on the mindfully an act of breathing, and then you can influence through the existing
act of breathing, you can okay, along the breath, short and the breath, the point is you're
mindful of the breathing, that experience being mindful of the breathing, because breathing
is bodily, it's bound with a body, it's inseparable, it's inconceivable, so even just the thought
of breathing already implies the experience of the body, it's in there, so when you're
thinking about breathing, when you're breathing, through that you're already imploring a form
of experience of the body, and that experience of the body is determined by your active engagement
in breathing, so your record is, because the breathing of the body is there, and obviously
the body is bound with a breathing, doesn't mean that, doesn't necessarily mean cause
an effect, breathing results in body, that means they're inseparable, that's it, that's
the problem, they always occur together, never apart, inconceivable to have them apart,
you can't concede the breathing without a body, inclined in that act, you just can't be,
no matter, even if it's the utmost abstraction, if you think breathing, it implies the body,
thus it's a body, it's a body, it's a body, it's bound up with a body, so then you recognize
okay, because this is inseparable from, this experience of the body right here, now separate
from breathing, you don't have to think about your active breathing, but this body here,
it's that body that is inseparable from breathing, so only form of experience of the body, it
will be the body that implies breathing, inasmuch breathing implies the body, so then through
calming down the mindful act of breathing, oh no, because that body, that abstract body,
you can say even like that, that is implied in my thought of breathing, that abstract
body is this body right here right there, and that relationship is external, but that
body that you think of, when you look through the act of breathing, is that body right here
right now, so then through affecting, through calming down the active breathing, calming down
those thoughts in regard to the active breathing, actually you are pretending you are gradually
affecting the body right here right now, because that relationship is external, the thoughts
that you had in regard to breathing and the body that's assumed in that breathing, you're
learning your head, that thought is the appearance of the thing, and that thought, that thought
that has the tacit implication of a body in regard to breathing, that body there is
the body that's right here right now, so when you think breathing and that abstract
body that appears, that body is the body that you can access through your body, unless
it's the thoughts of breathing, and that's it, it's this conscious body and name and form
externally, the thoughts of breathing are the name and forms externally that imply that
body, this conscious body right here right now, so instead of maintaining the connection
of my body, my thoughts, you actually pull it out and you recognize no, it's the conscious
body right here right now, and when I think about it, that's also external in regard to
the conscious body, there is no internal dimension that it's mind, so through cultivating the
act of breathing, the thoughts of breathing, the mindfully subreading, you start discerning
a phenomenon of body within that act of breathing, there is actually this body right here right
now, just seen from a different view at the same time, the body that appears, yeah, well
don't, yeah, don't worry, that's a different approach, don't try and mix it, the elements
and that, because of which it appears, but yeah, if you start seeing it at the same time,
if a thing is present wise or if it's seen at the same time from two points of view, so
to speak, none of them can be yours, because mind, me, I am, requires that singularity,
I look from here to there, but now you recognize a thing is present, I'm seen from there, and
experience right here at the same time, which one is yours, well you recognize none of them
can be yours, so put your attention and experience of the body right here right now, and
then start breathing, and through that breathing, discern the body, that then you study basically
this discerning as, oh, the body that I'm discerning through my breathing actually stands for
this very body that I'm experiencing right here right now, but the relationship is external.
And then you can spread it, a thought of the body, that's all the name Rupa, that then
you just conceived to be off, this is this body right here right now, through that internal
connection.
Oh, my thought is this body comes from this body, it's this body, in the body, out of the
body, from the body, it's for me, it's my, but when you recognize the thought of the body,
as in the reason phenomenon externally, and then see it standing for that body out there,
yeah, out there right here, for that flesh eye, for that nose, for the tongue, again, flesh
eye, it's a designation, it's an appearance, that stands for the flesh eye, but you assume
oh, it's my flesh eye, but if you see that that flesh eye will not be known if there is
no external appearance of a thought flesh eye, phenomenon without it, it's just inconceivable,
inseparable from you, then it can't be yours, then it just becomes all external, oh, it's
all out there, just there, right here, or younger, or whatever, none of it is mine.
Because that's the thing, you don't need to keep constantly attending to this body right
here right now, because this body is right here right now, and you're not sure about it.
All you want to do is stop misconceiving it, or misconceiving things that appear in regard
to this body right here right now.
So mindfulness of breathing, through actively engaging in active breathing, you start discerning
the body, the phenomenon of body, which you can, oh, this is my body, this is the same
as this body, this is the body, all you just are seeing this body is basically that's
the representation that we spoke earlier of the body present right here right now.
So there's one way I'm looking at it, all you can then just be mindful of the erison
body, conscious body right here right now.
You can't really imagine it, because if you would imagine it accurately, it wouldn't
be imagination, it would stand for how things are.
The generalizes is seen from two points of view, always, you can't just have one point
of view, inconsiderable, so it's always present, vice, simultaneous, not vice, there will be
one too.
Here's a present, it's double, explain that, yeah, I can try it, but I can see that everything
is seen from two different points of view.
Like everything other it is, it arises, there are two points of view to every experience,
simultaneous present, which is why you can then develop the assumption of one point of
view, which is me.
If you were to see that you're the center of your sense of self, it's always determined
by something else different than the sense of self, it's two things of present, the
center of the sense of self, and that which is there with you.
At the same time, it's simultaneously present, a colleague, that's what it means, not
pertain to time, it's simultaneous, there is no time in between.
So if whichever point of view you took to be used, within that you discern, there is determined
by that which you didn't take to be used.
If you take that to be used, you discern, there is some, basically, no matter what point
of view you take to be used, simultaneously it's determined by that which cannot be used
at the same time, because you can't have both things at the same time, because I would
require a third point of view, that's more general to these two point of view, but that's
inconceivable.
So you can't help but have a point of view, well sorry, you can't help but attend one
point of view, but through that you discern another direction, that it's not the same direction,
that it determines this direction.
So there is a direction of the conscious body, and there is a direction of the name and
form externally, and you can discern, both of them simultaneously present, obviously,
you have to be attending one point of view together, if you attend conscious body, you'll be
discerning the form externally, if you attend the form externally, you'll be discerning conscious
body through that.
But if that's all you can ever have, if you contemplate that long enough, you'll stop
assuming one single unifying point of view, that it's neither here nor there, no box
nor whatever, because that's only maintained through a simple knot, not discernment of
the arrangement of things, basically by knot, fully understanding that things cannot
be yours, you may attend the ocean of their mind.
So right here right now, while you're thinking about what I've just said, your body is seated
present with the conscious and spared with it, there's two same thing as things.
And no matter how hard you're thinking, whatever you're thinking, through that, the discernment
of this conscious body present right here right now is possible, because this conscious
body right here right now is there, and in this particular instance, it's basically the
reason why you're able to think in the first place.
That's why any dama can also be a sancar, any of the aggregates can also be a determination
because they're watching the breath.
It depends what you attend, then the opposite, if the discern the opposite of where your
attention is.
So if I'm watching the body, if you're watching the body, I can see that it's been
termination as the breath, but I'm not looking at the breath directly, I guess, so yeah,
I can see it in the background just there, or if I'm looking at the breath, I can see
the body.
The practice is on the panasati, but just in terms of that practice, watching the breath
and having the body.
Well, in terms of that practice, yeah, you want to be doing the manifest of breathing.
You want to be actively, because it's a form of enact, you want to tune yourself into
the new breathing, and you recognize through this very act, you start discerning the implicit
notion of the body, present, right there, right there, inseparable from.
If something were to happen, while you're breathing there and discerning the body through
the body, if those elements that the body is comprised of would change, disappear, be
affected by some other external factor.
You realize that the whole act that you're still mindful of engaging with breathing cannot
remain standing, yet its foundations are completely inaccessible to you.
You can't happen.
If something happens to the elements, you can't possibly continue breathing.
You can't possibly continue discerning the body through that.
So through contemplating like that, you have abandoned the very nature of action, of intentional
action that you're breathing.
It's an act, it's a neutral act, which is what it will praise it.
So you can't even do that long enough.
You develop mindfulness that then won't be disturbed by any other form of act that
the notion holds, obviously that, to be abandoned beforehand.
So when you're sitting, walking, eating, talking, none of that then becomes, none of that continues
to imply, well, the notion of permanence, the notion of controlling, regard to things.
So you abandon your own intention, ceases to be yours, because through practicing of intentional
ascending to breathing, and breathing in like this, breathing out like that, discerning
the body through that, and then seeing that if that thing changes, if that determination
is swept away, none of your present acts can remain.
You do that long enough, none of the notions of I am, and this is me, this is for me, can
remain standing, it will just evaporate.
So you just breathe, and through breathing simultaneously, you discerning the presence
of the body.
Now you can start attending to the body right here right now, but then obviously you're
not mindful of the breathing anymore.
It's fine.
You can be mindful of the body, but then you're not doing an open sati, that's also fine.
And there's just one way of developing mindfulness.
But if you are a stickton of a sati, you just continue breathing, while you discerning
the body through that, and then it is all right, if I calm down, this breathing, this
active engagement, that body will calm down.
If I slow down the experience of that body through that slowing down and breath will be affected
as well.
And then you can contemplate the flow of the truth, or any other thing, as the Buddha says,
through that breathing.
So you have refined your active engagement with the action, with the nature of action.
So you're not distracted, you're doing it mindfully.
And through that you discerning the present, because no matter what you're doing, whether
you're sweeping leaves, walking, sitting, talking, there is an implication of your body
present right there, simultaneously.
Because if that body is not present right there, right then simultaneously, you wouldn't
be able to be engaging in these acts actively at the very time.
You're not aware of it, you're not aware of the presence of the body.
While you engage actively in this task, because your attention is mindful.
So then you maintain the notion of appropriation through that very thing.
But you start discerning the body, and then you recognize that, well, there is no room
for me and I am in the act.
Direct, this act, this intention, these choices are making, next moment, are all possible,
because there is the implication that you can see through of the body, right what those
acts are present.
So is that thought that is crystallizing, or that body that's revealed, through mindful
engagement with these acts, or the body is always present, there's a phenomenon of present
body through these acts, and that body is at which this body is, when I think about it,
separate it.
So either, whether you think about it directly or indirectly, you stop conceiving it as
yours.
You see there's that thing out there, because of which you're able to move an act and
choose.
And then you start seeing your own choices as a result, because of that present conscious
body out there and out there at the time.
So then next time you make a choice, or rather, when you practice it sufficiently, then when
the choices are being made, even that, the most personal thing I want this over there,
ceases to induce the notion of personality, because its understanding is seen through
it through, because would you be able to think, unrelated things to your body, just think
something completely out of the imagination, abstraction, can't you see?
Would that be possible, if the body is not present?
If the body, if the consciousness is not present, then living there.
So no matter how disconnected, unrelated your thoughts might be, the nature of the thought
is bound with the body.
Inasmuch, the body is bound with the mind, I, thoughts.
Hence it only depends what you attend, it will be determined by the other.
Because you wouldn't be able to even think about body, or talk about body.
If the mind doesn't designate you as a time as body, as that, as that physical in regard
to itself, or as that mental in regard to itself.
So to fully discern that, those thoughts in regard to body would stop conceiving, would
stop making you assume that that is actually that matter, no, it's still the thoughts.
So you can have your thoughts and thoughts, that's why the mind comes first.
Would you know a cup is a cup?
Would you know matter is matter, like even saying it matter, thinking it matter.
That's all a good designation, that's all you have.
Just designations are different levels of generality pertaining to different things, but still
designations.
So what you really do is make sure that when it comes to the designation of the body,
in regards to body, whether peripherally, whether directly, when you're attending it,
you don't conceive that that is that matter, you don't conceive that that is what those
great elements are, because they will always remain below your feet, they will always remain
that because of which this appearance is, and this appearance in this case is the designation
of this body, right here right now that I'm seeing, I can touch parts of it, I can think
about it, that's all fine, that's the only thing you can have, even if you were to think
about it, just stop conceiving that to be standing for this external world of four great elements,
because that's another thought, so you have your thoughts in regards to thoughts, but those
thoughts can be discerned, oh they are because of the four great elements that I'm thinking
right here right now, which is all I can do, but I'm not conceiving to be those four great
elements, and that's the important thing, because if you only say, oh all you have is your
thoughts, then you fall into a very obvious naive form of ideal, whatever you think it's
in your head, well no, see, whatever I think it's in my head, you assume your head to be
materially in regard to your thoughts, but then even that is your thoughts, you can't even
in touch or be saying whatever you're thinking it's in my head, because that's in my head,
which is in my head, which is in my head, which is in my head, indefinitely, but if you
recognize the notion of my head, it's because it's underlined by the four great elements,
there are also another notion, but the notion does not conceive itself to be the actual
four great elements, or to be apart from them, which would imply them to be something else,
or to be in them, or to be from them, or to be for me, or to be mind.
The notion just doesn't conceive any of that, it's as the notion, it's known, and notion
is known as a notion, so it doesn't conceive that because of which the notion is, or put
it in more simple terms, the notion is fully disowned, the notion is disowned as impossible
to know, notion is a dharma, a dharma, notion is a phenomenon, notion of this, notion of
that, think, I thought you can call it whatever you want, basically a phenomenon, phenomenon
is that which has an age to appear, what has an age to appear, everything has an age
to appear that you can talk about, things that have no age to appear, you can't possibly
disown it, since they don't appear, you can't even think about it.
When you reach that understanding, abide in that understanding, yeah, become that understanding,
it would used to say about finding a balance in it, it's you, you can't find it.
When you need to balance it, once you understood, you can't undo the understanding, so there's
no balance to be maintained, because it's developed, and that's why you know it's developed
with vision that you see it, what you're talking about now, you see it, but then you
can, well you can know that it hasn't been developed sufficiently, it hasn't been developed
fully, and then you just have to keep repeating it and drilling it, they're very, same inside.
Find the best to get in there, those dummies, those, yeah, by understanding the dummies,
by understanding the, that which has an age to appear, which is your thoughts, your feelings,
your intentions, so perception has an age to appear, feeling has an age to appear, attention
has an age to appear, even your attention has an age to appear, because you can talk
well I'm attending to this, so it's indirect, it's negative in regard to what is being
attended, but it appears, has an attention, and so all of that is normal, the designation,
name, that's a Nama Rupa, Rupa, there you go, you just said it in the same sense, you
said in the same way you said Nama, so Rupa is also designation, but it's a more general
designation than the designation of Nama, more fundamental, directional, but it still
maintains actually to the nature of the designation, they then stops conceiving itself to be
that Rupa, Nama Rupa, that's all, what is all, it's Nama Rupa, that's all they can
appear, nothing else except Nama Rupa can appear, but it doesn't mean that Rupa is actually
the Rupa because of which Nama Rupa is as appearance, so there's only one way to correctly
accurately designate Rupa, and that way is by not having that designation stand for that
Rupa, if it doesn't, if it doesn't conceive that Rupa, the designation of Rupa doesn't
conceive Rupa, that's the only accurate designation, and that's the liberation, you practice
that, and it will be free from all conceivants, from all implications of my, thus from all
implications of I am, thus from all implications of self, myself, and personality, or you can
take your experience as a whole, and regard, and you have kind of things aspects of it
in a more mental, and aspects of it in a more material, so to speak, but both are actually
part of the designation, Nama in regard to Rupa, so what you have to do is, while they
are simultaneously present, well stop regarding the material aspect, as, stop assuming the
material aspect, as pertaining to the actual method, because of which the designation of material
aspects can, can arise, stop conceiving them, because any movement of your mind, it's
already pertaining to the, it appears, thus it's part of Nama in regard to Rupa, so you
can know your experience as a whole, and whatever shape and form can arise, it's because of
the four great elements, as long as that knowledge, well then you won't be a knowledge, but
as long as that thought, does not conceal the four great elements, through the thought
about them, you don't actually assume that that's what they are, or that there's something
else, or elsewhere, or both, or neither, you just don't give into any of those, you just
have a thought of four great elements, so you don't overdo it, you don't underdo it,
and then that thought won't be conceiving them, they won't find footing in your experience,
which means your experience will be free, and that's just something that needs to be repeated
on and on, not through different means, but you end up repeating the same principle,
by all the other things, it's a hard call of contemplation, it's a bit of a head spin-off,
well it's a head spin-off, obviously you will not be as particular as that, but you
don't have to, because they are much less particular things, sorry, much less ambiguous
things that you can contemplate, there would be maintaining and obviously drilling the
same principle, no mind, not for me, not for my control, if you extend that principle
to the point of pertaining to the thought of not mine, not for me, not my control, then
you won't leave anything excluded, and if you repeat that long enough, then that will
become apparent, because it does correspond with how things actually are, not yours, not
for you, not in your control, how do you call it, okay, that's the Mola Parianas
so it did amongst the not-the rejoicing world, because they didn't understand it, right,
for example, there's elements we're talking about today as well, essential pleasure, essential
pleasure element, and renunciation element, doubt, yeah, and your will element, not your
will element, cruelty element, not cruelty element, so when one is experiencing your will,
your will is the greater, and seeing those two things, why is it, then I'll go greater,
why is it more, why is it greater, why is it greater, but it takes, it doesn't take
you, no, that's why it holds them, but why is it greater, why is it structurally greater,
then your will, why is your will lower, then your will, because your will is determined,
no, it's because your will can only rise in regard to particular things, yes, that's
what I was trying, actually, yeah, it only, so if you experience your will, it's going
to be in regard to something, even if it's a very general ambiguous mood of thought, you're
having your will in regard to that, which means your will is always circumstantial, because
these things could have not or risen, so which is more, things that, sorry, no more, which
is more, oh yeah, no, can you have, can you have desired a last or your will in regard
to things that you've never seen, you've never heard, you've never thought of, you can't,
you can't have, you just see it's inconceivable to experience these other last or a version
in regard to that which is never, has never manifested in any particular form, you can't
have those, those things, you can only have non-real will, you can only have non-aversion,
non-last, that's the default mood, on the basis of non-last, you develop last in regard
to something that's being manifested, but if you know that I can't have lost in regard
to things that are not manifested, that means that whatever is manifested, it's circumstantial,
because if it was manifested and hasn't been manifested before, if it was manifested
means, it could have not been manifested, and it certainly means, oh, it's manifested,
does, it would unmanifest, it will cease because it has a reason, you can't possibly have
lost for that which does manifest, you can't possibly have well for that which does manifest,
so then when you do have last or your will, you recognize, oh, it's in regard to a circumstantial
thing that could have not been, does it completely treat us, does, it's unnecessary, does it's impossible,
because last would actually imply that whole notion of, oh, this is special, this particular,
this is worth, this is valuable, this is great, but when you recognize that it's circumstantial,
it, it, it, it, it, it, while it loses its elevators, this is important, yeah, that's
what it means by saying, non-nil will is greater, it's more fundamental, it's more important,
why, because there are more things that happen in a reason, there are more things that are
manifested, and for them we should, for them we can't have lost, we can't have a little
ago which means, there is more non-nil will, even for people who are always angry, they're
always angry, that's a particular, which means on the general level, there is more non-nil
will, so that's why you don't do the non-nil will, you just discern it, and because of that
you can't engage in a will, and same, you discern the absence of passion as an inherent
characteristics of the five aggregates, and because of that you stop at the 10 notions
of passion in regard to the five aggregates, who pedan is not the five aggregates, he can't
possibly be, but it's not found anywhere else apart from that, is the designer last in regard
to five aggregates, the idea assumption is there, the non-design, non-last, or the five
aggregates, it's greater than particular manifestation of desire in regard to the particular
manifestation of the five aggregates, it's always essential, it always could have not
been, and that's another of the manipulations before, you start thinking that over the things
that are appearing, oh this could have not been, and this it will not be for me, so this
could have not been, the things that will be will not be for me, because that circumstantial
mess of it, the thread of it just pertains to the past, to the present, and the past that
is present, and the future that is present as a possibility, oh so when the things in the
future, if this ball is still remains standing in your eyes, it's impossible for them to
arrive for me, as much as this present thing is also impossible to be accepted by me,
it's impossible to be for me, that's your real is always, my whole past was actually
never for me, and that's who it was never mine, so that's how you don't dwell in the past,
and you don't go in the future, by discerning the present, by discerning them through the
present, not by stopping your thinking and the refraining from thinking about your past.
But by fully discerning that if thing is inaccessible now, their nature pertains in the future,
and their nature pervades the past, so that's why Arunhand does not like, you know, he was
in Arun always, but when he becomes in Arun, he doesn't have thoughts anymore, I was in
the past, now I'm in Arunhand, but I was in the past before, I actually was, as a person,
that whole thing is affected, why? because your present, any future, sorry, your past and
your future are both present, so either have present towards possibility, present future,
when you have all you have the overdetermined present which is your past, obviously you
don't have always laid in front of you past, present, future, because they will require
an entity, a subject that kind of has an overview of these three things, they're the flowing
in front of your eyes as a slideshow or something, you are part of that, which means you can
only have overdetermined present, that is present, or underdetermined present, that is present,
in other words you can have past that is present, if that's the direction you're looking,
or if you look in direction possibilities, you can have the future that's not yet present
and that's present, so it's a bit more complex, complex, for people who commonly think
it, I don't think about the future, don't go into the past, well no, that's present and
you have no choice about that present, don't regard your past as yours, don't plan
your future as belonging to you, as belonging to you, as arising for you, and there's no
problem, you think the future you want, it might not be, sorry, it will not be, it will
not be for me, and certainly it could have not been, whatever it is, it could have been
not, circumstantial, circumstantial, so if you make any choices, any decisions, commit
any act, based on that which is circumstantial, you can only regard those choices, those
acts as yours, if you forget, or if you don't fully discern, the dependence of your choices
upon this circumstantially, a reason thing, if you remain mindful of the circumstantial nature
of the reason thing upon which you're acting and choosing and deciding, you won't be
only your choice either, but that can be only abandoned present, you can't go in hindsight
and say, ah well because things are not mine, my decisions are not mine as well, well that's
wishful thinking, you have to see that directly, while things are seen as ideas, why you decide
upon that, will not be yours, and then limits the things you can decide, because if you do
see circumstantial, a reason thing as the present, simultaneously present the terminations
of your choices in regard to the circumstantial thing, your choices cannot be infected by
the last version of delusion, it's impossible, because last version of delusion requires the
opposite of circumstantial, it requires the special, the important to the mind, but you see
that it can't be yours, it's not special, it's particularly a reason, but I can't
have the basis of all of it, it's not a reason, and you can't last the words it, and you
certainly can't have a little to the words it, and you won't be the living in regard to it,
it's just not worthy anymore, exactly, and that's what we're going to say, this is not worthy
of delight, of craving, it's not worthy, and you automatically stop doing it, even the
grief that arises through abandoning this, it's in this realm, again, the grief that
happens, it's within that, even that is circumstantial, so you surmount that, you're surmounting
grief as well, because grief is grief only when it's mind, but you stop grieving when it
doesn't pertain to you anymore, it's up when if you are renouncing sensual pleasures
actually bring you strength, you're emulating the right order of thinking, but you also
know no matter what happens, because of your renouncing, because of your not engaging
sensual pleasures, it can't be a good thing, and it's, yeah, that's what we're going
to say, even if a person doesn't develop any wisdom, even if a monk doesn't develop
any wisdom, stays a protusion basically, and lives his whole life, his renunciation
life in tears, because of the pain of his renouncing, it's still better than giving
him the sensuality, because at least he's living the principle, the principle of non-last,
because anyone can say anyone, he won't be enlightened as a result of it, but he certainly
by living the principle, he brings himself closer to enlightenment, obviously, in lives
to come, so it's still better in a long run, but when you have the knowledge, when you
have the knowledge, the sense, the principle that you start living beforehand, which is
why Celia has to come first, that the knowledge discerns, that's it, you discern, you
fully understood, now you don't even have to keep doing it, because you are it, you don't
have to keep emulating the principle, when you become a principle.
Yes, it takes over, yes, that's all, yes.
But always you can spend all emulating you want, now when it points out to you, if you
don't discern it, you won't, you will remain a Batujana, so that's why, there is no
dhamma without Celia, but certainly Celia is not dhamma, but the dhamma is impossible
to have without starting with emulation of the right principle, because dhamma is done
properly renunciation, can very easily be wisdom, with very little instruction, that's why
he sees the, he sees the danger in the slightest fault, doesn't mean he becomes neurotic, obsessed
with anxiety, he means he sees the danger, he starts discerning it, the slightest deviation
from the principle can be an obstacle, massive obstacle later on, it's a big danger,
so I won't deviate, it's like, you know, your ship is on a course, and you might move it
just like, I don't know, 0.01 degree, but then if that course goes long enough, that 0.01
can pose you to miss the whole continent, because eventually it will light up, so if
you literally, if you just start emulating the principle of non-last, non-aversion, non-delusion,
non-indolence, with your body, with your speech, with your mind, with little instruction from
the suitors, maybe more than enough, obviously, you need to emulate the principle harder, with
more discerning, disdestruction, you can emulate it, to a lesser extent, because then the
knowledge can take good quicker, and then obviously you become it, it doesn't mean like
somebody will keep the presets less if they understand, on the contrary, they need to
worry less about the presets when they understand, or if they have more understanding, it will
take good quicker, but for those who don't have, who have lots of faith, and then just
emulate heavily, they really need to take a whole new level of emulation, and then it
will take good, you know, with a little knowledge, they might have, but they need life, without
any knowledge, as I said, you can emulate the principle all you want, they were very
wholesome like, we become very authentic, but you can still remember to do that if nobody
bought you, but today it's kind of impossible, because today nobody emulates the principle
of wholesome living, and those who do, do it as a result of the Buddhist instruction, which
means, those family of the principal are already familiar enough with the Buddhist teaching,
they may not all go into all the details that we just talked about, for example, conceiving
and stuff, but they don't need to, so they emulate, you see, they're familiar with the
principle, and then you start discerning that that is how things actually are, not yours,
not for you, not in your control, not possible to actually be affected by last, not possible
to be affected by a way, not possible to be affected by the illusion, pain that is, and
then all the factors will fall off, it's a slow reprocess, then the one who is emulating
the principle and actively trying to understand it, but to double, yeah, double, but basically
you fight in both fronts, but it's the same relation, it's the same result, and it's
the same relation, yeah, it's just always, if somebody is just emulating the principle,
I'm not trying to understand the principle as well, then you might have people with greater
intellectual capacities, they can understand the principle with actually quite a pure emulation,
they seal it, no, actually develop properly, but they have quite, quite some intelligence
they can discern, and then we'll develop, but until they develop and they seal it properly,
this understanding of that principle will not reach to fulfillment, that's what sort
of buttons, who have seal us efficiently for sort of party, but not our hands yet, they
need to keep practicing nekama, renunciation, restraint, and feel the principle fully
when it's everything, so they just need to stick to the virtuous living, sort of on us,
and they'll become our hands, because they've fully understood the principle, oh, the
ones who didn't stick to the virtuous living, they didn't compromise their understanding,
they just slowed down their progress, like the sort of buttons in the suit as I mentioned,
or in the minerals, you know, the drinking, like lay people as well, he was a sort of
button, but he was drunk and so on, so he wasn't keeping the principles, why, because he
had faculties developed, to such an extent that he could discern the principle at the
very little occasion, where he did keep the priests, where he did live also many, and
he discerned the principle, then, you know, his habit and last took him over, but the
principle was discerned, so at most in several lifetimes he would have brought it to fulfillment,
and there's a thing that says when he's discerning the principle, he's virtuous, so at the
moment of death, when you can't engage in anything circumstantial, he is that principle,
that's why it's often, it's such a prominent kind of role of that in the suit, when somebody
who has the right view, or who is, who's only a mere each, oh well, he might attend,
he doesn't attend the fruits of his understanding, he is slightly attending the moment of death,
because it's where the principle is, not mine, not for me, not in my control, that's what
death is, the manifestation of death, you can abide in that for quite some, you know,
well you can develop it before you actually go through it, that's where the German died
before you die, he didn't mean that in a poetic, inspirational way as well, it's quite a
fact, die before you die, go where the death is, and abandon it yourself before it hits
you, go where the death is, yes, go where the death is, because death is everything opposite
of my life, death is the ultimate not yours, you can think, you own death, you can think
you're ready for death, only arrogance is ready for death, because there's no, no holding
of any form of life, any form of Baba, any form of meaning, but for Patugina, death always
comes from the opposite way you're looking at, it always comes from behind, from behind
your attention, from underneath you feel, which means you can never be prepared for death,
that's Patugina, that's so explainable, so explainable you can, but you will still experience
some anguish in regard to it, because well, because you have left work, I'm done, you
can just do the principle, but you haven't been emulating it sufficiently, for it permeate
everything and make all of the factors evaporate in this day, where's your boy, good sleep,
so perfectly emulating all some living, see the danger in the slightest fault, with the
instruction that you already have, with the decircumnication that you already have, you
will probably be the tenth of it, he will be enough, but it needs to be done, it needs
to be stuck to and maintained, for our long well that that can be only known in hindsight,
Once you get it, once you once, once the mind knows that it knows, then you can say, okay, well,
took me only a four-night.
It took me only seven years.
It took me only seventeen years.
In a long scheme of things, it's nothing.
Took me only this like that.
Because investigation of Thomas investigation is cannot be very painful.
Yeah, trying to think, thinking about these things too.
Well, it's painful in the beginning, because you don't really know what to think about,
and how to think about, so then it requires, once you know, then you will be able to tune in your
effort. So you won't be ashamed. You won't be painful. Just thinking about them, I see,
like, you think I have to think about these things. You can say that, but basically it's more
accurate. You have to discern these things within what has already risen, the demos they have
already risen. You just need to change the way of looking at what's already right in front of
you all the time, and you're not just about it. You're not fabricating anything new,
you're just discerning within what's already there. And that's actually quite effortless.
Because really, you're renunciation, you're just keeping the precepts.
Yeah, and we're not in there. Yeah, can you walk some pain?
Looking up to your thoughts, probably, keeping the precepts. Yeah.
That's, yeah, they can walk pain, of course. But even that, you know, all the pain in the
beginning, the same as giving up any habits, central habits in particular. Because the pain in
the beginning, but then after what it doesn't, it evolves the pain in the beginning because you're
just too dependent on, you know, the non-renunciation. But if you stick with renunciation,
then you recognize what actually, you know, this is the natural state of things which,
it's a sensuality that requires the effort, not other way around.
The renunciation has a required effort. It requires the effort when you will mind
distal center upon the sensuality. And saying no to it requires the effort when you start discerning,
that that is the, that is the correct order. Sensuality is circumstantial,
arisen on the basis of non-sensuality. Thus, it's sensuality that requires effort.
So by not engaging in sensuality, you're effortless. No burden, no pressure.
And then your mind just won't go to sensuality because that's, that which needs effort,
not the current state. But that wouldn't have happened if you haven't been emulating the current state
beforehand. If you haven't been emulating the non-sensuality beforehand.
I thought it delighting the renunciation. No, it's secluded. It's effortless. You have to do that.
And that's just without all the other more important methods of not exposing yourself to danger and
your mind and everything else. You're freedom. And peace to all of you.