So I have a few suitors that I would like to go through and this theme is really about
sense of restraint and the Buddha gave a short teaching to Bahia, he gave a short teaching
to Malonkia Buddha, the same, the same verse. So I'll just read out Janabhira's translation
of this. Okay, then by here you should train, train thus, in the scene there shall be just
the scene, in the herd, there shall be just the herd, in a sense there shall be just
the sense, in the cognize there shall be just the cognize, thus by here should you train
yourself. When by here for you in the scene there shall be just the scene, the herd,
just the sense, just the cognize, then you will not be that by which, when you shall not
be that by which, then you shall not be in that place, when you shall not be in that place,
then you will be, you will neither be here nor yonder, nor between the two, just this
is the ending of suffering. So when he says you will not be that by which, you will not
be in that place, and you will not be here, or yonder, or between the two. So I think
here yonder and between the two, what is that, you know, here is the sense basis. Yes,
yeah, yeah. You will need to be your sense basis. Well, you neither, your self will neither
be taken to be your sense basis, or sense objects, or both, or neither, whichever you
think, something you can through denial of things, you can establish your sense of self.
So you can deny, like, there is here, there is yonder, and in between the two, would
stand basically for both here and yonder, and neither here nor yonder. The mental attitude
in regard to the experience of the whole of here and yonder, because the self can always
kind of, even through denial of it, can reestablish itself as not that, but implying I am something
else. Although there isn't anything else to be found simply through that denial, negation
of something, you give enough space for the notion of self to remain. So in that sense,
basically, when in seeing that is just the scene, no amount of movement, so to speak, of
the mind in regard to the high and the sights in the experience of the scene, no amount of
the movement, whether it's in it, a parchment, both in it or a parchment, whether it's
mind, whether it's for me, whether it's this, none of that will induce the sense of self.
When in seeing, there is just the scene, or in other words, when the scene is not appropriate,
and the senses that are seen are not appropriate. When both, the senses in that which is being
seen are not appropriate. Then, in the scene, there is just the scene. So when you're neither
appropriating it, and appropriation is basically established either through indulging it or
running away from it, indulging it or denying it, either way, you basically relate to it.
So to speak, and that relation is a form of appropriation. So that's why he doesn't,
he doesn't either indulge the sights, nor does he fear them or run away from them. The
scene is just a scene. There is no need to do anything in regard to it, for and haven't.
Because you have a pleasing sight or a displeasing sight.
Exactly. And so he. Pleasing sight is just a pleasing sight. For somebody who is not
developed in regard to pleasing sight, pleasing sight would be inducing last in their mind.
The last is not in the pleasing sight. That's what the Buddha said. That's one other
of Nianavira's translation, in the back of the book, saying that the target that perceives
beautiful objects in the world. He still sees, oh, this is beautiful, this is agreeable,
this is nice. But he, his thoughts do not have desire and lust in regard to those things.
But it's when people can't see that, can't see that the nature of desire and lust
pertains to the mind, it's not in the objects, then they deny the objects. They try to overcome
the desire and lust through sheer denial of objects. And that's the suit that the similar
of the, the bait in Majimonika, where, sure, one day, her eats Mara's bait, I enjoy the
sense of scale. And then, and then because of that, Mara does with them what he wants.
Then another group of their sees that, sees that the hunter controls this there, does
what he wants, because they're eating their traps and wearing it. Then they think, okay,
like in, in, in, in, completely similar range to the big ones, and the big ones would
see, okay, so indulgence of the sense of objects leads to, like, us being slaves to Mara.
So then, they deny the entire sense of fear. And in that suit that says the deer, then
shuns the bait completely, forgetting that they do depend on it to some extent. They
shun it, they go up in the mountains, but then sooner or later, the food, the water runs
out in the mountains, and they have to come back to that bait. And because they were never
developed in regard to the bait in the first place, they end up eating it, carelessly,
like the first deer here. And again, in the end, Mara does with them what he wants. It's
exactly like the indulgence and denial results in the same, results in you not being, not
understanding the nature of the bait and being controlled because of that. So the point
is that the deer would recognize that, if he would recognize the nature of the indulgence,
the nature of denial, and then it would stay within the domain of bait, because it depends
on a certain extent to it, it depends on the food, but it would not eat carelessly. And
that's the key. It could eat carefully, it would be careful of the bait. So he wouldn't
deny everything, he wouldn't throw away the baby with the bathwater, it would basically
start distinguishing. And that's a very, well, it's not necessarily subtle, it reminds
of getting used to it, but for most people, it's a very subtle distinction because people
either say yes or no completely. And then obviously, you have to start with restraint first,
restraint in regard to things that are not necessary, such as sexual integrals, things
based on excessive lust, things based on anger and so on, but then eating food is necessary.
But you can do it lustfully, you can do it because of craving, or you can do it mindfully.
But people who don't know, who can't distinguish that the lust is on them, not on the food,
then they start denying food, they try going food, and this is exactly what's happening,
a setisism, self-mortification, then that will sooner or later, that won't be enough.
Then they start denying more, then it can go as far as denying breeding, denying air, denying
anything. And the Buddha tried that and he said, no, this is not the way. Now that doesn't
mean that, okay, so now you should go back and eat everything unwarily again and be completely
unrestrained, that's as serious as it can be. But the Buddha was quite clear how one should
then practice. So you develop the virtue first, you develop the strain, you stop doing all
some things that are completely unnecessary and they have like inexcusable. But then other
things, you can't help by encountering agreeable sights, agreeable sounds. So if you're just
blaming sights and sounds, well the Buddha again said, you won't be different than a blind
or a deaf man. If you think that the domain of sight, the medicine is a problem, it's
not. His desire and lust in regard to it. So instead of being the second ear that runs
to the mountain in fear of the whole domain, no, you recognize that, so you stay within
it. Practice restraint to the extent necessary. But then for the rest, you start developing
mind from a sin regard to it. That means eating the food carefully, not being careless in
regard to the bait. Because that's what the bait is, carelessness. That's what gives
rise to lust, to aversion, to delusion. It's not the actual food, it's not the actual
sense objects. No matter how agreeable they are. What was the other quote you just said?
They don't want to do that out of our video. Well they didn't know, because it's exactly
what I'm saying. Just before that, what you're saying now, because to shun the bait seems
to me, it's a very, well it's a very, some sort of evil will be. Oh yeah, of course.
You're pushing away. Yeah. It's aversion. Your aversion. Yeah. You're averse towards
that. Out of fear. Because you fear that agreeable sight sounds, melt taste, that will induce
lust, because you absolutely don't know, nor equals to prevent it, because you don't
understand it. But do it. So the only way that you know how to get
pushed things away is to be able to, well, you push away pleasing things, and then you bring
the things that displease you closer. So then that becomes that which pleases you. So
end up just acting in the same way, like the first herd. Because that other herd, they
see what the hunter's about, they see what the bait's about, and they've overcome it.
He's kind of bewildered by the bait. They stay there, but they don't need the bait, so
he can't see them, because they're never caught on the hooks. But the food is eaten around
the bait. But is there really a bait with the hunter
really exists in illusion? Yes, it's much. That is the case. That's the situation you're
born in. The hunt, the ground for hunting you in there. Oh yeah, that's all the gosh
people can deny. It's all sorts of views and stuff, which is of course, that's why the
acknowledgement of those things has to come first. But when we are talking about, we assume
that we agree on that. So it's a different topic now. We agree that there is such thing
as being controlled by the senses and being a victim to it. So this is another sutra from
Saint Utanikaya, and chapter 35 verse 94. It's called untamed or unguarded. So the Buddha
is speaking, because these six bases for contact, if untamed, unguarded, unprotected, unrestrained,
unbringers of suffering. Just six because of the basis for contact, where one unrestrained
meets with suffering, those who know how to restrain them, well uncorupted, with faith
their partner. Having seen forms at delight the mind and having seen those that give no
delight to spell the path of lust towards the delightful and do not soil the mind by thinking
the other is displeasing to me. So they have been seeing the delightful. It doesn't say
run away from delightful. Cover your eyes from delightful. It says, dispel the lust in
regard to delightful. Having seen a non-delightful, don't end up thinking about how non-delight
I don't end up developing a version in regard to non-delightful, mental version, but it
doesn't say run away from non-delightful, because that is the way out. That means you're
blaming non-delightful and you're blaming the lightful for your lust and for your
lust. You're not seeing it where it is, but not seeing it where it is you cannot possibly
have rooted. Having heard sounds both pleasant and noisy, do not be enthralled by pleasant
sound to spell the cause of hate towards the noise, do not soil the mind by thinking
this one is displeasing to me. Having smelt a fragrant delightful scent and having smelt
a putrid stench, to spell a virgin towards the stench and do not yield to desire for
the lovely. Having enjoyed a sweet delicious taste and having sometimes tasted what is
bitter, do not greedily enjoy the sweet taste, do not feel a version towards the bitter.
So if you can't be clearer than that, yet many people blame the taste. Do not greedily
enjoy the sweet taste. Don't be greed in regard to, it doesn't mean don't ever eat
sweet, agreeable taste. No, if you're generally equanimous in regard to the taste, it doesn't
matter if it's agreeable or disagreeable. It means if you're generally equanimous you
won't be running away from agreeable cause you fear that it will induce the last. No,
equanimity is basically absence of last to understanding. So removing of greed in regard
to the agreeable, in regard to delicious, having enjoyed delicious sweet taste. So you
can even enjoy it in a way without being greedy about it. Why? Cause it's agreeable, that's
a form of enjoyment. And that's just the fact. The sense enjoys it. You don't necessarily
enjoy it. And that's obvious that many people don't enjoy it because they fear it. And
that's a mistake. So you let the sense enjoy it, why? Because you have to eat. But you
don't do it unwarily, you don't do it carelessly because that will then induce greed in your
mind. And then you will be appropriate in sense that enjoys it. But you can't enjoy
the taste even if you want to. You always pertains to the like that physical sense, presence
of the matter that is your tongue. So the fact that you think that you can enjoy it and
then you deny it through running away, through practicing extreme asceticism, through not
eating because you fear the taste basically. You are fully appropriating your sense base
and then protecting it because you can't let go of it. The hunt is chasing you. You've
been chased. You're running away. You can't sort of... Well, no, yeah. I mean, in the sense
you can't run away because you're holding onto the bait. Yeah, you're not eating it because
you're fearing it, but you're holding onto it. Which is amounts to the same thing. You're
hooked by the bait one way or the other. Are they treating it carelessly or through holding
it tightly out of fear? We're saying as well. And you can never see that actually you can't
even enjoy the taste even if you want to. The sense will enjoy the taste for as long as
you deny it. For as long as you deny agreeable taste. So you know for fact that you're restrained.
You know for fact that you eat once a day. You know for fact that you're not seeking out
for a pleasant taste. And then you encounter a pleasant taste. And feeling that is just
basically completely like a wisdom. Running away from it, it's even further like a wisdom.
Trying to prevent it, trying to not feel it with your tongue or whatever. It's just playing
ridiculous. Because those objects of the senses are for the senses in their domain. It's
their business kind of. Exactly. So whatever they get. The file animals, they have
feeding grounds. It's not. I mean, you will be affected by it when you appropriate that
feeding ground, when you appropriate that animal the feeding. When you are, when your mind
is inseparable from your tongue, when your tongue is appropriated, when your eyes are appropriated,
you will be well, you will be affected by what you see, what you taste and so on. And running
away from it, it's just another form of being affected by it.
Because no matter what comes into the eye, so to speak, where would you see the eyes?
Yes. So then in the scene, there is a scene and then you will not be dead by which. And
that's what it means. Being dead by which in another sutra, when another says, it's
the eye, eye, as the organ makes you dead by which you are the conceiver. You are the
one who sees the things, thus you end up conceiving them as mine. So because you just automatically
appropriated the sense-basis, because they don't appear as objects. They are always
negative in regard to it, which means they are even harder to see. They have to be seen
as a negative phenomenon. And because of them, most people don't see it. And because of
that, because of their appropriation of their sense-basis, in this case, let's say,
eyes, they are the seer of the eye objects, because they just descended down into the eye.
They took them. So now what I see means I see that. What tongue-tastes aren't tasting
that. And that's what they mean, they're being dead by which. But if seen, there is just
a scene in taste, there is just a taste. They will not be dead by which. But they're not
dead by which. They don't appropriate the sense organs. Well, they will not be in the
objects. Whether they are not properly in the sense organs, nor are they found in the
objects, they will not be here, nor yonder, nor between the two. No behind in front.
No behind in front, above, left or right. They will simply not be room for the sense
of self. Because sense of self can authorize without the basis, which is appropriation regarding
things as mine. But that's completely prevented, through understanding that it's impossible
to be there in the first place. You can't all those things in the first place. So you
prevent the appropriation means there is no room for sense of self. You don't even think,
oh, now I have to practice the non-self. Not that experience or non-appropriation is the
experience of non-self.
You take like there's the sum of those animals and the senses as the animals. So the dog
is eating its food. But if you, you can never have that food that the dog is eating because
you're not, you're not the dog. You're not the dog, yeah. So even if you thought you were
holding onto the dog and thinking that you are eating this food, whatever it is, that's,
you can't get any of that stuff. So you're going to be suffering constantly.
Well, think of it like this basically. The only way for you to eat the food is for tongue,
mouth, digestive organ to engage with the food. And all of those things, if you look at
them independently, so to speak, are independent of you. Your mouth, your organ, it's not in your
control. Those things have a reason and they correspond, well, they have objects that
correspond to it, they engage with it. So not recognizing the impermanence of the sense
basis, for example, you're appropriately automatic.
Yeah, the similar of the animals doesn't quite work in this sense because you can always
well, nothing stops you from eating dog food. The thing is, the five animals, but basically
you know the domains because of them. You can't, you can't have, you cannot have relationship
with sight without the eyes, which means basically all you can have relationship with, it is,
all you can have relationship with is eyes seeing things. You can't access sights unless
I see them first. So you can't even have the idea, you can't even mentally think about
sights without applying eyes. But if you don't appropriate your eye, then your eye is going
to just look at it. It's going to be on your strength.
Exactly, that's what people think, exactly. So they think, oh, so I must let go of my eyes,
which means, but no, you're still, you are responsible for your strength. So once you
start restraining and the precepts are quite clear, where the five, where the eight, where
the ten, no matter how many, they are quite clear. And that's what you decide beforehand.
And then you start seeing the negative phenomenon of the eye, eye object. Sorry, eye base, eye
bases, the sense bases of the eyes. And then you recognize, okay, so it's still within
that strength. So if you were now to make the jump from non-appropriation of the eye to
a non-restraint of the eye, that would have to be a conscious jump. That can't happen
by accident. Why? Because eyes stopped engaging in an awesome, fully, un-awesome thing through
setting up the seal at first. So now you can genuinely let go of the eyes. Why? Because
they won't go into that awesome. Because they used to go into an awesome, only because
you were sending them there. That's why the Buddha said you can't possibly engage in sensuality
without having fully established sensual perceptions. And for that, you're fully responsible. And
that cannot be done without appropriation of the eyes. So quite the opposite from what
people believe, genuinely letting go, genuinely not appropriating the eye base, fully prevents
even a possibility of sensual engagement. Because that is intentional, once the eyes have
been taken as mine, then you relish the pleasure that you fully feel you can access. And that's
the whole point of sensuality. That's the whole nature of it. You feel you are in touch
with your disagreeable objects, either through consuming them through your mouth, through
your eyes, through your nose, through grasping them with your hands. It's exactly what sensuality
is consumption. And you can only assume that you can consume things when you have appropriated
the bases. There are the only ones that can access them. But even then, all you are consuming
that you are consuming are the sense bases that then, on their own external kind of level,
correspond to these sensuality and interact with them. So you can never actually access the
sights. All you can have is, all you can see, so to speak, is eye-seeing things.
Exactly. So all you can have is your sense base being affected by these things, but you
can't access those things. So you can't actually taste the food. You can taste your tongue
tasting the food. You can't touch things. You can experience your body being touched
by things or your body touching things. In other words, it's always indirect. You can
never bypass the body as a sense of touch or bypass the tongue and go straight to the
sense objects. Which means, the sense objects are kind of always determined by your sense
base. Because if your eyes are not seeing certain colors, that's it. You can't even
consume those colors. You can't even consume. You're only like in some, like, maybe external
communication, I get the idea. You're seeing things differently, but for you, that is what
you see. That is the real thing. Which means you can only access sensors that are being
affected by external objects, by external magic. And that recognition already approves any
desire you can have for central engagements with those external objects, by, because
they're inaccessible. No matter how hard you press, how hard you squeeze, how hard you
taste, how hard you look, or you know, you're fully understood. You can't doubt it anymore.
That all you're seeing is your eye seeing. All you're tasting is your tongue tasting. All
you're touching is your body touching. So it's always an indirect. An indirect man. Like
you can't turn away, turn back and look at the things. The only way you can see them
is by having a mirror in front of him. That's your way of looking back. And in this
simulate, looking back is basically the sense objects. There are there in the world, inaccessible.
The only way to access them is when they're reflected upon the sense base. When they engage,
they're corresponding engagement with the sense base. Then you see it. How it corresponded
to it. But it still doesn't mean you're actually accessing the matter of the sense objects,
impossible. They will require you to come out of all of your sense bases and it goes straight
to the matter. But that is inconceivable. Because even that thought is based on a complete
experience of sense bases, even in the imaginary basic, even in the imagination. In a 7 out of
6 animals. 5. A 6 out of 5. Comment what they are, crocodile. Crocodile monkey, yeah.
It's 5 animals and then the mind base their meat in the mind. Like the 5 senses in the
mind. Because it's the monkey. He says the monkey mind. I don't know. They pull to their
own feeding grounds and the thing is he's got a rope tied. He ties the rope in the middle
and then they just pull. I know that was ever the strongest. That's where everyone
has got it. Because they're tied to the same meal. So everyone goes with the crocodile
or whatever. And then he doesn't just tie it in the middle. He tied it to a post and
that's discernment. That's mindfulness. And then they get tied. They stop pulling
it. So they can't actually go there because they tie it. See that similarly. You don't
tie it in the middle together because then the strongest will pull. That's basically
when people use a certain sense to overcome other senses. See unpleasant sights sound
abothering you. But then your mind just goes start thinking about a pleasant taste.
You're bothered by unpleasant touch, unpleasant taste. But then you like the beautiful
instance and then you're enjoying the pleasant smell and your mind comes down because of that.
Or sometimes admiring the beautiful view as a form of meditation. Which is as
mistaken as it can be. Because that's exactly it. Ah, this sense seems calmer than
the others. So you use that sense to overcome the others. But in that sense,
when that sense changes, you will be pulled and all the other senses will go for it.
Because this is the strongest among them. So I don't really recommend that way.
That's why you must not use any sense as a basis for a meditation because that's
not meditation. And the Buddha did say that actually. Like a jackal waiting for
a mouse or an owl waiting for a prey, praying upon a fish. Like waiting hunting,
hunting, waiting, grabbing the moment, waiting, waiting, waiting. So the misguided person
overmeditates, undermeditates, mismeditates, premeditates, but he doesn't
meditate. And basically, when they miss the point of meditation, they end up
meditating with the mind revolving on centrality. And revolving on centrality means
revolving around dependence on a sense, for pleasure, for pain, for peace.
Yes, there was nothing pleasing in a sight, nothing pleasing in a smell,
no taste, no sight. It's a pleasing sight. But there is no greed for the pleasure
of that sight. It's just a pleasing sight. But if there's no pleasing,
but there's a, the only way you can get pleasure is to say your body.
Right, right, right. Then you would go comfort. You would go to the physical comfort.
There's no physical comfort that you go fences about the sight, or even just
going to your imagination. It's kind of a reproduction of the other senses in
their peaceful state, in the state of not being gained by their hunger or
whatever else. But it's again, revolves around them.
So, everyone's got to, well, suppose everyone's going climb to certain
senses. Yeah, exactly. From the front of each other, or some people have issues
with food restraints and so on. Or music, you have to listen to it.
Oh, yeah, that's another thing that people listen to music as a form of meditation.
That's exactly what I was describing here. It's, it's after, after the
limous guide. When touched by a pleasant contact,
and do not be enthralled, do not tremble when touched by paint.
Look evenly on both the pleasant and the painful, not drawn or repiled by
anything. To me, that touch is quite a, it's very inside, you know,
it's so close. It's quite a, to be able to look evenly on both
pleasant and painful touch.
Not have your mind swayed by it, by the prospect of comfort,
by the possibility of discomfort, fanophysical kind.
Being swayed means not, not, not, not craving it.
And not running away from it. Why? Because it wasn't
able to begin with. Why are you running away from it?
Why are you trying to avoid it? You trying to avoid it means basically
you're still regarding it as you are. The sense basis,
you're trying to avoid things that correspond to your sense base.
So you're trying to avoid comfort or discomfort depending on your view.
But you will only be committed to avoiding it because you fool
the appropriate in this body. Instead of letting go of the body,
relinquishing any notion of appropriation,
then sometimes comfort, sometimes discomfort.
The mind doesn't, it doesn't get swayed, doesn't get affected.
Because as you can feel your whole body, your whole body is touched.
So it's not appropriate, you know.
See, that's the thing, you can't run away from that.
Yeah, you can't.
That's why mindfulness in the body plays such a fundamental.
Because of that, and because all the other senses are basically bodily,
so eluded, contained in this very body.
So if you stop appropriating the body as a sense base in its entirety,
there's a sixth sense base, then you won't be appropriating
sight, sense, notay, stutters, or thoughts and energies.
You won't be appropriating anything physically or mentally.
And if you're not appropriated, you don't run away from it.
Because disagreeable was not yours to begin with.
And even if there is any response to agreeable,
it's a bodily response.
It's a response of the sense base that you don't appropriate,
which means it's only a limited response.
It can never be a response with lust,
a response with aversion, a response with delusion,
because they're all intentional responses, responses for which
you and your misappropriation of things was responsible for.
You continue further the same, Sutta.
When common people have proliferated perception,
to see even proliferate, they become engaged.
Having dispelled every mind state bound to the home life,
one travels on the road of renunciation.
When the mind is lust, well developed in six, these six phases.
If touched, one's mind never flutters anyway,
having vanquished both lust and hate,
because go to the far shore beyond birth and death.
So this is another suit of mine after its 95th millennium.
A great monk was a great name.
And he goes to quite old apparently, at the stage in the...
I think I remember him from my journey, he was a Sutta fan.
Yeah, he was a Lenin.
No, he was a Lenin.
There was a Sutta fan, he was asking whether I'll come so that my mind can sometimes also be affected
by I'm also a steady forget about that mind, so on.
Oh yeah, there, also.
But maybe there was a different one than him, you know.
I don't know if it was a dip, yeah, but the same name.
The same name, yeah.
So he asked the Buddha for a short.
You might say that you might, a short discourse or a short message.
So you might dwell alone withdrawn, diligent, ardent, and resolute.
So the Buddha goes on to say, questions.
What do you think Melunkiya Buddha?
Do you have any desire, lust or affection for those forms cognizable by the eye that you have not seen or never saw before?
That you do not see and would not think might be seen.
Yes.
Do you have any desire, lust or affection for those touches cognizable by the body that you haven't, have not touched you and never been touched by before?
And you do not touch now and would not touch you.
Is this no veneration?
It's impossible to have lust for things that have never, for sites that have never been seen.
They will never be seen.
You can't possibly imagine them.
Because why? Because they have never been seen.
So you can't have lust for that, for that which has an arisen.
You can't have lust for that which has not left an imprint on a sense space.
So to speak, figuratively speaking doesn't actually have an imprint, but you can't have lust for that.
It's inconceivable.
And it's similar what I was saying before.
So you recognize that.
Then if you see that basically it's impossible to lust or have aversion towards site that has never been seen, never will be seen.
You can't even imagine seeing.
Then you recognize that sites that you did see, that you will see are completely circumstantial.
They are far more inferior to all of the things that you haven't seen.
What? Because they were seen.
Which means it's always like things that are seen always arise on a basis of great things that haven't been seen.
So then you realize that even your lust is completely gratuitous and unnecessary and pathetic.
Because you're lasting this sight that was completely random and circumstantial and easily could have not been.
There's a big change.
So if you recognize that in whatever you're experiencing that this could have not been, it is but could have not been.
And the fact that it could have not been precedes the fact that it is.
It means it's completely circumstantial thus it was never for me. It could have never been for me.
And it certainly never be for me.
Because that being for me, the mind, it's already like makes it special, it gives it priority.
It makes it more important.
But if something is circumstantial, it could have not been between it and it won't be.
Something else will come its place. And then when that does, that could have also not been.
And you can't have lust for things that have never been.
Thus, when you do have lust for things that are, that's just on top of that completely gratuitous on top of that circumstantial arising.
So just through recognizing that you can't have lust for things that have never reason, you can actually bang on lust for things that have.
By seeing the circumstantial nature, which is nothing other than saying by seeing a reason things as a permanent.
And if permanent means impossible to home, means basically subject to cessation, subject to cessation.
Doesn't mean you actually witnessing the cessation.
You just recognize it. This is circumstantial, which means you have no idea where it came from.
And because of that, it will cease.
Even if you keep witnessing it for the rest of your life, it still remains permanent.
That covers everything that might be seen.
It covers all the possibilities as well, exactly.
Because whatever might be seen, it's going to be seen on a circumstantial basis.
And as a danger, if you don't cover it, if you don't know that, the danger is...
You'll have things unincluded basically in this direction, yeah?
It's like a couple, I say, a man and a woman get together, they love each other.
Infatuated with each other.
But he's seen her, but he might see someone else tomorrow.
There might be even more desire.
And he can't stop that from happening.
He can shout off his eyes, but then...
Yeah, because you never practice restraint. You got the things he sees, things he touches, things he desires.
And then he loses interest in his wife.
Exactly. He just moves on to another.
But if he were to see that even the first one was completely circumstantial,
he would have... well, he would have been able to control his desire, if not completely abandoning.
There's a reason for abandoning.
But what I'm saying is that even a lay person, not necessarily a man who is practicing for our hardship,
a lay person who is in union with the opposite sex, can use this reflection to remain faithful,
to remain restrained, to remain but to the other wisdom.
There's that sort of a couple, the man and woman, came to the Buddha.
And they asked him how to...
I think they might both have the right view.
And the Buddha...
How do you...
Well, I'm not sure if it was that sort of how to really go together, but he was basically sort of a...
He says, oh, yeah, they practice like perfect, they're perfectly faithful to each other.
He's like, not just, they've never...
Like, the husband says, not just that he never cheated on the wife,
but he also never, never like verbally was unfaithful to her.
And it was never even unfaithful to her, even in his mind.
And she says the same.
It doesn't mean that he never saw a pretty woman,
nor that she never seen a more handsome man.
It seems to mean that they recognized, like, the intentional aspect of the desire of the choice,
and they clearly respected each other, then they just...
Okay, there was a more pleasing sight, but more pleasing sight does not mean last is there.
Last is there when you're careless in regard to the more pleasing sight,
and they were never careless.
Thus, they were never unfaithful to each other.
And they would have praised it, that's exactly how somebody who wants to be a union should live.
And you can see that's already quite a...
quite a good degree of wisdom that most people today, an average person,
just be too conceivable for them.
Why?
Because what you see, you just go for it.
And then even though a lot of union marriage just remains utterly random,
and circumstantial based on just things.
And then, yeah, people divorced, people end up hating each other,
because why?
Just follow the senses, then and now either aging will go bold with it,
or find something better, but then the whole kind of notion of marriage and commitment
is sort of now basically hindering it.
So they feel enslaved by their own choices, basically.
And they only have themselves to blame.
Oh, nothing.
Yep.
So in this suit, again, he goes into that...
You can see in the shot, you can just see, he gives you that short teaching.
And then Melanchio put, he says,
I understand in detail, when it was so the meaning of what was stated by the blessed one.
And then he gives, he says, this verse.
And the Buddha agrees with him, good, good, Melanchio put it,
it is good that you understand in detail the meaning of what was stated by me in brief.
And I'll just read down to you.
When seeing a sight, mindfulness becomes confused.
If attention is focused on the pleasant aspect,
experiencing it with the mind for the desire,
one remains assuming to cling to it.
Many feelings grow arising from sight.
So again, back to the beginning of the verse,
so it says quite clearly,
that wrongly attending to the pleasant sight,
desire and last and assumption grows in regard to it,
not just by merely having a pleasant sight,
which means pleasant sight or a pleasant sight was never the problem.
It's not the problem.
It's you don't know, not knowing how to attend to it,
you end up being confused.
Being confused, you end up assuming,
the whole desire, the whole, the whole basically thing
ends up proliferating and growing more and more.
And then, yeah, just the feelings grow.
Well, exactly, yeah.
Upon giving into pleasure,
you might sometimes experience more pain.
Then by trying to run away from that pain,
you discovered some new pleasure.
And there was all based on the initial confusion
in regard to pleasant sight,
which you, like, ignorantly,
crave for and went for.
Desired for, delighted in, lasted after.
Because of that, you just created basis for now,
all sorts of pleasant and pleasant neutral.
And giving into that, you create more basis for pleasantness,
for pleasantness. So again, feelings grow.
They're just cutting it off right there, and it doesn't.
Not even.
Well, you can take anything,
no matter how proliferated it is,
you can actually uprooted in its entirety
if you see the nature of craving towards pleasure.
Of nature, nature of avoiding.
Having aversion towards this pleasure.
The nature of indolence towards
neither pleasure nor this pleasure.
By understanding the nature of it,
then that just pertains,
permits the whole, no matter how proliferated the picture is.
Then basically, you kill the roots.
You kill the proliferating life.
There was being fed by ignorance.
You try it up, and then it's like a palm stump.
So the proliferated tree branches remain petrified.
They don't spread anymore.
Ignorance doesn't feel it.
So now it's just dried up habits of certain kind.
The ones they were completely dependent upon
sensuality fall off.
But some of it remains
until the aggregates break apart completely.
For another end.
Maybe you want some of the pure, obviously,
one feelings to grow is like in the pleasure
to get more, more.
Oh, yeah. Well, that's right.
That's why sometimes people like
to expose themselves to the risk of this pleasure,
because it makes them pleasurably regret it.
So within a pleasant, non-threatening situation,
you kind of want to spice it up so to speak.
And then you make yourself kind of liable to some pain as well.
But it's all within the pleasurable image
that you've already fully engaged with.
Like, you know, overcoming challenges and stuff.
You can only engage that on the basis of pleasure.
If the whole thing suddenly turns
and then the whole thing becomes light-threatening.
Oh, now it's serious.
And then you stop engaging in the same way.
But yeah, that's what people, you know,
go after frame, for example.
Even go after risk that, you know,
maybe they'll experience this pleasure.
But it's all within the image of pleasure
that they've initially given to you.
And then proliferated.
And then same, initially given into a version
that you go to this pleasure,
even if you study experiencing pleasure on top of it,
you won't be appreciating it,
because, you know, the mind is upset or whatever else.
So feeling good on top of each other.
But if you stop,
establish mindfulness,
all you can say, a feeling is there.
It doesn't matter.
It doesn't matter if it's the top of the proliferated tree
or the bottom. It doesn't matter.
A feeling has a reason,
which means every feeling,
no matter how many of them have grown,
how many of them have spread proliferated,
goal established,
every feeling carries an nature feeling,
which means in regard to every feeling,
you can practice abandoning of craving.
But they all carry the principle,
the universe of principle,
which principles lead some further.
So for me, you don't have to chase all of these proliferated feelings
as that's impossible.
Now, they're trying to train all these branches
that are constantly growing.
You can't possibly keep up.
Instead, just kill the roots,
approach it,
remove the food from the ground
and the roots are sucking onto it.
That's it.
They die.
You don't have to worry about the branches spreading anymore.
You know for sure, they won't.
Even if you don't know where exactly they have proliferated,
you got so big,
no, you know that you've killed the roots,
one way or the other,
and the trees are being fed proliferation stuff.
Yeah, one task.
Yes.
As opposed to trying to manage,
contain direct,
no, fashion,
the branches.
Yeah, managing.
It's just for management.
You know, many feelings grow,
arising from sight.
The mind is damaged by coldness and cruelty,
heaping up suffering like this.
You said to be far from the barner.
When hearing a sound,
mindfulness becomes confused,
if attention is focused on the pleasant aspect,
experiencing with the mind full of desire
when it mains a sumitur.
Many feelings grow,
arising from sounds.
The mind is damaged by covetousness and cruelty.
Keeping up suffering like this,
you said to be far from the barner.
When it's smelling a smell,
when it's saving a taste,
when touching a touch,
when knowing a mental phenomenon,
it continues,
the mind is damaged
and it's far from the barner.
Then it goes on to say,
seeing a sight with mindfulness,
there is no desire for sight.
The experiencing with the mind full of desire,
one doesn't remain assuming to it.
As it is for someone who lives mindfully,
when repeatedly seeing a sight,
feeling is ended,
not added to.
Reducing suffering like this,
you said to be in the presence of the barner.
To this even, by making mindfully in regard to pleasant sight,
mindfully in regard to unpleasant sight,
so he neither develops lust nor aversion.
Mindfully in regard to neutral,
neither agreeable nor disagreeable sight.
He doesn't develop indolence,
he doesn't develop ignorance,
he doesn't develop delusion.
Which means all of those feelings
arise simultaneously with that.
He understands as they arise,
so he doesn't add to them.
Basically adding to them means
he doesn't induce craving in regard to them.
That's what means ending of the feeling
as it has arisen.
Because when you crave for feeling obviously,
you go further and then you experience
another feeling when it can't do that,
and then another feeling when it can't do that.
There's no piling up,
so to speak, but increasing.
But if you're mindfully in regard to sight,
the feeling that has arisen,
that's it. You see it as impermanent.
By seeing it as impermanent,
why? Because you're mindfully in regard to sight,
there won't be any craving
in regard to that feeling,
because craving requires notion of permanence.
Be it craving for pleasure
or craving for avoiding of pain,
either way.
So by removing the craving,
you stop assuming it.
There's no pedana.
And touching a touch with mindfulness.
There's no desire for touches.
You're experiencing with the mind,
fear of desire one doesn't remain assuming to it.
As it is for someone who lives mindfully,
when repeatedly touching a touch,
feeling is ended,
not added to.
Reducing suffering like this,
is said to be in the presence of nirvana.
That's what I read there one night,
because there's a difference between touch and feeling.
Yeah, absolutely.
You recognize it.
Oh, I feel something in my back.
No, you're touching something in your back.
What is sensation in my knees?
Yeah, that sensation is perception of the touch.
It's not a feeling.
People think sensations are feelings,
sensations are perceptions.
But is that repeatedly practicing mindfulness
in regards to it?
It approaches.
Yeah, feelings.
Reducing suffering like this.
Reducing it.
Because suffering can arise only in the basis of craving.
Encoding can arise only in the basis of ignorance in regard to feelings.
And in the ignorance in regard to feelings,
can arise only in the basis of non-mindfully attending to pleasure,
non-mindfully attending to pain.
Then you're touched by the feeling.
When you're touched by the feeling,
you crave in regard to it.
So by mindfully attending to what's seen,
what's heard, what's taste,
what's touched, what's thought.
But mindful attending to it repetitively
the desire and lust in regard to diminishes,
aversion diminishes,
which means that feelings are not entertained,
not engaged, not crave for.
But each site and so on is either agreeable, disagreeable.
Or neither agreeable nor disagreeable.
So it's always felt.
Oh yeah, perception and feeling are conjoined.
You can't just have perception and feeling coming later.
It's over simultaneous.
That's why the mind is determined by perception and feeling.
So it's experiencing an agreeable sight?
Well, you can say there is an agreeable feeling corresponding to it.
But that still doesn't mean that you're touched by pleasure.
When you're ignorant in regard to agreeable feeling,
you basically, you're touched by pleasure, which means you crave for it.
And the craving is the inclination towards,
the inclination towards?
Yeah.
I'm going to suffer, like just leaning of the mind towards,
leaning the weight, craving for, craving against.