So, as one of you could say, a little bit about social compassionate, engaged acts as
a path to freedom, you know, to engage bullism as a very big thing nowadays, and that as
a path to freedom from suffering.
Like, path got a hundred?
I mean, I guess depending on how you define engaged, to one extent, depending how you
define engaged, but what you said social engaged means like engaged with society, the social
work and stuff like that, no, it's impossible.
Basically, the maximum amount of engagement is what the Buddha prescribed for the monks,
in the part and giving the teachings to those who want to hear it.
That's about it.
Even that, it's kind of on the margin.
So, yes, first, there's four laypeople engaging socially compassionate.
Well, that's fine, but they cannot expect the results of our relationship, but as a
monk, devoting your time.
Well, it's a contradiction in terms that you'd be better off as a layperson devoting
a time to that, because there's a monk wearing the robe, keeping the vineyard, it's like
your statement that you're practicing towards the arrangement of supposedly.
So, if you dress as a monk, I mean, you are a monk, you keep the vineyard, but you act
like a layperson and social engaged, it's nice in lay terms and secular terms, and it's
very worldly, but there's nothing to do with practice of done, quite the opposite.
I mean, the Buddha was criticizing the monks who were quite detained at the time, like
Ananda and other teras, when they were sobbing the robes in that sutra, and they were just
talking around, like, you know, they had katina and sobbing the robes, and the Buddha came
in and was like, what was going on here?
When they said, oh, it's just Lord, you know, it's the katina with sobbing robes, like,
well, I thought he was like a band of fishermen, like shouting, like when they sell fish,
there's this ridiculous noise, and then he rebuked them all, and Ananda especially, you
should not be socializing in that manner, and those like monks with monks, for the, you
know, the great purpose of the katina, which is usually regarded as this great gathering,
yeah, the Buddha is just completely cutting down, because they were just, yeah, socializing
for no dharma purpose, basically, and you could see how much more that would be the truth
in case of, like, socializing for something completely secular.
It's nice, charity is nice, but it's no more than a good deed, so if a person is practicing
for art andmanship, he cannot afford, basically, to spend his time doing charity, unless he
can do charity completely in an undistracting manner or something, but it's highly unlikely,
and the best the person can really do is free themselves, that's how you contribute
to the well-being of the entire humanity, one being, one five aggregates less that is
trapped by samsara, there is no greater contribution to the big perspective of samsara, you can
be building hospitals and schools and everything else, and they will last, you know, maybe for
hundreds of years, but that's about it, but if a person frees themselves, they contribute
it to basically one entire being that's been tied for eons and eons and eons, they would
be freed from samsara never to return, there is no greater contribution towards the world
than that freedom of one by one, like, every person can help one being, let one being
be themselves, exactly, oh, well, that secondary, whether that being is yourself or not, but
yes, if you have to be yourself, exactly, you cannot do enlightenment for somebody else,
but when it comes to enlightenment, it ceases to be, when yourself, you remove the ownership,
which is why you become enlightened, that's the whole point, but from the ultimate point
of view of the, like, samsara and being strapped in it, that is the greatest contribution,
obviously, a person who cannot, people who cannot see beyond their sense of self and self
centeredness, they'll think, oh, that's your selfish, they're just doing that, but everything
you do, everything you have a desire to do, it's selfish, because you're just fulfilling
your desire, even if it's to help the others, so that's not optional, so you just want
to basically see how limited your goals will be or how expanded, you know, dedicating
your life to something that will make a difference in the world is very limited from the ultimate
point of view, it's certainly better than not doing anything at all, neither practicing
for enlightenment nor being generous and doing charity, but the problem is when people
start to charity thinking that's what leads to enlightenment, well, that's not true,
so if you can do a charity that won't impede your way towards enlightenment, that's absolutely
fine, but as I say, it's highly unlikely you'll be able to do that, or you might have
to limit your activities towards charity and helping others, because they should not
be the priority of somebody, we supposedly dedicated their life towards the practice of
enlightenment, I, about this month.