It's about dealing with tinsets for annoying people, for just in general how to not be offended
about what others are doing or what they are saying to you, no matter what, it's kind of
something insulting you, how do you become bullied?
Well that is, there is another thing that there has to be rooted in the strength before
basically because you get offended by people by insults because your mind has no control
over itself, so then immediately it jumps at the worst scenario, jumps at the insult and starts
not wanting it, resisting it, refusing it, wanting to retaliate because of it
but if you were able to keep your mind in check then the insult would just come and go
and you wouldn't be affected by it, but you can't expect to be able to keep your mind
in check if your body hasn't been kept in check and your speech hasn't been kept in check
so that's why, that's why it's a hard thing to do in a way because people are generally impatient
so they have a problem, they want to fix, but if they don't, but in order to fix it
you need to start building these bases for the fix, for the solution
because if you were a well-restraint person in regard to your own desires
they usually move people left and right, if you have confidence, if you have confidence
come from the restraint, from being able to say no to yourself, then you wouldn't lose perspective
even when others are basically abused you verbally or even physically
like you wouldn't, the mind would not feel beaten because of it
because it's basically the mind gives in, the mind makes itself insulted and affected by it
because those, the words, I mean the physical actions can stop at your body
the words, they stop at a level of speech, but then it's the mind picks it up,
persists, it doesn't want it, hates it, gives into your will on account of it or similar
so if someone calls you an idiot, your views are ridiculous
if you were, you're going to get offended
you get offended if you were not clear about your own views beforehand
if you were holding on to them for various unwholesome reasons such as
a sense of identity or because you fancy yourself as an intelligent person, smart person, intellectual person
or just generally insecure and then you kind of find solace in conviction, faith
and then you solve the challenges that you did struck right in your call
but if your views have used the product of restraint and wisdom, nobody can tell it
I mean the whole world can disagree with it, like you wouldn't be able to be affected by it
because it's nothing wrong with it, it's not based on unwholesome, it doesn't harm anyone
and it frees you from suffering right there right now, sorry right here and now
in a sense of that you have a direct verification that you're not proved and controlled by your own desires
and as much as you used to be, which means there's already that sense of confidence
oh yeah, no this works, people can come and tell them no, that doesn't work
that's ridiculous, that's just nonsense
it won't make a difference to you because actually you've seen it work
so you would only, the only conclusion would be ah, they don't know what to talk about
because if they were to know, they would agree with this
which is universally right, freedom from desire in that sense, it means freedom
so if you have that kind of clarity internally, then insults will won't be able to insult you
like if somebody says something in your will, his or her or her or your wouldn't necessarily cause your or your will
and then you wouldn't because you're not full of your will, you wouldn't lose your own perspective
which means you would be able actually to hear what they're saying
even if it's a completely ridiculous nonsense insult
you would still be able to hear it because you're not immediately automatically or in a defensive
and then sometimes you would hear, actually he has a point there
I mean he's completely wrong because his full will will and coming from a wrong place
but that's not my problem
but the content of what he was saying, yeah, I should have known better, I made a mistake
and that's it, you wouldn't be able to take it personally
you wouldn't be able to juggle, come in, you wouldn't be able to take it personally
and that's the problem, people cannot help but take this, well people's mind cannot help
but take whatever comes their way personally and then immediately end up either rejoicing in praise
or defending against the blame and attacking and fearing blame as well
even if it's completely grounded and ridiculous
they'll still fear just the phenomenon of blame and then then
it doesn't matter by whom or for if it's completely like if it's just after fabrication
it's not very true, it doesn't matter they'll still try to avoid blame for the sacred because they fear it
because they don't have that clarity and transparency and control over their own mind
you wouldn't be able to jump in it in that irrational manner
what about things like that?
no, no, like, it's like the weather
well again it's the same, similar attitude, just slightly more, slightly more subtle
can you pull the curtain please?
I know again it is a form of you resisting things that are not really your goal
to get the example of the weather, to acquire your noise
because you have desires that require a good weather
and while those desires are present, the bad weather is causing that discrepancy
that's making you know you want to get rid of it
but can you get rid of the bad weather?
can't, so that's why it's important to recognize that that discrepancy is causing you to suffer
if it is then you will recognize that the way that you can remove that suffering is remove the discrepancy
so if you can't change the weather, you can't change external circumstances in the nature
which means what you can change is change what you want at the time, change your desire
if you remove the desires requiring a nice sunny day
you will be affected by it by no amount of rain or any other weather
if you had the desire to just stay in and not going anywhere
it doesn't matter if you are a knowledge, it's got to be a reason
and that reason is that basically what makes that discrepancy
so you can either continue blaming the circumstances, blame the weather, blame the world, blame the other people
or recognize that that is inevitable and that's not where that suffering is rooted, nor that discrepancy
it's rooted in things that you can say no to which is your own desire
but people take that for granted so they never want to say no to their own desire
which is why it's always someone else's fault whenever suffering arises
it's because of this or because of that, it's never because, oh, I crave and I cause discrepancy with my desires
and as a result of that discrepancy I suffer
there is no other cause of suffering like that as if craving is sometimes suffering or something
whenever there is suffering it's because discrepancy caused by craving, nothing else
and not like more or less or a bit later
to the extent that there is discrepancy to that extent there is suffering
and that discrepancy with craving is either trying to prolong that which doesn't last as long
trying to get rid of that which lasts too long
because there is certain techniques that some people might do
if someone's, you know, someone who's very an insultive person
who's got a lot of your wealth in you
right?
then you see them, you sort of think that they're only human
they make mistakes
no, all of those things are management of the problem
none of them, management cannot approve the problem
it can only manage it which means it requires it
so yes, in the beginning when there is absolutely, you don't believe that confusion
you don't know what to do so then your management can offer some sort of help
but it's a mistake to regard management as a way of practicing towards
abooting the problem altogether she won't arise ever again
because management just covers up, just builds the door
which means when the next one comes you have to manage
which means that's not freedom
when you need to do something whenever this occurs
I need to go through these motions, I need to do it
sooner or later it's going to get too much
that's a definition of a burden, do you teach?
so you want to aim at the development of mind or meditation
or practice whereby you don't have to do anything on a kind of suffering
except see it
and you cannot not see it if you're just mindful
you'll always see it because you're mindful
and suffering is something that universally you cannot be oblivious to
which means all you have to do is remain mindful
and see the suffering and then the suffering which is
I mean if you're doing things rightly
then seeing suffering means uprooting the suffering
because you understood it
but management of suffering does not mean uprooting of suffering
so management of annoyance does not make you
impenetrable to future annoyance and you know that
you might become very skilled manager
and be able to deal with these things very quickly
but still you need to deal with this
which means you're affected in the first place
and freedom of it, freedom from it is when you're not affected
even in the first place
so that's the difference when it comes to freeing yourself from suffering
don't confuse management of it as the way out of it ultimately
it's not
the way out of it is understanding the nature of it
whereby having suffering or isn't means you're free from it
or simply put having suffering or isn't means it can't touch you anymore
a rising of suffering just reminds you that you're free of suffering
which means it's not your problem
which means it's not your suffering
there is no suffering at all