So I feel distracted most of the time, and my mind can never really settle down.
So how can I calm my mind down?
The first step is putting yourself in the calmer environment.
In other words, no matter how strong your resolve is to calm your mind,
if you are in the middle of interaction, engagement with others, with duties, with noise, visuals, you won't become.
So the wisdom lies in preventing these things from disturbing your peace,
so you want to see it ahead before you are in such an environment.
Or if you already are, you want to see that it's necessary, not just beneficial.
If you want to calm your mind, it is necessary to step outside of that environment, even temporarily.
So you want to calm down the circumstances around you, isolate yourself more from it.
Then, on the basis of that, you can start practicing mindfulness
and basically trying to understand what makes calm mind calm.
That's how you get the knowledge, and that's how you calm your mind.
You're not in the midst.
No, no, of course not.
Later on, obviously, when your mind is calmer and when you are stronger,
then you might end up in circumstances that are not calm but remain unaffected,
but not until your mind grew out of it.
Imagine like, I don't know, you catch some infectious disease.
And the first step is to get out of that environment,
because the environment is infecting you and just causing you to be constantly sick.
So then you have to spend a certain amount of time in a non-infected environment.
And then when you cure, you develop resistance, then you can go back, if you have to, to the infected environment.
You won't be affected again.
But it's the same if you want to calm down your mind and develop it.