You can see me as a bag drop.
There's only if you could describe me Bana, what is that?
What is your aim?
Your aim is Nibana, what is it?
You mean if somebody out gives that as an answer to a question?
What's in on my aim is Nibana?
Well that's the thing actually, understanding correctly what Nibana is means you would be at least a sort of Bana
Fully developing that understanding means yeah you have now developed Nibana as it became an arhant
As to what it is, well as the suitors would describe its absence of greed, aversion and delusion
Complete absence in the sense of the possibility of greed, aversion or delusion is impossible
So the mind has fully understood it and fully got rid of it
So it's not a place that one goes to?
No exactly, it isn't, it's not a...
It's not a magical realm that kind of gets one enters upon, if upon some certain practice of a special meditation technique or something like that
It's not a place you go into and replace what you know with it
It's really what you know now, your experience as it is, what you have now
Remove greed, aversion, delusion, remove possibility of greed, possibility of aversion, possibility of delusion from it
That's what Nibana becomes, that's what Nibana is
That's why we would say cooling down, literally, cooling down of the fires of passion, anger and so on
So you cool this thing down, this experience, this life you have, you cool it down
To the point of being irreversible, you cannot go back and be entered again by greed, aversion or delusion
It's been fully frozen to the point of these three things dying out and now they cannot reappear
And that's a developed Nibana
So you can see that in order to cool something down, you need to have it, you need to acknowledge it, you need to admit it
You need to see where the work in cooling it down lies
You're not replacing it with some new world or new realm or new meditation experience
You're actually fully understanding what you already have, so you don't need anything new, whatever it's necessary for Nibana
You already have it, everybody already has it
That's why the Buddha would refer to the element of Nibana in everyone's experience
As in possibility of developing the phenomenon which is Nibana, that means the element of Nibana is present
It's not about belief
You see, when people took it as a belief, that's when they started saying we are already in Nibana
Because Nibana is already there
That's when you fail to see the difference between the possibility and the actual development of something
Yeah, Nibana is there as a possibility
But saying that you have developed Nibana means you need to have it as your actual experience
As in you need to do the work of getting rid of greed, aversion and delusion
You will, hatred, sensuality, all of that
When Nibana is the perfected human being, and it's not perfect at all
Pretty much, but then see, perfect human being basically
It's certainly a perfection, but you wouldn't refer to that person as a human being anymore
Because human means going with the nature, going with the grain, going with the current, going with desires
Going with the cravings and so on, that's what makes humans human
So you actually, you cease to be a human
Arhand is not human anymore
If that's the designation you would use for a human
But yeah, overall, sure, as an individual, he still protects as a being in a human realm
But really what makes human human
Are these things that you sort of undo and relinquish as another hunt, as somebody who is enlightened?
Overcoming your humanity
Well, pretty much, first you need to overcome the immorality and non-virtue
But then you need to overcome that as well
That's why you're not really measurable by any human standards
He's not like a good human or a bad human, a good person or bad, no, he's not a person anymore
It's done
His abandon, relinquish the ownership
Of the slightest sort of appropriation of his own senses, his own aggregates
Yvonne is also called the non-appropriation in English, another
Right, yeah, yeah, sure, sure, non-appropriation
Or the undetermined
The undetermined, yeah, because the things that are determined for a human
For an unenlightened, unenlightened being
Are things that are determined by greedy version delusion
So you remove that and there is nothing determining things as mine anymore
Hence, they've experienced the undetermined
The experience of the undetermined
But it's a real experience as such
That's why Nibbana is a thing, a phenomena, a dama
If you can't really show people that Nibbana, can you show them?
No, of course not
Well, you can guide them to it, but even that will not necessarily result in them getting to it
Unless they have made the effort themselves
So you can point at it, you can describe it
You can lay out the way that somebody can practice towards it, but unless they practice
It's like getting real, getting absolutely real
Sure
Being honest with your situation, it's up to me, it's not
Oh, yeah, absolutely
Well, not just being honest with your situation, but also recognizing
The Buddha would refer to it as measure the task
Like a person would go and listen to whatever
Somebody he deems wise, somebody he deems that he can help him
And then he would ponder on the meaning of what's being said and what needs to be done
Once he starts grasping the meaning, he can see, oh, okay, this is the amount of effort
This is what I need to do to measure the task
And that is absolutely necessary in order to be able to do it
But most people don't, they kind of omit that whole thing of holon
What does this actually mean?
It might make me feel good, it might be very inspiring for me
But do I understand what it means
When I read the suttas or when I face instruction
That's sort of directing me towards Nibbana, am I aware of the actual meaning of it
As in what exactly I need to do?
And most people are not encouraged to think like that
It's most like, okay, you're inspired, that's great
Now here is a meditation technique that you just do mechanically
And then the experience you have
If it's substantial enough, if it affects you significantly enough
Then we can interpret it as Nibbana or as something leading to Nibbana
But Nibbana is not an interpretation
Any, any basically, any part of developing a wisdom
Does not partake in interpretation, certainly not by external terms
It protects the direct understanding of the meaning of it
Which then results in direct freedom from suffering
And hence, that's the greatest verification of your wisdom
You know you're right because you cannot suffer a mid-suffering
You cannot engage in your will, you cannot engage in centrality
You cannot engage in craving or distraction or delusion
And even if the whole world says, no, that's wrong
You know that they're wrong because you had one free from suffering
That's why Aruhant, Anagami Sakadami, Suddhupana, basically
They had one, well Aruhant is completely developed against the grain
Against the grain of nature and the outputs of the mind
And intentions and cravings and feelings and so on
Suddhupana is somebody who got, he understood it
He understood what it is, but he hasn't fully developed it
He hasn't fully went upstream, so to speak
Because, as I said, it's not like a theory or ideology
That you are sort of justifying and making it like an argument proof or something
No, it's directly verifiable in your experience
Why? Because you have the criteria, suffering and freedom from it
Sensuality and freedom from it, ill will and freedom from it
So you're free from those things, not because you've been running away from those things
Or you've been hiding or sort of trying to manage the circumstances
So you don't get challenged externally
No, you're free from those things because amidst those things
The mind cannot be overwhelmed by them, so you don't engage
It's not even a matter of restraint anymore, it becomes impossible
Once understanding has fully taken place, it becomes impossible to suffer, amidst suffering
And as I said, that is the greatest verification a person can have
That they've been practicing rightly
There's no verification from others saying that
No, of course not
Well done
I mean, the others can verify it as they did in the suitors basically
Not by, yes, I see the magic blue light aura around, he said he's another hand
But by talking to that person, interrogating them
To the point of discerning the subtle meanings and they were like, yeah
Because another hand would know what another other hand needs has to have understood beforehand
So he would know that, which means through questioning you could see the extent of other persons understanding
And that was also a way of progress as well
The Buddha would often encourage that in the suitors
Saying the monks would sort of interrogate each other, not like for the sake of argument
But for the sake of pressing for the meaning, you wouldn't leave anything unturned
So you'd be drilling and delving and basically making effort to understand
And then being questioned by your translation, by spiritual companions and so on
Again, it's like, have you understood this, have you?
And if you thought you did, well, you will then be able to convey it
To somebody else who did understand it
But then again, if you thought you did, but you haven't
This questioning can actually spur you to make further effort
Because you realize, oh, okay, I haven't been considering this or that
Or whatever the questions contain
But again, you can see that most of the modern practice today, when it comes to Buddhism, meditation, it's nothing to do with it
It's just watching nostrils cross your legs, sit in lotus, and that's it
And it will happen, or whatever
And what you just said, it seems that discussing the Dharma is useful
Gone, shall I tell you a sentence?
Yeah, discussing the Dharma is useful, provided that at least one of those people has understood it
Otherwise, it's blind leading the blind
In other words, two underlying persons, people who haven't even understood what Sotipati is
They can discuss the Dharma all they want
It won't result in knowledge, as in, like, you pair two ignorance together
It's not going to amount to knowledge
Because Patujan's experience is top to bottom ignorance
So you cannot accidentally stumble upon, or even find the right reference towards that ignorance
That's what they said, the absolutely necessary condition for arising on the right view is utterance of another
Of another who hasn't understood it
And, paired with that, they need to have the right attention, as in, they need to know
Basically how to hear it, how to dismiss it, how to attend to it
And how to practice that right utterance
So, then, once, see, like, for example, two Sotipanas could enable each other better in practice if they were to discuss it
Because it would just be reminding them of what they already know, but they haven't pressed it far enough in terms of understanding
Or even better, Sotipana talking to an other hand
But Patujan, it can only remain in Patujan
Or be dealing with mundane terms
Well, exactly, it might be helping each other how to manage their suffering better
But Sotipana is not management of suffering, it's the first step of uprooting it
As in, you know exactly how to approach it
And that's already freedom from suffering, you know, to a great degree
So, what about speech, truthful speech?
Right speech
Which you said, so you wouldn't say that discussing the Dhamma or your concerns, your spiritual concerns
With other people who are also on the same kind of path
You wouldn't say that's right
Well, if you define Noble by that which Patakes to, like, sort about your higher, then it isn't of course
Now, it can help people because in a sense of, it can make them make the effort on the personal level further
By having an intelligent feedback, even if it's another Patujan
What they should not expect is that the conversation, the discussion itself, results in some great epiphany
But in the same sense you come across a new Sutra or you come across other wrong view that then you actually understand better
And by doing so you clarify what the right view is
So, of course, that's all thanks to their personal effort
Towards understanding the nature of suffering and freedom from it
But yes, if the other person is equally sort of striving as you are
Then that discussion can sort of just, well, at least hint at certain directions
Of your reflection and of your contemplation
Good, both of those people say, well, I'm not enlightened
Are you enlightened? I'm not enlightened
Well, no, yeah, exactly, there is a difference between that
You have some of these people debating just because it's pleasant
Hey, let's have a discussion about it and just bounce ideas off each other
Well, I mean, that's utterly pointless
But if you know your situation, the beautiful Patujaner, you know that nothing sort of
Supremundane, so just speaking, come out of this discussion with another Patujaner
But you do it just to highlight your ignorance further
Which means you did begin with that self-honest attitude
But in that same sense, you don't even need the other person, just pick up any philosophy book
And look it like, okay, this is supposedly the wrong view
But have I understood it why and to what extent and where exactly it's wrong?
So you're not looking for faults, you're generally adopting that view
In order to be able to understand the extent of it
And by doing so, that's why often the Buddha would describe all these wrong views
They were present at the time
Because by fully understanding their extent, one would be much closer to the right view
So, as I said, discussing with another equal intelligent, equally self-transparent person, that can help
Stop making noise
That can help, in the same sense, reading other books or other teachings can help
But not if you don't have that necessary self-transparent basis
Come here, come here
So ideally, you want to be discussing these things with a sotupana
Someone who has a sotupana
Because otherwise, I think it is just stabbing in the dark
And even if you actually do
Even if you do actually stab something, you wouldn't know
So that's why I mean, like, hey, you can profit from it if you're already very self-transparent
In the same sense, you would profit from reading other views, other things
So you're not looking for faults, you're not covering it up, you haven't just adopted the belief that this is wrong
But you're genuinely understanding the extent of it and why it's wrong and how it's wrong
So, for a person who wants to discuss with a sotupana, how can you find one?
Well, exactly, he has no reference
What is his criteria?
What the closest to the right criteria can get is this self-transparency, being honest with oneself
And not being dismissive of other views
Even if they are not pleasing to you
Because usually people's criteria, for the views, opinions, ideologies, beliefs, is basically emotional
This is pleasing to me for whatever, there is maybe a small kind of degree of reasoning involved
But mostly, this is emotionally pleasing to me, thus this is my view, and that's why I'm defending it
And that's why I'm criticizing other views
Not because I have understood my view or I understood other views, no, it's just because
circumstantially I adopted it and now I'm defending it at all costs
So that attitude cannot, that attitude is basically the main impediment, that's like the wrong attention
When one looks, and the Buddha said they're looking for faults in a speaker, will prevent you understanding what he means
And by not getting the meaning, then you might actually sort of cross over a sotupana or even an other hand
Who's been speaking, you've been listening to it, but you were not paying proper attention
As in you were dismissing it, or not listening to carefully enough, and that's it, it's gone
And your views, your wrong views, your wrong criterias remain unaffected
Which means you're non-advisor, non-advisor even by having a Buddha himself in front of you teaching you
So that's what I mean, if you're self-transparent, honest, with yourself, so you know your situation, you know that you're not free from suffering
Not free from sensuality, or greed, or aversion
And then you also recognize the inevitability of having to have some views
But you don't judge your situation through your views, you judge your views through a situation
As in you can't help having views, but at the same time you recognize, well, I'm not free from suffering
I'm not free from greed, aversion, delusion, I'm not a sotupana, basically
Which means the views that I do hold in regard there, I should put in question
Because it's because of those very views that I'm not free from suffering, free from greed, aversion, I'm not a sotupana yet
But people might think one thing, then they might think about the second thing of their views, but they never put it together and see that that's a contradiction
Because you can't have put two generous views that are right and not be a sotupana
Because right view means sotupana, so if you don't have the right view, you can't entertain the notion that you're put
Sorry, if you're not a sotupana, if you're a sotupana, if you're a sotupana, you can't entertain a notion, did you also have right views?
And that attitude is unpleasant, because it's like living in perpetual doubt of your own existence
And that's very, it can be very anxious, very, yeah, like lots of sort of concern
Because any single view that you look into, you realize, well, this might be wrong
Then any confidence that you might have had as a bhutujana gets completely undone, demolished, but that's the whole point
So that's why when the practice of dhamma, when thinking and reflecting upon views, it's not optional anymore, it's existential basically
You need to do it, you need to clarify it, because you realize the parallel of it
You can't just simply adopt a belief that's
Well, you can adopt a belief, but if you're self-honest, if you do have that honesty, you wouldn't be able to
As appealing as a belief might be, you wouldn't be able to
Well, you would be able to at the expense of honesty, self-honest
But if you realize that self-honestity should not be compromised ever
Then that's your safeguard against adopting and proliferating things just simply upon a belief
So then if you adopt something, it would be after heavy scrutiny
And even then, you wouldn't adopt it as a belief
You would adopt it pretty much as a strategy towards your practice of freedom from suffering
Which means if that strategy is not bearing any fruit and you're not free from suffering
You're going to be upgrading it or changing it, and you won't be afraid to do it
And faith
Well, that's there, you can have a belief without faith, but you can have faith without a belief
So the faith that we are talking about is the, it's in the suit, as you mentioned, and I might have spoken about it before
The faith we are talking about is the faith that you would have, that a person would have in a doctor
As in, you recognize your situation through that self-honest scrutiny of yourself, basically
You recognize that you need help as in you are a subject to suffering, you are prey to suffering
You don't know the way out from a reason suffering
And then you find something that promises their way out
So you have faith that it might work, if it's applied, obviously
So in the same sense, you recognize you have an illness, you go to a doctor
So you have faith that he can help you, that he can prescribe your medicine, and whatever course of treatment or something
They will then result in that freedom, not from that ailment
So if you do start taking medicine and doing everything rightly, you understood the doctor's instructions properly
And you're not being free from your ailment
Well, maybe a faith a bit longer, a bit more, keep applying it, but then if it's nothing, there's no results
Well, then you won't have a problem changing it, looking for a different way, because it's not working
You haven't done it out of a sort of emotional attitude, or you, nothing, no, you really, you generally tried, anyhow, it didn't free you
But if it does free you, then that faith disappears, because you don't have to have faith that you could work
Because now you know that he worked, and you are cured
And that's when the suttas, like for Sotapana, his faith in the Buddha Damasanga has been replaced by the confirmed confidence
So he was confirmed, now he can see his health as a direct result of having faith in this application
But again, you need to be honest, because if you're not, you're going to be blaming a doctor
You're going to be blaming the one who gave the instruction
But actually you first need to start with yourself
Because if it's not working, if you don't have patience and you're no self-transparent, you won't see that you're impatient
So then you won't see that it's actually your lack of patience, patience, that's a problem
As in you need to take the medicine a bit longer, and then you're just going to dismiss a doctor who could have been Buddha himself
So that's why I insist always on self-transparenting, because if you're not, you will be pointing fingers, basically, when there are no results to show flow
So that's why I insist on self-transparenting, that's why I insist on self-transparenting
So the instructions given by the Buddha
What are they? What was his first instructions?
What was his first instructions again?
There's suffering and there's freedom from it
Because you have...
By the way, you're recording, yeah
The Buddha only gives precepts much later on
In his people during his life, much later on
Well, he defines them specifically later on
The actual virtue that was sort of contained in the eight precepts
Has been praised by him throughout the Suttas and Deganika and Majmika
He would say that the wise men of the past were virtues
He was taken for granted, basically, that somebody who has already came to that point of practicing the Dhamma has already had their virtue developed
They've been restrained, moral virtues, honest and so on
Where do they get those morality from?
The people who...
In the past?
I'm understanding the natural principles, as in the universal principles of a human existence
It gets an understanding of principles
Basically, if you understand wise virtue virtues
It's already the beginning of wisdom
So you can also arrive at that understanding by taking virtue of faith
The faith we discussed
So you have faith that virtue is necessary
In the same sense, the doctor tells you
Well, this medicine will work only if you follow a strict diet
If you're careless with what you eat, it's going to cancel the effectiveness of a prescription I'm giving you
But obviously some people will not have even that little bit of faith
But if they do investigate, reflect upon themselves in that same transparent manner
Well, you would see basically that virtue is virtues
Because it does not contain any existential discrepancy or contradiction
Which means in order to arrive at it, you are already developing wisdom
Like good things are good because they're basically aligned with the universal principles
With things that are most fundamental
So like for example, sharing and giving and charity is good
Like why?
Well people say, oh, it makes me feel good
That's all secondary
Existentially, charity is good
Because it goes along the way of you not being owner of the things in the first place
Yet everybody starts with a sense of ownership
It's completely gratuitous, but everybody owns
Everybody immediately feels they're the owner of their body, their senses
Basically through engagement with the world through the tools, which are your senses, which is your body
You start, you're fully identified with the tools
With eye, nose, nose, ears and mouth, body and everything else, basically
So you don't know why, but they said giving is good
Well, giving is good because you basically deprive yourself of something
To give to somebody else which resembles the experience of non-ownership of that
Which has been owned
That which I still regard as mine, I give to somebody else
So you can arrive at it either through doing that and then contemplating it
Or not doing it, but then you need to have this on it
But it's highly unlikely you're going to arrive at it
Through stinginess and complete lack of any virtue
Based on virtue or charity in kindness
And you can take any, any other thing that's regarded as good and virtues generally
You would see that it would be along the, it would be mirroring
It would be reflecting upon some, some principles of your existence
That you're living right there and then, but you're not aware of
Lying, basically it's another discrepancy
There is a truth, you choose to override it
You choose to act upon that discrepancy
And then perpetuate it as a non-discrepancy
And that's why it's not wholesome, same stealing
It reinforces the perverted pattern of human existence
As in, I am the owner of my body and my senses and things that I can gain through
To the point of then taking that which you perceive through your senses as not yours
As an extension of the very attitude that you have towards your own senses
Because basically you do become a thief
We might have all started as, as borrowing
We're all just, just basically renting these body and these senses
So to speak, they're given to us for our use
But the moment you start regarding his yours, that which you have rented, you have effectively stole it
Taking from Marlon
Exactly, yeah, the Buddha did say that, is it because people take and use that which doesn't belong to them
Well, they take it as theirs that we just belong to them
That's why the matter controls them and does what he wants
And that's why they're subject to suffering and the whole death and misery and everything else
And then when the monks are so what are those things?
He said it's eyes and the objects, ears and sounds, nose and smells
Mouth, sorry, tongue and taste, body and touches
Those are the things basically that don't belong to you
That you're just renting, they're just borrowed jewelry as the Buddha would refer to you
But you start entertaining the notion that you are their owner, they are their own
And it's not like a metaphysical secret that you need to figure out in order to drop it
To not regard it as yours, no, you just need to dwell on the fact that they're not yours
Just need to keep really, really, really investigating the meaning of not mine
And then applying it to yourself
And they're obviously in the most general terms, that's what the Buddha would describe
Well, if you were the owner of your body, for example, would the body be subjected to sickness, aging and death?
You would it?
See, many people think that, oh yeah, of course I understand that, I'm subject to all these things
But if you truly understood, if you were to truly understand that, you would be completely free from appropriation
So that's what I mean, if you're self-transparent, then you would see a discrepancy
On one hand, I'm thinking I understood it
On another hand, I don't have that which is supposed to be the result of that understanding
As in freedom from appropriation, freedom from suffering, freedom from greedy version delusion
And if you see that discrepancy, that contradiction, then you'll know exactly where to do the work
Which is, okay, I need to understand this further, and what I think understanding is, it's not sufficient
Or sometimes it's just playing out wrong, but you wouldn't have seen it unless you brought this discrepancy
Like to the fore, I fully understood it
So initially one takes on virtue, given from an external
Well, yeah, exactly set of values, or whatever
But you could see that in every society, there is a degree of it because it would kind of seep down
Into like, you know, collective society awareness that's sort of among the completely unenlightening people
But you'd still get the sense of it
Sharing is good, patience is good, all these things
It is good, but it's also good to understand why these things are good
Because then you can take it even further
Then you can discover virtue by yourself
Yeah, I suppose, well, the Buddha did, so you could say that the Buddha did discover it by himself
But it's highly unlikely, because you would kind of need some point as some external reference point
You got a bit deeper without having
Well, you can only take it so far, basically, you could discover virtue by yourself to a degree
But not fully understand it to the point of becoming a sottabhana
As in the one who has understood Sila, and thus he is free from Sila Bhattaparamasa, which is virtue and duty
A factor of virtue and duty is free from
Because that's another thing
In order to understand virtue, you need to have it
You can't be a non-virtuous person and then understand the nature of virtue
You need to be having it present in you, presently, there is an experience
As in, you need to be virtuous, basically
But being virtuous in itself, it's nice, but it does not result in wisdom
And if there's no wisdom, there's no liberation
That's why, obviously, Sila and virtue, it's not the Dama
But that's why also Dama is impossible to arise without Sila
Because how can you understand, how can you develop understanding of Sila without Sila?
Impossible
But many people don't see their connection, which is why that is the very first feta of Sila Bhattaparamasa
People think you must be virtuous, and yes, you do, you do have to be virtuous
But then they think, okay, so I'm doing that, and now the practice of Dama and understanding is over here
I'm doing my meditation technique, I'm reading the suttas, I'm studying Pali, and I'm virtue, so it's all contributing, no
Basically, you have the virtue, you have the morality, you have the restraint
You take it in further, and practice like the sensory strength, even of things that are not necessarily known virtues
But are not virtuous enough, perhaps
Such as pursuing sight, sound, smell, taste, touch, they're distracting
They're not necessarily rooted in anger, and breaking of moral precepts or rooted in sensuality
And breaking celibacy precepts and so on
But they can be rooted in distraction and carelessness, so you stop doing that
And then you understand that very basis, you don't need to go elsewhere
You don't need some other, like, whatever, developing some sort of sappra mundane concentration, no
You already have it in front of you, now you need to start making the effort to cut through that fog of ignorance in regard to it
Don't just take it for granted that it's good, understand it, why it is good
That's why the definition of Sotapan is he's the one who knows good as good, and bad as bad
Putujana is like a virtuous putujana, a good putujana is the one who doesn't know good as good, bad as bad
So if you do want to practice meditation and contemplation, practice it within the basis of your virtuous behavior and sensory strength
You just left right before or after it, within it, as in when this, this is
When the basis of virtue is present, me trying to understand it is also present
But the point is to understand that they are not found elsewhere or they are not given to you through some sort of divine providence through some sort of
Super concentration you developed and then you have this great revelation
You develop it on the basis that you maintained
So you're maintaining the basis of virtue and then you develop your understanding of it
That's it
And that's why for Sotapan who has understood the nature of virtue, who has understood good as good, bad as bad
All he needs to do is continue practicing Naikkama Sankapa, as in the video we described it
It's thoughts of renunciation, basically, so being virtuous and sensory strength and practicing thoughts of renunciation
And that in itself would then result in other energy because he has understood that
So through doing it, he's developing that very understanding of it
And that's how you would also, as the Buddha will often encourage people to see the danger in the slightest fault
That's how you would start seeing the danger in the slightest fault
Or it's just a small thing, it doesn't matter
The biggest thing or small thing if it but takes in the nature of unwholesome, it's unwholesome
Thus, it's directly against the principle of dama, the universal principle
And that's why it would be enough for somebody to receive instruction as simple as
Avoid anything that's unwholesome and cultivate anything that's wholesome
As they did in the Suttas, the Buddha's foster mother, when she asked for that instruction
And the Buddha said, anything you know that's unwholesome, abandon it and anything you know that's wholesome, cultivate
And then she went for like a seclusion for three months and so on and came back, in other hand
Fully enlightened, fully freed basically, because she fully understood it
And you could see how many people today, oh yeah, of course, this is bad, this is good
But if you were to truly understand that, you'd be this sort of person
So then, if you think you have a knowledge of what's good, what's bad, ask yourself, are you a Suttupan? Are you a stream mentor?
If the answer is no, then don't take that knowledge for granted, because it's not sufficient
I mean, it might be good and sufficient for mundane terms
But that's, well, exactly, if you might be means you're not free from another
Fatir, which is in that first group, which is Fatir of that, if you don't know, your Suttupanam means you're not Suttupanam
Understanding what Suttupan is makes you one
Understanding what Sillabad Paramasa is, frees you from it
Understanding what a self-view is, frees you from it
So you guys, I might be free from self-view, but I don't know it yet, means you're not
I mentioned yesterday when I was talking to those people
We don't want to mention names
Well, this whole self-reflexive attitude is like, you really want to do it
In order to gain wisdom, to learn from it, basically
You don't want to be, hey, you're not doing it because you want to justify your actions
I mean, that's what people usually be doing
I'm not going to say it again
Joe? Andy? Oh, yeah
Crazy little, crazy little, calm down, calm down
You really want to ask yourself, basically, like, say when it comes to practice with them, why are you doing it?
Like, really clarify
Where do you want to arrive with it? What's the goal?
Or in general, in any areas of your life, basically
Just ask them, what do I want to do in my life? What is my purpose?
But don't ask an expect immediate answer or something like that, but ask and then think about it
And then if the answer presents itself, well, then question that answer
Because most people will be going through life, basically
I don't know if there's an English expression, but certainly back in Serbia, like a headless fly
Headless chicken?
Well, you know, like a fly that doesn't have, and it's just flying like mad, left and right, hitting into wind
It's still flying, but it doesn't have the heads, it doesn't see where anymore
And most people would actually be able to help themselves if they just stop for a second and ask yourself
Like, why am I doing this particular thing? What for?
Why do I want it? Why do I want it?
Most people don't even know what they want
So it's just like habitually scratching the edge like an animal, basically
And going through things as they arise
So the attitude would help, even in terms of like an ordinary life, somebody is not interested in greater development of the dama or son
But let alone for somebody who does want to practice dama, it's just completely necessary
You need to develop that self-reflection, that transparency and that kind of scrutiny of your own self
Of your own thoughts, of your own intentions
Because it will force the correct perspective upon you, you can't have it willingly, you can't just willingly adopt the correct perspective
Because any perspective you know of, it's already perspective that's affected by greater version delusion
So just ask yourself, where do I want to be?
And say, in one year time or two years time, provided I lived that long, what's my purpose? What's my goal?
Or you can basically review things that you already got committed to or engaged
Well, why am I doing this? Why am I still doing this? Why did I start doing this? And see where the answers come up?
You want to be successful?
Okay, so what for?
Say I'm doing this job because I want to earn money and be my own boss
Why is that a good thing being your own boss? Why is that something you value?
Well, the answer would be because it's unpleasant to have somebody else telling me what to do
Okay, so why is then the unpleasant experience of having somebody else tell you what to do?
Why is that a problem for you on the personal level?
Why can't you just remain indifferent towards the economy and just do it? Why is it a problem?
Well, it's a problem because it's making me suffer
Ah, so suffering is a problem
Now, you're doing this job 10 hours a day, earning loads of money, trying to start it on a bit
Just because you don't suffer
But is there a guarantee that you won't suffer after all that effort you put in?
There isn't
And then secondly, that all effort you put in, you might have overcome
possibility of suffering on account of somebody else telling you what to do
But the millions of other ways of suffering in your life
means you invested your whole life
How many years of building something up just to address like 0.1% of possibilities of suffering
Because you haven't freed yourself from the nature of suffering
You only freed yourself from one particular manifestation of it
Having somebody else less qualified than me telling me what to do and boxing me around
Is that a fair investment? Is that a good investment?
You realize it isn't
So then obviously the inevitable question is what do I do then?
Well, you ask yourself what's more important?
Being completely free from suffering or partially
Now you can choose whatever you want, but then you will choose it responsibly
Because now you know, okay, there is a possibility of being free from suffering altogether
But I feel it feels a bit daunting for me
So I'm kind of satisfied with sort of halfway
But that's fine, but then you will take responsibility for it
Which means when the other half of suffering that you haven't freed yourself
Comes your way, you won't be blaming others, you won't be resorting to ill will
Psychologizing your suffering, finding excuses for it
No, you'll accept it as part of the deal that you accept it when you clarify your perspective
And your goals
But if you haven't done that, everything will always be someone else's fault
And you're not going to be responsible for anything you do, yet you're going to be equally bound
Even more probably with suffering and you won't be able to do anything about it
Which means your efforts are completely misdirected, yet that was the goal from the start
And now for somebody who does practice now, I'll just again ask yourself
Well, why am I practicing that? To be free from suffering?
Well, is my current way of practicing, is it contributing?
Well, yeah, I hope it is, but do you know for sure that it is?
Well, it must, well, that's not the right answer, it must be contributing
Because I've been doing it for 20 years
If it's contributing, means your suffering is lessening
Means possibility to suffer is being lessening, fading out
So you need to be honest and admit because the answer might not be a pleasing one
Especially if you invested 20 years in practice and you still can't tell whether you're anything closer to being free from suffering
But that is the absolute necessary step, for as long as you ignore to address it in such direct, non-compromising manner
You can be practicing for hundreds of years and still remain a protugena
And sometimes, all it would take for you to stop being a protugena is that
Just admit that you're a protugena
That doesn't, because some people might have actually done the right practice, but they don't know it
But they can only find out once they admit that they don't know it
And then if it were right, their efforts, their reflection, then they're like, oh yeah
But because they're too afraid to go that way, they'll never find out
And that's why they won't be a sort of one
And that's why it's their great loss
Basically, all your efforts remain undermined just by lacking their last grain of courage
Just admitting to yourself that you don't know, truly, on that existential level
You know, after so many years of practice, of so-called practice, of trying to
Suppose like some are trying to get rich and then pretending that they are already rich
Well, pretty much, yeah, again, it's another discrepancy
That's what I mean, like, I don't have to completely 100% discrepancy free
Any discrepancy in the existential is impossible
That's a definition of another hand
So if you start recognizing that, you would see exactly, yeah, so I'm practicing
Or say, I'm working to be rich, but I'm not rich
So I can be blaming others
Or I can accept others as a factor in me not being rich and then incorporate it in my efforts
And then upgrade my efforts
But only once I admit that I'm poor
If you don't admit it, to be everybody else's fault
That's preventing you from getting there or whatever
And you're still going to be doing the same things
Because of which you're not getting where you're going to get
So you won't be questioning your efforts of getting rich, acquiring wealth
Despite your immediate poverty
So is there like a time period that one could say?
You can try a certain...
Well, that's why we'll go back to the very first thing we said about the faith
And then, yeah, so you have to have some faith and you have to give it some time
But yeah, after a while you might even have to cut your losses and just restart
Because you're not doing it for the sake of doing it
You're doing it to be free from suffering
You're doing it for the gold
You're doing it for the fruit, you're doing it to arrive at that degree of liberation
But obviously somewhere down the line for some people
That kind of got pushed in the background
And now they became too precious, too protective of the efforts they invested in their practice
Despite the lack of result
And then they defend that
They defend that kind of indefensible position, really, it's a contradiction
But they say, well, I might not be a Sothepana, but surely all these efforts do not have been wasted
And they refuse to let go of it
But that means they have to keep doing it
Because if they change their effort, they will be almost like the affirmation
The fact that they've been wasting, that they've been misguided and misdirecting their efforts
So then they have to stick to it just to keep validating it for themselves that they're not wrong
And because of that, they get becoming more and more wrong with each time
Because that transparency, if it were there to begin with, gold completely obscured
So basically, question yourself and be honest
Don't fabricate, don't push for answers
Just be honest, where am I in my practice?
Am I complacent?
Do I think I have time, as in how long will I live?
All these things
And you read the Sothes, that's all the time you're talking about
And you don't do it for some sort of, gaining some sort of emotional kind of uplifting
No, you're doing it for understanding
You're doing it to develop clarity, to maintain perspective basically
That's why you're doing it
And same again, this is like from the point of view of practicing the Dharma and the Buddha staging
But even if you just want to live a wholesome, skillful life
As a normal layperson, not interested in some renouncing the world that has family and job
Still, it's going to help you
Certainly going to strengthen you
And develop your mind to deal with anything else that comes your way in a lay life
And there are a lot of things coming people's way
Lots of pressure, lots of stress, lots of burden
Initial responses, you just deal by any means necessary
But if you start dealing it rightly through the right perspective, restraint and virtue
It's going to make things more difficult in the beginning
But in the long run, it just creates this resilience that nothing else can match
That's the definition of wisdom, basically
Obviously, you can have it to different degrees, but
Having perspective on yourself in a situation
Not just being absorbed and pulled by the immediacy of a situation
And it would usually result in being quite reactionary
Situations like this are react like this, just like an animal
And it's also useful before, like if people, the sooner people start thinking like this
But as in thinking in terms of self-refracting and really questioning themselves all the time
The sooner the better, because you would have committed less in life
As in starting a family and now you have people there to look after
And so on that you can't just turn your back on
But even then it's not too late
Because there is no end to a human proliferation in the world
To the proliferation of sensuality in the wrong view and lack of restraint
There is no end to that
The only end to that is self-reflection
They will then prevent you from proliferating carelessly
Through greed and ill will and wrong views and hatred and whatnot
It's true protection, you can't
Taking up responsibility is a true protection for yourself
Going and getting to a group or a certain nationality or identity
That's the opposite
That's when you have already disowned your responsibility
Then you find that formation in that act by identifying with a greater group
That just obscures it even further
The fact that you already covered up your personal responsibility for your personal existence and your personal choices
And then it's just intoxicating, that's like the masses, you know
And even things that you wouldn't have necessarily done on a personal level
If you were with yourself questioning yourself, you would have, you do it in a group
Because again, it's just got all absorbed in this impersonal day
As either gate we've been talking about
The now is just acting as this complete protection and you can do whatever you want
That's like mob, definition of a mob mentality
When you know these things are wrong and you wouldn't have done them if you were on your own
Or with somebody else who is not like
But now it's just mob is intoxicating
And why it's intoxicating because it's just extension
Of complete lack of, well of complete cover-up of your personal responsibility
And then you just do stuff that you were not supposed to for their very sake
It's going to be quite inviting to do it
Here let's smash these windows and break this
Not because they done anything to us or have any game, no
Just because you're not supposed to do it
And if you do it you'll be responsible for it
But now we're in a mob who cares, they can't get me and then you do it
That's like the ultimate non-restraint
And the ultimate contradiction
Because you can't really, you can only cover up responsibility
Which means through every single act of covering up your personal responsibility
You reaffirm that personal responsibility because that's the very reason of your actions of covering it up
Hence a sartre will define it as bad faith
Or in authenticity
But you carry it in the heart of everything you do
It's almost like if you want to make your society strong
You have to do your work
Exactly, society will be, the strong society will be a result of personally developed individuals
Developed in a sense of accepting responsibility
And gaining perspective on account of it as in developing wisdom
The result would be a strong society, a resilient society, a just society
Society that has the right perspective on things
Society that's quite aligned with good is good and bad is bad
Because that's what I mean
It's that contradiction at the existential level
That's bad, that's why bad things are bad
So if now you're not self, not not through adopting like
Tama or Christianity or anything just through that self reflection of not tolerating existential contradiction
Not covering up your responsibility for your own choices
Maintaining perspective through constant self questioning
Basically that will already result in you aligning yourself with good action
Even if you don't necessarily know it or have not accepted it as some sort of external set of values
And then if everybody were to start doing that to perspective degree as much as they're capable
It would reflect on the society as a whole
Because there's no society without individuals
Individuals precede society
But obviously it's much more inspiring so to speak
And it certainly requires less work to just identify with impersonal notion of society
And by doing so, enable yourself even further to cover up your own responsibility that you have been avoiding
Because if you were transparent to begin with, you wouldn't have identified yourself
Because you realize what a contradiction that is
You can't be they
No matter how much you're absorbed in a greater cause and what not
You cannot step outside of your point of view
Ever, you're completely confined to that perspective
Yet you say no, this is not me, this is a greater good, this is a greater service, a greater group, basically
But if you really want to contribute to a group, you do so from the inside as in every single individual
You can't abstract the group as if it's independent of individuals
It's basically attempted a shortcut
Hey, let's create a philosophy or a policy or a political system
They'll be dealing with group as such
Putting individuals second
And there was a definition of communism
Or certainly one of the principles, maybe not a definition
But it's like, okay, well, you theorized the perfection of a group
And then you try, okay, so in order to maintain this perfect image of a group
Will be sort of attacking individuals and dealing with them
And all you're doing is maintaining your own notion, your own perspective of what you think group is
That's what I mean, you can't step outside of your personal point of view
Ever, and if you do, it's in order to cover it up
Hence the group identity, group politics
And if mob mentality, nationalism, anything, religion
If it's done for those reasons, and it is, usually
You wouldn't be stepping outside of your group if you're not running away from your own self-responsibility
You wouldn't need it
On the house of society, we would look if we were going to present each other
Well, as I said, it would probably be much more aligned with principles of good and principles so bad
People would have that on an average person would have a good sort of judgment of what's good
As in, it would have an notion of why good is good, bad is bad
So you could see how modern society, how far it's removed from that
People would know and value certain things, but that's far from saying that they understood those things
That's why the Buddha was talking about the justly, the back in the day
The righteous king, clearly, has developed knowledge of good, is good, bad is bad
And then he wouldn't be just taking and conquering, be giving back
So basically, people can have a certain quality to their life
Not just exploitation for the sake of personal gain
And because of that, then people are valuing that, and then they start doing the same
Because the king is just dead justly
And they don't blame and gratuitously or try to avoid their own responsibility
Why? Because basically, that's how people already are acting, responsibly and so on
Then you would really stand out
That's a decline of society, basically, when sensuality and avoiding of responsibility become a norm
And you realize that, like in schools, for example, when you were growing up, when I was growing up
I mean, we were taught everything and nothing
But as any of us ever been taught in our schools, elementary or higher
Like, you know, the value of patience, the value of sensory strength
The value of being able to say no to yourself, to be bitter
If you got any of that, it was circumstantial
And I think that's quite universal
I don't think, like the whole notion of school back in the days of the ancient Greece
Was to part, sort of, to enable people to go through their life more wisely
To be able to deal, basically, to create a perspective for them
They will then create in a better life for them
And you realize today, there's none of that
Perspective? No
You're just being thrown information by the teacher
If you pedal the information back, you pass it if you don't
Very little understanding of it is actually encouraged
Why? Because people who are teaching haven't understood it themselves
You're just going through a curriculum
So then you can't be surprised that the value on the level of society
Is just the mirroring personal values
Which is just following your desires, getting what you want
Whenever you want it, however you want it
Not being responsible, blaming others
It's kind of a norm nowadays
But it's impossible, a perfect society
It's impossible, yeah
The perfect society would be basically a sangha of arahans
But there wouldn't be a society anymore
That doesn't mean, of course, that a person should not be aiming at perfection internally
Personally, because aiming at 100% will at least mirror 20% into society of good
That then other people can learn from
That's not the goal, it's not to perfect society
But basically, think of society as a generated image
And a kind of operating individual
And it's that operation of those individuals, their actions
That's the problem
Generating image of it is just a symptom of a problem
So you could basically see the problems of individuals by looking at the problems of society
You would just be a more general projection of it
By you trying to deal with the problems of society
It's like trying to deal with the projection of a problem, not the actual problem
That's why you can use it to learn from it
To maintain perspective, but the problem is undone on the personal level
Through that responsibility and self-reflection
And questioning and natural virtue, they will come out of it
Then the projection will change, you'll be projecting those things
Not the lack of those things
Yeah, exactly, let's replace this kind of arrangement of society with another arrangement
With a different system
But again, that's missing the point, there's just basically fighting over types of projections
Or trying fighting over ways you should be dealing with projections
But you're not uprooting the actual problem that is being projected
And again, that attitude itself is a projection of the individual attitude towards your own problems
Like when people suffer, when people experience difficulties
They don't necessarily look into themselves
Is this a projection of my attitude or my actions?
No, they want to manage it, they want to manage the problem
They want to remove the problem, they want to get rid of the problem
So that's why I mean everything on the level of society is a projection
From the level of individuals, whichever prevails
And that in itself is already a projection of the individual attitude
That they have, that people have in regard to their own problems and suffering
Or I have a problem, well, who caused it? Well, if it's me, okay, well then I'll either apologize or let's pretend it never happened
All these things are management of the problem that has already arisen
Yeah, you can do that, but that's not uprooting the problem, don't confuse the two
Approaching of the problem is then reflecting further and saying, okay, but will I in the future then cause the same issue for myself through my careless actions, for example?
Or will I be able to prevent it? How can I prevent it?
And that's the truth, the official learning from your own mistakes, like trial and error
Well, you want to look not just to deal with this particular issue, there has arisen
But to basically extrapolate the principle that you can discern, that can then help you not make the same mistake in the future
And if that's your attitude towards your own personal existence and actions and responsibility and choices and so on
And that's the attitude of other people as well, that will be reflected in society
Or at least not the largest society but your family
Well, of course, yeah, certainly, yeah, yeah, it's individual, then the family, then the smaller group, whatever, then obviously
But it all trickles down, like a stream on a mountain top that's filling down
Lower streams, they're filling down lower rivers, they're filling down lower lakes and other rivers, then eventually filling down the seas and so on
If you dry it up at the top, or if you remove the pollution from it at the top, eventually even the sea will cease to be polluted
But if you're just trying to deal with the level of the sea without addressing the source of the pollution, well, you're fighting a losing battle