those within that and you pull it apart.
Of the random operation of all,
you can't even put your arms up.
That's it.
You cannot see remaining alive.
So if the body, the material aspect, the flesh aspect,
the hoop bar gets deformed, destroyed,
they cannot remain any consciousness in regard to it.
So that's how you recognize that then your eye,
your nose, your ears are that ultimate away from you.
Then you just have obviously been appropriate for so long,
and it's so close that you can't see it.
So then you just assume it's in you, it's yours,
and you have the result.
Well, it's kind of the expression of you, so to speak.
But if you start to see that when you think about the eye,
it's the certain expectation that they will find
a real eye somewhere else.
But you want.
Thoughts you have about the eye are all you can have about the eye.
Because I myself, it's always going to be ultimate negative,
and it doesn't appear.
So what appears is that because of which there is sort of appearance,
and that's determined by that eye.
So even when you think eye, you have to stop regarding that
as a real eye or as a non-real eye,
or as both real and not real, you can just recognize,
I can only have thoughts that stand in place of an eye.
And when I say an eye, that's another thought that stands
in the place of an eye, which is another thought,
which is another thought.
So you can never access the eye.
You can only be a second sort of to it.
Whatever thought, whatever abstraction,
whatever is going to be secondary to it.
And that's all it's necessarily to recognize that
because then you see, oh, by being inaccessible,
you cannot even conceive ownership of it.
And Bande can you even access thoughts?
Well, exactly. Then if you start refining that principle further,
I mean, it's relatively refined when it comes to body,
it's the same principle that comes to mind,
but it's much harder to see, as the word has said, himself.
Because putution can get rid of the body.
So do, do, do, do, do.
If you extend the same principle,
then you realize that thoughts themselves,
in their nature arise on their own.
You sort of manage them, you intend upon them,
but that intention is secondary to the arising of thoughts.
Thus, intention shares the same nature of,
cannot be owned.
Because it's founded upon things that are inaccessible to ownership.
And that's how the mind gets free from the suckness,
conceding, and becomes an utterance.
So then you can think and will, and still not own it,
while you're willing and thinking and deciding,
and telling off, and whatever else,
what you do, you have to know about it in a way.
It's the same principle, but it's much harder to see it
on the level of the mind,
but if you see it on the level of the body thoroughly,
then yes, it's far from impossible.
Because that's the whole point.
It's, it's used spinning over,
in the same sense that after all,
that spills over the five aggregates, and owns them.
Once that's gone, well, then you still have perceptions
in regard to the sense basis that spills over,
that assume the access to the eye to the nose
hence the sensuality.
Because the only benefit of central sides,
that benefit can only pertain to the flesh eye.
Nothing else can benefit from sight.
Skin and the sense of touch can only benefit
from touching things.
You, you can't access that.
But by fully assuming access to the body,
to the eyes, you have been drawn
by that which these things want.
So then you think you are accessing
all the external sensuality.
You are touching pleasant objects.
You are tasting pleasant sounds.
Sorry, pleasant taste.
And you're hearing a grieble sound.
No, ear is hearing the sound.
It cannot be different.
Eye is seeing the sights.
But you, when you say eye,
you assume the eye.
Hence, you are pulled by the sights.
So that's why the mindfulness,
this mindfulness I'm talking about,
peripheral, or letting in the ear is necessary
because you never see a connection
between your thoughts about the eye,
your sights, the lip.
And that indirect, fleshy organ
that is simultaneously present
because of which all of this is possible,
that in return defines that, which is an eye.
That's why the sense base is defined
by the sense object.
In itself, you can't even conceive.
The extent of it.
But if the mindfulness is developing
the way we're talking, yes,
then you would be able to hold the thought
of the present organ of an eye
because of which I'm thinking of an eye
and doing all of this without leapsing,
without either jumping too much
onto the external notion of the eyes
or thinking of, you know,
is this eyes in me, I am basically.
You're able to see both ends
without kind of sort of snapping towards one,
if the mindfulness is developed
to the extent necessary basically.
Like, you know, like a rubber band,
sort of you stretch yourself,
well, it's either going to sort of snap
from this end or from this end.
You won't be able to kind of include both ends.
And both ends are included through development,
through discernment of enduring
endurance of the simultaneous theories
and two things, right?
Basically, it's a simultaneous present.
For that, you basically need mindfulness,
without mindfulness, you cannot do anything.
Just impossible.
Because mindfulness does not necessarily bring knowledge
unless you know where you're supposed to know.
But certainly, without it,
there is absolutely no basis for any discernment.
But if you already have discernment,
then all you need is the practice of mindfulness.
And satipatana is enough for somebody
who developed you.
That's the only way that will lead to
full purification of the being
and anything else.
Here's a good describe.
Because what else would lead to the full purification?
No, no, no.
Then just sticking to that clear vision
and developing it to the extent necessary.
What I've thought about from time
is the assumption of that something,
I think it's in context of what Nanda says,
the eye is that in the world,
which my specific theory,
there is always a assumption that, you know,
there is vision,
but there's also behind that.
Sure.
You assume that spatiality.
That's what it ends up with.
The assumption is the spatial kind of being.
I am here and things are elsewhere.
So you can't stop that.
But when you do have such thoughts,
you start including them
in that proper mindfulness of knowing
that all of that is possible
because there is the actual operating flesh of an eye.
That you also know at the time
that you're thought in regard to it.
But it's an accurate thought
because it doesn't consume it anymore
as that hidden entity in the hidden place.
In my mind,
because if I was studying Nanda here,
it's kind of the explanation of the body
and that's one letter we're doing in the height of it,
it's kind of things.
And that's the thing
that we've given first experience of the whole.
And then within that,
you discern that here and the younger people
prioritize the here and the younger that are seeing there.
Yeah, and then when they think of there,
they think in some terms
of like a third of the younger,
they think of that level.
Instead of seeing that both are possible
because there is already there.
And that's the basis of an unknown that there.
That's it to get so off
and this can seem too pretty.
Oh, very neat.
It's possible to see.
You can see it.
Yeah.
Thanks for my hot seat method.
We need you to, I remember.
And you're according to the sutra.
Yeah.
And by using as a breathing,
watching, watching breaths,
you can, you know that the body is there.
This is, this breath is happening.
Yeah.
You can.
That's why the body, the breathing is,
it's kind of symptomatic.
It's bound with body.
It's just inconceivable,
one without the other.
It can't feel.
Yeah.
The body is there.
The breathing is there.
But they're not the same thing.
Yeah.
And then that body.
It is just looking at one aspect of the body.
Well, the breathing is there,
then that body can be manifested as the body,
as the healing, as the thoughts are,
as any other thing,
within the principle of two symptoms,
they need to present things,
while you're breathing.
Yeah.
So you can focus on the body aspect of breathing.
But still not see the actual relationship.
But yeah.
But you can keep focusing on that breath,
but you've got to see that relationship.
Yeah.
That's why it's there.
It's a successful body.
Yeah.
It's completely unnecessary to be focusing on anything.
But yeah.
It actually takes your way.
Yeah.
But just, you can use the breath as one of those things.
You can just...
Stereas.
They're breathing at once.
Yeah.
It's like the intention to bring in a mindfulness
in the actual,
or actual breathing.
Yeah.
And if you look at the intention to breathe so much,
the intention is there.
Yeah.
But this particular...
Miles.
Yeah.
And so it's beyond mind control.
Or this...
This...
Pleasurable.
Yeah.
Experience.
Breath.
By the presence of this.
The feeling of this.
Yeah.
What is that?
Yeah. That's how you start including your volition.
But that's volition.
And it doesn't start introducing the ignorance.
Because volition usually comes from the center.
So it feels...
So when we will,
we engage in the center self.
But I choose to breathe slowly,
because I think that's already there.
It's actually to give a possibility,
based on the simultaneously present and breathing.
That's possible.
So you...
I choose to...
And then you realize that I choose to...
It's already because of that.
So then you stop it here and do it.
As mine.
It's fiction.
I went from my mind to this.
When you say, like,
there is control and a lack of control.
Yeah.
I think I can choose how to...
I can choose how to breathe.
The old thing, I can't choose.
And the breathing is possible.
Yeah.
And when you fully get rid of the slightest assumption
of control outside of the lack of control
to a tiny degree or something,
then you fully stop the assumption
of an external entity that controls it.
But it seems that that agent said that
there is not necessarily for this sense of self.
Because it can be completely paralyzed
and still consider you're willing to be...
You're willing.
Yeah.
The will of the mind.
That's ultimately mind.
Speak fully.
That's how the will of life is.
That's why the action,
the three-time selection.
So you can be paralyzed,
but it can still be very much willing.
Ah-ha.
Having a mind,
and perpetuating the same type of mistake.
Just to the self.
But it just won't plan anything.
Sure.
Because as this stops being usable,
because it can't.
But it still won this early.
That's why a parallel expression
does not automatically become an error.
Yeah.
Because you remain ignorant
just on a different level now.
You cannot express your ignorance
in a bodily way in the past.
But if you want to speak...
If you want to move their eyes
and procreate that.
Sure.
Even if the only thing you say,
you lose everything.
You won't result in the bond.
You will result in the rebirth of another
being affecting the religion.
So you need to do that while you are alive.
Get the mind out of that.
Self-centrements are discrete.
That sense of error.
And then the river can also affect you.
Even this is suicide.
You can't actually kill.
You can't.
Yes, so for an argument.
Like for example, he can't kill himself.
Yeah.
Only acts.
He's sort of...
is to prevent body from trying to exist.
But that's not a suicide.
Suicide is when the self-centre person
well, attention to kill himself.
And kill themselves by killing the body.
Yeah.
Because you can't kill yourself directly.
You can just kill your body
and then you wait for death to come.
Yeah, that's what it is.
You can just make the body dysfunctional.
But then the death of the body
comes from the complete direction
of you and you don't have access to it.
Yeah, sure.
Like you don't even...
Yeah, exactly.
That's why you kill the body
hoping that that will result in death
because that's what you see in heavens.
But when death does come,
it doesn't come from the way of...
you kill the body.
It comes from the way of the mind.
That's what that is.
It comes from way behind.
So let's speak.
That's what conclusions are always swept
with the death.
Like always swept through the flood.
Swept.
I mean, it just comes from behind
and takes you where you're going to see it.
But for another one who has developed
that direction of death,
that direction of...
not adhering to anything,
seeing... seeing impermanence
and everything, basically,
seeing that nothing is his,
when things do get swept away,
he's not there to be swept with it.
And he has absolutely
inconceivable to fear death
because it's not death for him.
You think it is as we can try,
but because it's...
And I think that's what you work
and show their last...
however...
A terrible problem.
Yeah.
And also, yeah, that's another assumption
that, you know, when you see somebody,
I don't know,
they're shocked in the head
and anything at their dead.
Their body is gone
in terms of its functionality.
But from their point of view,
mentally, death,
might be lasting much, much longer.
Once the body is killed,
that's what death sets.
And we all assume,
automatically,
based on the observation
that it's instantaneous.
But whenever the Buddha wants
to emphasize that,
that the extensive pains,
he would say,
pains like those of dying
or death.
And then he would say,
oh, okay, yeah.
Probably it's one thing
that body dies instantaneously.
And once that happens,
then the experience of death begins.
And it's horrible.
Respect for the mind that...
It's here.
It looks at the mass of your life.
There is the feeling that
you're living with breathing,
and there is another feeling
that you're living with the body.
Right.
Yeah, I don't remember that.
But you still breathing,
but still alive.
Right, right, right, right.
Yeah, sure.
Sure, sure.
I feel of feeling terminated
of life first and then.
Yes, you're right.
You're right.
Are you?
Yes, you're right.
Oh, they're very, very good.
And then this life itself.
And that's the one that can last
for probably quite a while.
Okay, imagine part of your brain
something on the floor,
and still feeling...
So you have been sort of withdrawn
from, because it was destroyed,
the past six cents a base.
Except, you don't have these
excesses anymore.
Yeah.
Of eyes, nose, and stuff.
Now, you're just being sort of
crushed from everywhere, basically.
The mind is dying in itself, down here.
And, you know, there's another suit
where it says, like, that the suit
upon a based on his insight,
he can become an other hunt.
Again, that's commentary
at the moment of death,
like the mind moment of death.
The moment of death,
it's the extent of the experience of death
that can endure.
For how long?
Well, you don't know.
Yeah.
So sort of going to keep you coming
out of hand during that time,
which now, when you think about it,
makes sense, actually.
Because it's all instantaneous.
It's a period of complete,
crushing destruction of the five
upgrades that he has full understanding of.
What's going to result in full dispassion?
There is nowhere for him to adhere
to distract himself from.
All he has left is his right view.
So he can easily become an other hunt
in the moment of death.
He said, if he doesn't become an
other hunt while he's dying, basically.
Mentally, he can become an
other hunt while he's in interval.
When he's neither there nor born yet.
Then he can become an
other hunt.
The third type is upon landing.
That was a translation.
And he can become an other hunt
in that next life,
or then eventually in the seven lives.
So you realize it's not seven.
He can become an other hunt in any time.
Up to seven.
Yeah, up to seven.
But these kind of intervals
in between, and stuff,
you realize this whole notion of
I'm alive, I'm alive.
The moment of death, I'm born again,
die, born again.
The interval can be an event
before you're born again.
Hence the sense of urgency.
You have no idea how long you'll be dying.
You've had a very long time.
There is that kind of assumption
that it's like, you know,
like people speculate about
like reverence,
like someone died in 1973.
Even born in 1973.
It might have been the rebirth
of that person.
Sure.
No, it's fully based
on a gratuitous,
based on an external perception
of death,
the kind of just switching of the body.
That's it.
Because that's all you can see.
And you never experience
yourself differently
to be able to tell
that actually it's not just that.
Yeah, it's in the similar way
like it's being born.
You cannot really say
when the person is born.
You can't say that.
You can't.
You only know that someone
is pregnant
and then somebody comes out.
And consciousness is already pregnant.
Because imagine like
in a medical school, you know,
like in a Czech Republic,
the abortion is legal up to three months.
Yeah, it's the usual.
But imagine if it's actually
it's a real human being.
It is.
And you are just the whole life
sitting down as a doctor.
The thing is,
that the Chinese friend of yours,
yeah, he must have it.
But the thing is like,
even though, say,
even if you're not,
because the Buddha said
when the human being
does kind of descend,
which is when embryo is born.
Yeah.
So already the conceiving of embryo
means conceiving of life.
Yes.
They dismiss that because
it's just an embryo,
it's a cell.
So they can arbitrarily decide,
or three months,
it's a however,
even when you do abortion of a fetus
or for one month or two,
you are cutting a body inside.
That's how they do abortion.
You start chopping it inside
and then pulling parts
two months.
So it's not a fetus form,
yet you still see
little arms and stuff.
Or recognize,
this is an arm.
This would have been an arm
in a week.
It's already an arm.
So even people who kind of
medically sort of thought
that you have a certain
heavy amount of denial
that this is just,
this is not the way
being I'm killing.
It's after the third month
that it becomes alive.
It's completely stupid.
It's terrible.
I think they focus on the,
you know,
it's the one,
like we were giving women
the choice aspect.
Sure.
They focus on like,
oh, this is my job.
I just do that.
It's on my phone.
Yeah.
Where they give their justifications
of, oh, you know, this person
with great tiredness,
pregnantness,
immoral kind of abortion.
Yeah.
You can even kind of
sympathize with it almost.
Yeah.
But you can be quite a serious
killer.
I'd be like,
a hundred and a hundred.
So, yeah.
Yeah.
Boy, Chinese children.
They're one child.
They're one child policy.
Yeah.
And the story.
So you imagine how many they
get pregnant a second time?
Yeah.
She was doing like,
in the height of some days,
or something,
ridiculous, like,
I have a memory of saying
thirty in one day.
Thirty a day.
They say it was ten.
And in a month.
You can say,
you killed 300 people.
Imagine that coming.
And she said,
she would sleep at night
and just have,
with visions of,
after one,
blood.
Right.
And this.
She said, no,
but it's okay.
Because they do it
chanting after.
So all the notes,
as they get together,
for each mother,
who's chanting.
Like, somebody's chanting
and they go,
what's next?
But they know.
Very well.
Like, this is something
wrong.
That's why they're chanting.
Yeah.
So, you're singing about
300 people.
Thousands, thousands.
One after a year.
Yeah.
Oh, it's quite.
And the Christians
in America,
some,
wrongly,
but they still recognize it.
It's not a good thing
that they go too far.
They would kill the abortion.
Yeah, they killed the doctors.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
I'm reading about it.
You get the bombings
of it instead.
She was.
In the name of God's moral
will forever.
There it is.
And there it is.
Get all the more.
But it is, it is a,
it is a useful reflection as
well,
to stop associating death
with the death of the body.
And see something that comes
from the ultimate inside,
so to speak.
You can't,
in the same sense,
you can't conceive,
the sense organs,
the direction you can't access
them,
you're just because of them.
Well, death
speaks them.
It means you have no,
you can't,
you can't have a relationship
with death,
because it doesn't come
from any direction
that you can possibly conceive.
But you can also, basically,
you should,
basically we should say that,
you know, because it's
now my Rupa,
it goes together,
they die together.
So even if you like,
say the bullet comes
or goes through your head.
Yeah, that's not the only Rupa.
But there is the particular,
other parts of the body,
which I would say.
You don't have any parts of the body.
There is a body.
Yeah.
On the basis of the general Rupa.
On the basis of which,
they give you a consciousness.
Yeah.
So when this body is destroyed,
that's, there wasn't your body
upon which you were really existing.
There was just a more particular
manifestation of the form
upon which your consciousness was existing.
That's where you can transcend your body.
You can fly out of your body.
And that's why,
if you die with ignorance,
you get another body.
You get another particular manifestation
of the same form.
So that's another important thing.
The form that you depend upon now,
where you're bound with Rupa,
is the same one.
You depend upon previous life,
and previous life,
and previous life.
Despite having different bodies
and different particular forms,
the nature of the five aggregates
remains the same.
And the Buddha said that,
even if a monk recollects one past life,
he'll 500 of them,
or he recollects,
is these five aggregates,
or one among them more particularly.
But that's it.
That always remains the base.
And that's it, because again,
people think,
this is a journey.
You're just passing
from this life into the known.
This is always what's present,
has always been present.
In that other sense,
the five aggregates.
That's why you keep remaining,
being born.
Not because you keep traveling,
because you keep holding on to the same thing.
So now,
the stuff you're holding,
is the stuff you've been holding,
beginninglessly,
for billions of years of time.
And it's right here,
right now,
can be freed from.
In that sense,
it's a calica.
But again, people have the linear assumption
of death,
rebirth, elsewhere,
and this,
and it's a journey,
and you come to know,
it's right there.
That's why, if you stop associating death
with that kind of movement,
you realize,
ah, death, basically,
death doesn't take away the five aggregates.
It takes away your dependence
upon the particular manifestation of the senses
of the five aggregates and so on.
So what you have to do to be free from death,
but really,
is free yourself from your senses,
and then eventually,
from the conceit in regard to the ideas,
and you'll be free from death,
and you'll be free from rebirth.
From this very same present principle
that we were talking about,
of mindfulness and simultaneous presence.
It's not, you know,
above it,
or below, or later,
or before.
And that's how you cannot possibly
be affected when illness affects the body,
breaking apart,
death,
loss of limbs,
loss of senses,
which is,
because you are not in that particular manifestation of it, you know.
That's why I also,
when we were talking about it,
there were the madness.
Like,
if the body starts
losing the balances
and doing things that are not,
the weird is that,
you wouldn't have personal problem with it,
because it's not yours.
If there was wisdom,
there was knowledge properly established,
you just, like,
without a jar like,
oh, honey,
you're actually not making sense.
You stopped engaging in that kind of outlet or speech.
It's not,
it's not yours to begin with,
so it's not an issue.
So you couldn't possibly be denying it
or having a problem with it,
if everybody says,
oh, that's, that's, yeah,
yeah, that's how this body is acting now.
And can this happen to other half?
Well, I think that,
well, like, say,
loses mind,
how do you,
look like a mad person?
I think theoretically,
it could,
yeah,
but that doesn't mean,
what,
what it can never be compromised,
like externally,
he could be mad,
and say that man disappears
and people tell him he was mad,
yeah,
he would probably already know that,
and he wouldn't have an issue,
again, same with other child,
he didn't realize
because of the stroke,
he was thinking one thing,
he was thinking he was saying one thing,
he was saying something completely different,
completely,
but there should be,
like,
in that I had some emotions
should be missing,
like fear or,
all of that is missing.
He cannot be afraid,
he cannot suffer,
he's absolutely fine,
because he's not afraid of death.
He's not afraid of death.
How can you be afraid of losing
the speech mind
and bodily activities?
He cannot be his concern.
Well, he cannot lose,
is that purified,
freed point of view?
So even if madness
becomes his reality,
basically,
but even that reality
is equally affected
with non-Avija,
he's fully understood.
So he might not be able
to express it anymore
because the speech is
slurring,
the chemicals in brain,
they were helping perception,
just don't work anymore,
just perceiving things differently,
and stuff.
There is his reality.
But still, he would not engage
like an animal,
some activities,
basically,
attacking people
or being aggressive
or disfigured.
He would be just mad,
and...
What is it?
It depends.
I don't know.
Because aggressive behavior
is not necessarily
the sign of real will.
Yeah.
But the more serious issue,
it's not aggressive behavior,
it's denial
of when these things
were pointed out,
it's that kind of almost
conceited refusal.
No.
I cannot get mad.
I'm not mad.
That's an issue.
Yes.
Even if he was punching people
in the face before that,
then we're not necessarily
being an issue.
In the same sense,
there was that other hand
who was like,
oops.
Like the whole province
got upset in monks
because he was rude,
really abrasive,
telling people off,
just calling other monks,
shavelings,
just horrible,
and people complained
to the Buddha.
And they would have called them.
He was a big issue,
and then the Buddha
saw he was actually an
other hand,
fully enlightened.
But he was reborn,
he had the habit,
basically.
He was reborn like
over 500 lifetimes
in a high ground in February.
But I think he was not
so rude actually.
I read that story.
He was only called them
like a...
Well, no.
That's what the story
would always condense
the meaning as he called
them shavelings.
But you can imagine,
if the point came
when the whole area
complained to the Buddha,
and the Buddha had to call
him for that.
Like, he wouldn't
have like one man
got upset.
You call him in sharing
and then the Buddha
saw on him and said,
no, he was a big issue
because he was going
around doing it.
Yes.
And people said,
no, the kind of monk
is that.
So you can extrapolate,
relatively accurately,
that actually was probably
many ways.
But then the Buddha said,
no, he was just
he was used to talking
down to people.
But I can't understand.
But he was doing it
without a real will.
How he can punch
someone in the face of the
Buddha.
No, I just said that in theory.
No, no, no.
Like, you madness.
Like, you really,
you don't, the way your
perception goes messed up
with the chemicals
in your brain and
everything else,
you don't necessarily perceive
him as a human anymore.
And you hit him.
Oh.
Hit it.
And then afterwards,
they tell you,
you punched this monk
in the face.
You would not be denying.
That's my whole heart.
Yes.
Like a transparent person,
which is the basis of
wisdom, transparency,
is mindfulness,
will not be denying it.
Even if the most horrible
stuff, so to speak,
you wouldn't be able to
deny it.
Yes.
And you wouldn't have a
reason to deny it,
because it's not personal.
Yes.
It's not personal.
That's why,
that's why you wouldn't,
you know, you don't have,
that's our heart,
is as in private,
so in public,
in terms of his behavior.
He has no, like,
oh, this is really good.
You know, when people
sometimes are that
regard personally,
some weird stuff.
It's actually so big
about it.
It's nothing personal.
Like, you need to hide
about it.
Why would you be hiding that?
Yes.
And most people do.
Most people,
like, like,
lay people out there,
have a lot of stuff
like that.
Yes.
That it's kind of, you know,
why?
Because it's taken personally.
That's the sole reason.
So that's more of an issue.
Yes.
Not the actual
manifestation of behavior,
because you know,
even in the,
in the rules,
often,
if somebody is possessed
with the madness,
he's exempted.
Exactly.
Yeah.
Which means he could have done
serious offenses,
but he was a genuine
madness.
Yeah.
Means he wasn't his
intention of doing.
That's funny.
Yeah, except, say, if he does
something like
women, rapes,
rapes of women,
that is.
He's not purergic,
because he needs
a man.
He's completely mad,
yeah.
His last thought,
sense of, like,
so his point of view
was not involved.
Yeah.
So to speak,
his individual was not
possessed.
But,
if when that's done,
he's just this full-on,
you know,
rude or aggressive denial,
and like,
no, no,
high and beyond all of that,
then he's just like,
well, not that.
Now, that's not
meant speaking,
because it shows,
basically, some
thinking is done.
At some notion,
at some idea of yourself,
and that's the definition
of conceit.
I don't know.
Well, even if you say,
you know,
like people say,
you're mad,
you can't agree
on the terminology,
well, I wasn't mad,
he was yak as possessed,
my mind.
Who's made me see those things?
But if people say,
well, yeah,
you were mad,
you wouldn't be arguing the
point.
Okay, yeah.
That's how you can
call madness, sure.
But he wasn't.
He doesn't affect
your personal image,
unless there is an
image that you hope
personally.
Yeah.
Yeah, he was
shitting,
pissing himself,
that's the whole point.
The point
of being yours.
Because, you know,
it can happen to anyone
anytime.
Yeah.
Absolutely.
I'm not sure that
tomorrow you will not
Well, always,
you get that
cephalitis,
and you start
really turning into
completely different person.
But your point of view,
can ever go down
if he has the
relevant wisdom,
because it's independent
of the content,
of the quickness
of the intellect.
That's what my opponent
says.
You can be, you can
become stupid,
you can have a stroke,
you can also think,
and that dimension,
you know,
remains completely
unaffected.
Yeah.
Because if I was,
you know, being rough
as people in my 30
years of my life,
maybe before that,
it had a
strong,
but then, you know,
okay, I can't
down with it,
I can't mind it.
And these things
got, you know,
they got
something in mind that
had my team back in.
Sure.
Because it's been done
much longer.
Okay.
Yeah.
That's just the way it's
been.
But as I said,
the point of view
that has been purified,
that it has no
will there,
or lost around
it.
Yes.
Is the relationship
of, like, with the eyes,
for example, you know,
I can think of,
an image of my eye,
kind of thing.
I assume it applies
just at a much more
subtle level
to the monolendama
that gives me
a monolendama.
You can think of
some vague
notion of what
is my,
like,
it's a sense
of an image of a brain.
Well, my
there's a sense
where it's defined by
the dharma that you're
thinking.
So it's a negative
in regard to that particular
thing.
So it's, yeah,
it's the same.
So then, when you do have a
thought about the negative
particular thing,
but you realize that there is
a negative in particular
that thought.
So you want to make sure
that the thought
about your mind,
itself, as,
actually, this is
what the mind is.
I'm mind,
and this,
you don't confuse
yourself that you're
thinking about,
because it's
another thought.
Exactly.
So that's what you have
to do.
It's not like to figure it
out,
or to catch it,
just to stop
misconceiving it.
That's the whole point
of the whole monolabarianism.
So maybe we can only say
that mind is only that
which can think
thoughts.
That's exactly why,
yeah, that's why
you can free your mind
because it's there
anyway, anyhow,
on its own,
by itself,
that's exactly the reason
why you can
equilibrate it.
It's like, you know,
if you can, you know,
you can kind of say
that anyone, you know,
is here,
things are yonder,
like, yeah, sure,
but then you go
to the mind,
and they kind of
just assume it's all
true.
There is no yonder
in the mind.
Yeah, that's the confusion
really.
Stop.
They're thinking
at that level.
Yeah.
But they're here
and yonder in the mind,
too.
Yeah.
You need more negative
to anything else in the sense
of it.
That's why you can
see if the
thinker,
like, you can see the
seeer, you can see
the hearer.
And that's exactly why,
even if your senses
are taken away from you,
they're conceived to the
remains.
This is perhaps
going a little bit
away from, you know,
a dama principle
thing.
But I think it's
interesting and important
to think about just
because of how
often it's brought up,
is, you know,
the mind,
it's not to say it, like, you
know, people
are studying neuro
chemistry, great.
But it's not to say
that it's like,
there is no
effect on particular things
because of things
in the range
that people go
to far and assume that
else is just a
manifestation of the
brain.
People go to far
basically and then
they describe their
point of view and their
responsibility to that
in the brain.
And that's not the
case.
The results, the
chemicals in the brain
can present you
with things.
But it's a new
basically to keep maintaining
ignorance in regard to
the reason things
or knowledge in regard
to the same.
Same with the eye,
it is, it is, it is,
then chemicals
in hormones.
Yeah.
But people say that
as if, like, oh,
it's because of it,
nothing has
happened.
Yeah.
We say that
correlation is not
causation.
Cozation.
Yeah.
It's definitely
correlated.
I was thinking back
the days when I
used to take antidepressants
things.
Yeah.
I can kind of say I
just, like, things presented
themselves, you know, perhaps
more pleasing way
and fundamentally do
anything.
No, exactly.
Exactly.
That's why you can't
treat depression
as a state of mind.
Yeah.
So then you can make
choices.
They will take you out
of depression.
But that's not how
my business presented.
It's presented as treatment
all such and such states.
And you can't do that.
One last one for me,
is this, because I've read it
so many times, and I just
never really
entered it.
There's a lot of times
in the suitors, or it's
like that, but I've
mentioned that he and his
disciples, like, they
don't get arguments
in quarrels in terms of
in terms of views and stuff like that, especially in the new suit and hip-hop, the transition that comes up a lot like, you know, I'm gaining and disputes and stuff.
I'm having trouble, like, I guess, understanding that, what are the same to understand that there is right things and wrong things.
No, that refers to his disciples, which means he refers to the noble disciples. So that's the point, basically.
They might be disagreeing in a particular explanation or description of something.
But fundamentally, if these two people both are taking the right view, they will have to agree.
So it's like an internal, that external kind of thing.
Well, no, even externally, it cannot result in an external, you know what I'm saying?
Like, not getting into, like, an argument from random ramen with weird views.
Oh, yeah, I think, I don't know. You read it yourself, but I thought it's referring to the internal.
To the actual, his disciples among himself are not arguing like other sects.
Because you see that in other suitors when they praise, and I see all these disciples always in Concord always sort of sharing the same views and taking it.
Unlike when I go there, they're arguing, attacking the teacher, and I say this, you say that.
You have the book here.
But you know, I don't know what's the impression I've got.
But either way, either way. They cannot argue among themselves.
Right.
If they have a right view, nor will they go into an actual dispute with somebody else on account of it, impossible.
Like, if another person comes, asks, he gives a speech, they disagree.
Like, it's absolutely not my problem, and certainly not me.
Or nothing that I need to defend will convince you.
Like, always, even when the Buddha was teaching something, there's like, no, they would check their head in disapproval and say, well, yes, okay, must go down my go.
And the Buddha couldn't care less.
So, while he says, ah, he didn't accept what I said. He didn't believe me.
And then he would go to another people who can't approve his view.