So what was the idea?
Well, maybe I'll start with a question and see where it takes us.
What is, how would you describe in its content, a thought?
The images of...
Of what?
Of things that I've seen, or that I've perceived.
And images of perception.
Okay, so what is the... and perceptions?
How do you then know perceptions?
What is a perception in its content?
In its content.
Yeah.
Or what you've seen, things that I've seen.
In particular, types of science.
So let's look at something.
What do we have here?
Take a measure.
So you're looking at a tape measure.
What is in its content, of your sight?
The shape, the colour.
What is the shape?
Colour in the content.
What is the shape, the designation?
Shape, shape, colour, colour.
What is that, in your mind?
Well, in image, I suppose it's the closest thing I can...
Sure?
It's a...
Yeah, that's fine.
We can call it an image.
So it's an image.
So then, is your perception an image?
An actual perception?
Is this also an image?
In your mind?
Yeah.
It's a different type.
It's not as...
What's the difference?
What would you mean, different type?
It would look like if I'm imagining a major tape.
Sure, okay.
And then when I'm seeing one, it's a different quality.
But what is in common?
What is in common to the sight of a tape measure?
And now, to your thought of it.
What is in common?
The thought.
Sure.
But what is the content of the thought then?
Like, because you have an abstract thought, a natural thought, theoretical, clear, ambiguous...
Why do they all have in common?
Why do all thoughts have in common?
They have thoughts.
But in terms of the content, why do they all have in common?
What is the common characteristic of all the thoughts?
Why do they all have?
You said it.
What are the images?
They have an image.
Literally, an image.
So the thought and the image is different?
Well, I'm trying to clarify it here
in the sense that image is like specific.
It's within a thought.
So you can't have thoughts without images.
But images are more precise thoughts, so to speak.
So you can call them thoughts, dummies.
You can call them phenomena.
Images of content.
But that's the thing.
You don't start with a pure recognition of image as a content.
You start with heavy concepts of abstract thoughts, ideas, designations.
So you need to make the effort through those ideas and designations
to discern a certain enduring container of an image,
which is what gives the identity to a thought as a thought.
So that's what I mean.
Thought is a more broader application of the term,
but more specifically images.
So can you say something has manifested?
Yeah, those are the characteristics of images.
Exactly, that's what I was going to say.
I can only know that because there's some image there.
Exactly.
So that's what I'm saying.
In the same sense, in the previous talk,
we spoke about the resisting aspect of your thought.
That's what images are,
because you have no say in how things appear to you,
in how it manifested.
Yet that is an image upon which you can think further and further and further.
So yeah, you said correctly,
in a way there is a difference between you imagining your images
and you perceiving,
but there is also the common ground to it.
And that common ground is not an external relation.
That common ground is a necessary container for both.
You wouldn't be able to think this particular day measuring if you've never seen it.
And you've never seen it if you've never had an image in mind of it.
That's why you can sometimes not see it,
but I can describe it to you,
and then you can see it and recognize it as the same thing,
because it's the same basis of the same images.
And any difference in my description and what you saw,
if the difference is not sufficient for you to doubt the identity of the thing,
or if you don't realize, oh no, that's the thing he was talking about.
Now I understand it correctly now.
So perceptions and imagination are mental images.
So whether you perceive,
whether you imagine images are there.
So in other words,
perception is basically images of the senses,
and imagination is images upon the images.
But you wouldn't say that an image represents what an image represents?
No, absolutely not.
Because that assumes that you can even conceive rightly
that from which my perception came about.
And how can you know that unless you're perceiving it?
Which means how can you perceive what comes before perception?
So this is before my perception.
That's an assumption.
That's an assumption of the external world.
That's how you allow the footing for the matter.
Because it's because of the matter that you perceive.
But see when you're thinking, oh, that's the real matter?
No, you can only perceive it,
which means you can only perceive your perception,
and then you get to assume the matter behind.
So would you say a feeling is an image?
Yes, everything, the manifest is an image,
on the level of manifestation.
And that's why I wanted to use the word image,
not the word thought,
because then people say,
ah, so only when I think it, it's real?
No.
You can only think something if the images are there.
And you don't have to think it.
You can just look at it.
And that's the common ground
that probably many people would struggle to find
between senses, as in the physical and the mental.
Because it's usually the senses,
and now I'm in my thoughts as a result of it.
No.
Whether my thoughts, images are there,
perceptual images are there,
that's why it's on the level of perception,
images as well.
So say somebody,
not mindful that they're kind of,
not really thinking about what they're doing,
but they're doing something,
aiming at towards something.
So that thing that they're aiming at,
they're actually aware of what it is they're aiming at.
But it's still present as an image.
Yeah.
It's just not something that they're actually going on.
That's the thing that I'm...
Yeah, exactly.
I don't know what I want.
That's the images you're having in mind.
Yeah.
You have a vague, ambiguous direction.
I don't know what I want,
but clearly you're doing something about it in some way,
which means you have some sense.
So whatever, a sense, a thought,
ambiguous idea, abstract theory,
actual perception of sight, sound, smell, taste, touch,
images are there.
Because literally,
Dhamma could be translated as an image,
a phenomenon, an image,
a thing, yeah.
So, would you say
the image is also, like,
what's designated, the designation
of whatever it is that's manifested.
So something's there,
it's designated in some way, that's the image.
That's already the beginning of your designation, sure.
Yeah.
Okay.
Can you have an image without a color of it?
No.
Exactly.
So that's why the Buddha described perception
in its fundamental terms.
He perceives yellow, white, blue,
white, red.
That's it.
But you can have an image without flavor,
sound, smell.
Sure, you can.
But you can't have an image without a color,
without space.
Without space, exactly.
That's why you can use space practically
to summon the senses.
You can have an image without a touch.
Yeah, I suppose.
It's like, there's not much you can designate,
not much difference in designate between the touch.
Your first point of touch is the first point of resistance,
which is this body as a whole.
So the image will then stand for that,
but it's not what you can describe about that.
But if you want to describe the characteristic of an image,
yeah, it has to be color, it has to be shape,
which means it has to have space,
it has to be off-space.
It has to be sound.
Not really.
So if I have an image of a taste,
I have the image of a taste,
the experience of a taste,
there's something salty.
Yeah, can you imagine?
Saltyness without color.
Yeah, you can.
Can you imagine color without saltiness?
You can.
Because the senses also, they're not linear.
The whole arrangement,
the material arrangement of the sense organs,
is such.
It has its own arrangement.
They're not all on the same field, so to speak,
on the same level ground.
So, but can you also, can you even,
can you imagine saltiness
without tasting it?
Like you can have, you can have the idea of saltiness,
but it's already quite secondary.
But you can imagine blue,
and it will go all the way to the point of the image,
whatever.
You can imagine yellow.
Literally, you have an image of yellow in your mind.
But saltiness, without tasting,
you're not tasting it in your mouth.
You can be hoping to taste it,
but it's going to be more on the level of a secondary concept.
Because you'll be really, when you imagine saltiness,
you're imagining yourself eating some salty food,
which is more like images of colors and shapes
that you're consuming.
They then get to taste like this.
You're going to say salt is in white.
Sure.
So the perception of salt is experienced through the eye.
Well, that's why the kind of,
the obsession is, sorry,
the perception of the image of tastes.
The image of tastes.
So not the perception of tastes.
In a way, yes.
Not specifically through the eye,
but you could say through the mental eye.
There has to be an image there.
Even if you were like blind your whole life,
you will have to have an image of your experience
as a whole of consuming some object in your mouth
as producing the salty taste for you.
But you can't imagine the pure saltiness in itself.
But that's beside the point now,
how these particular senses, which comes first,
doesn't matter.
Whichever way they come,
an image has to be there.
And if people were confused
why would you be describing the perception
in terms of colors, these images,
it's because, yeah, that's what it would boil down to.
And you can describe it also in terms of space.
That's where space is sometimes listed
as one of the elements.
It's not a fundamental element,
like four Mahabutas,
but it's out there with consciousness
and other Mahabutas,
so like the six elements.
So you said, why everything,
every image has a color?
First, every image is.
Because now when you think every image has a color,
they're saying color, it's another image for you.
So what you're really saying is
every image has an image.
And that's true,
but that's not practically accurate.
So there is an image
within which you discern the properties of color,
characteristics of it being manifested.
So think space.
When I say space,
what image is present in your mind?
Space, space.
What's present in your mind?
Well, something clear.
Something clear.
When I say space,
what's present in my mind is the word space,
literally.
OK.
Written word space is what's present in my mind.
But yeah, whatever.
I was thinking expansive, sort of.
The point is there has to be an image.
There has to be an image.
If I say, I don't know,
a term in another language
that you don't understand,
you still have to have an image in your mind
on the basis of sound
that I just produced at you.
You will have an image of
what does that mean?
Is this gibberish or this particular language
or you will have to have some image always.
There is no such thing as an imageless mind,
unless neither perception or perception and so on.
OK.
Even space, basis of infinite space
is basis of infinite image.
Yeah.
Image of infiniteness of space.
But both narrowly, even if you're not,
there's something's gone.
There's an image.
Within that image,
you will discern various perceptions.
Well, within that image,
you'll discern the five senses.
Within that image,
you'll discern more images.
you'll discern your intentions.
Yeah.
So there's a kind of
a sort of starting image,
which is basically the image of this experience.
Yeah.
And the starting image does not disappear
when the second thing comes in.
The starting image remains as a primary soul,
only container in which
you can't be outside of it.
That's where the mind comes first.
The image comes first.
So primary image.
You're thinking there's a side of this image
that isn't yours?
There's another image.
Within this image.
That image is what experiences are.
Sorry?
Experience as a whole.
Yeah.
Of course.
That's what the image looks like.
Experience as a whole.
When I say,
imagine your experience as a whole.
Or don't imagine your experience as a whole.
Come back to the body.
Be here now.
Present.
Be present moment.
What is present with you
in the most acute sense?
You are not specifically looking, looking well.
I might be doing,
if I'm doing some sort of meditation technique,
but if I'm not falling into that trap,
and so you just want to be present,
what is the closest thing to you?
It's an image of this experience.
That is a whole thing.
This experience.
So that's the point.
You can't really have anything other than that,
even if you want to.
But the problem is when you have images,
yet here you are,
thinking you're observing the actual form.
You think you're observing the matter,
the reality behind.
You think you're observing physical sensations and whatnot.
All you're observing is images enduring,
on account of which you end up
misconceiving those images as matter,
misconceiving those images as feelings,
as perceptions, as intentions,
as basically,
misconceiving the aggregates.
Or rather, conceiving the aggregates,
giving them the being,
assuming them, appropriating them.
Think about me, myself.
Can you even think that without an image?
A certain degree,
a certain independence of that aspect,
of that thought I am.
There's a certain shape to it,
but usually gets associated with your own face.
It's like veiled in the background,
but the point is an image is there.
It doesn't matter how ambiguous,
how subtle,
image has to be there.
And not being trained in regard to those images
means not being trained in regard to your mind.
And that's how you will always then be governed
by the kind of these assumed directions
that these images take you.
Image of my face means me, I am,
my control, master, owner,
appropriator, all that's implied.
Not seeing it, you took it upon yourself.
So leave your mind blank.
What is that?
You can.
It's another image.
So yeah, it's not truly blank.
Because, well,
how can you even designate blankness
unless it's absence of something else,
which is then an image present in your mind
in regard to this,
which is absence of that image?
Think about the empty room.
Yeah, well, yeah.
So see, that's the whole,
the sign of emptiness
that the Buddha was talking about.
Imagine when you go into the empty hut
and you realize this place
is empty of other people.
So it's actually factually perceiving an image
of absence of others.
Fully develop that image and then apply to yourself.
Oh, so so is this experience as a whole
in its entirety.
This image is absent of persons.
That's it.
Because you clarified the sign of emptiness,
the characteristics of emptiness,
means you see there's a clear image.
Now you see it also pertaining
to your own experience as a whole.
It's not empty, empty, just space out
and joules sort of us out unconscious.
No, it's empty of this.
This experience is empty of lust.
It's empty of aversion.
It's empty of delusion.
So if I say emptiness,
what's present in mind?
Emptiness.
What image is there?
Well, nothingness.
Okay, so what are the characteristics of nothingness?
Empty.
What is the characteristic of empty space?
So then the space is there.
So there is a certain container,
but it's empty.
So things that...
Things could be in there.
Yeah, but the point is,
so things that are making the space empty
are there as absence,
as a negative presence.
Because if there is nothing that could be in there,
you wouldn't say this is empty or so.
It would just be this is so.
So the nothingness of what then?
Nothingness.
When I ask you emptiness,
what do you say?
Oh, nothingness.
I say, well, what is the characteristic of nothingness?
Okay, characteristic is empty space.
Empty of what?
That space? Empty of what?
What is the absence in that space,
in that nothingness?
That comes to your mind when I keep repeating
nothingness, nothingness, nothingness, nothingness.
Well, there's not this...
the absence of something.
Absence of something, well,
but that's already something, isn't it?
Nothingness.
What I said is something.
So you can't say it's absence of something,
because then it's not absence of itself.
So more specifically, nothingness,
or emptiness, more accurately.
Empty of what?
Empty of everything else that's not there.
What are the characteristics of being empty?
Don't necessarily look for the...
It's empty of this, of this, of this.
Characteristics of being empty.
Can we just describe it?
It has to be kind of negative.
Exactly.
Negative presence, or presence of absence.
So it's well on the presence of absence.
Really empty.
It's not really empty, as in it's not really empty,
and you assume the external world of real absence of things,
which is inconceivable.
It's not really empty.
You can't even finish that sentence
if things were truly empty,
as in don't exist.
Emptiness is not non-existence.
It's only emptiness of certain things.
But people are used to, well,
not seeing the images in their mind,
and then just following the kind of
the positive directions of craving, pretty much.
You say something like it's a pure image.
Let's finish with this.
Okay.
So the point is emptiness.
It's an image in your mind.
Like you can even say,
when I say emptiness, I just have a word emptiness
written in my mind, big E.
Okay.
So what are the characteristics of something being empty?
You said, well, it's an empty space.
Okay.
Empty space is defined as an empty space
by absence of that which is empty of.
That is its characteristic.
That's what definition of emptiness is.
Doesn't matter what is empty of.
So it's a negative presence,
or presence of the absence of certain things.
Dwell on that image.
Presence of absence, basically.
It's not a contradiction because absence...
Is a thing.
Is a thing that is present.
So it's the content of that that's not there,
but the nature of absence is there.
What else does it matter?
The same principle in your experience then.
Yes, sense of ownership, sense of master controller,
because I am here, where?
What is the content of my sense of self?
Can you find it?
Can you find the content of what you are?
But you are.
It's always a negative.
So the absence of content is your presence.
And that's why sense of self is assumed in regard to everything and nothing.
But once you study...
Oh, so the absence...
Sorry, the presence of the absence is a real image.
I don't need to keep chasing content
and only to verify the image through finding the content.
No, it's other way around.
So by understanding the nature of emptiness
you get to understand the nature of anata.
And that's why this room is empty of others.
And his mind is established upon the perception of that image.
So is this body, these five aggregates,
are empty of the self as in the self master controller.
Empty.
So there is the sense of self that is the presence, absence of the owner.
Absence of the owner means non-ownership.
Doesn't mean there was never ever presence of the absent owner.
Sense of self is absent owner.
Not seeing it as an absent owner,
well, you get to then appropriate everything that you assume that self owns.
But you realize that self can only be the absence of the actual owner,
then yourself becomes not self, automatically.
So back onto the images then.
It's important to emphasize
your seeing, hearing, smelling, tasting, touching
would not be so unless it's already an image in itself.
Also, it's all in my mind then.
It's all in my thought.
That's an image that has a reason for it.
So images are neither in your head nor in the things.
It's just there in the middle.
Something is there.
Images are that manifestation, that arising that Buddha talks about.
That's what images are.
Within that you can discern now the direction, the content of the sense objects
or the absence of sense objects.
You can discern the content of further images in your mind
as in your own abstract thinking and so on.
And the crucial characteristic of these images is that
you don't create them.
No.
That's what I mean.
Based on the previous talk we've done about the aspect of resistance
in your thoughts, that's what images are.
That which resists already has some shape, already has some form.
So to speak, you wouldn't recognize if it wasn't.
Absolutely.
In some way, there was an image there.
Yeah, exactly.
It would not be known.
Resistance is already an image.
Yeah, exactly.
You cannot think of resistance and then the image resists.
No, resistance is an image.
Resistance is already a designation.
But there can't be an image.
Designation already resists.
Without resistance.
Exactly.
Either way, an image needs to be there.
So they're all equal footing those two.
They're not like one.
And you could see how it could perhaps make more sense then.
You could see how it could establish your mind upon the basis of infinite space.
The image of infinity, the actual resisting aspect of the thought of infinity, that is
what infinity is.
Fully understand it.
Fully invest effort in it.
As we said, fully develop theme of it.
As it fully discern the science of infinity, infinite space.
And then you'll be dwelling and abiding in it.
Whether you're walking, sitting, eating, lying down, going to toilet, your mind will be within
that container of infinity.
Meaning that you're including all...
Meaning that whatever comes to that will be inferior to it, as the Buddha would describe
it.
Being inferior to it, if you find it completely dispassionate about it, includes all resistance.
An image that includes all the other images you're used to.
Yeah.
So people usually swing between the two, like, I'm looking or I'm thinking.
I can't see anything in between.
So when you talk about images, these are thoughts.
But now this is the reality of my senses.
So you don't have to be excluding either.
You want to see what's in common to both.
When I have the experience of an image, when I have the experience of a sight, sound, smell, taste, touch.
The experience is, there's an image there that isn't present in, presently enduring on its own.
I just think it's like the whole philosophical tradition has been swinging.
Swinging between the empiricists who were saying the senses come first and then the rationalists
who were saying, no, no, no, the thoughts come first.
Senses and thoughts are only known because they're an image.
Yeah.
They appear as an image.
You're never seeing the middle ground, the middle way.
Practice of casinos is practice of images.
Yeah.
As in, the greater images than the images that you kind of encounter in your average experience.
That's why casinos of four elements, colours, space and consciousness.
There's not focusing on a desk.
That means focusing on what you're looking at.
If you're not actually seeing it, you can only look at something because it's already an image.
Because it's already known as an image.
It's already appeared as an image.
It's already enduring as an image.
So it's more about discerning more.
That's why, like, was it the Sariput or who was it?
The block of wood.
Mahamogalana.
Discerning it as different.
Yeah.
As air, as basis of air, basis of water, basis of fire.
Attractive.
Attractive, ugly.
The same thing.
Yeah.
Because it is.
It's the block of wood.
It's so far down that if you look at the more general nature of what images it pertains to,
it has solidity.
The image of solidity is there.
The image of heat is there.
And the image of beauty is there.
And it's rather that, so the image of solidity is that sort of higher ground where you can
see the block of wood.
Yeah.
It's within the experience of seeing the block of wood, but you see the higher ground as
coming first structurally, not the block of wood you're staring at.
And that's why the Buddha said, like, when you develop the casinas, like, his mind gets,
like he said, the Manprese then, I don't know, the casino of earth, the mind develops upon
the image of earth, image of solid, and that's literally in everything you can ever perceive
has a degree of solid, which means it pertains to the element of earth.
It's within that.
His mind develops upon that, he then develops dispassion, understanding, and escape in regard
to the image of earth.
And what is then to be said about everything that's inferior to it?
He abandoned it completely.
Water, fire, air, blue, yellow, light, and so on.
The point is, the principle is you get to discern an image on account of your current thought
or sense objects, but you get to understand there's an image coming first there.
So for most people, they might discern an image, but they'll always put it second.
So they'll put that which is first and second, and their second sight, they'll put it first.
And that's how natural assumption of things from the world first come to me here.
As in here, there, between the two, it's already an image of space in your mind.
And that's what's first structurally.
You wouldn't have any concept of distance, movement, intentionality, if the image is
not there, providing you with possibilities of that.
So the image is fundamental.
Yes.
And when you have a thought of now the fundamental, that's an image in your mind.
Any particular image, content, has the nature of image.
Sure.
There is no image, and now you have something different to an image, within an image.
All you can access.
Is images within images?
You can't step out.
Because any thought of something is not an image.
You can have an image of, so I have an image of a tape measure of this yellow thing in
my hand, and now I can, within that, start looking at different components of that thing,
and all of those are further images.
And even if I don't know what this is for, so I don't have a particular purpose in my
mind of this thing, of color, I have shape, image of color, shape is already in my mind.
And then, oh, so then there is the image in my mind, and there is a thing in my hand.
Thing in my hand is an image in my mind.
So it's mind within the mind, within the mind, within the mind, within the mind, within the
mind, the external world within the mind, the internal thoughts in my abstraction within
the mind.
So the mind comes first and things can never leave the mind.
That mind, not the mind of abstract thinking which is already within the mind I'm talking
about, as in within the image.
You cannot possibly relate to it, you cannot think it, you cannot designate it, you cannot
even fleetingly be aware of, what was that?
You cannot even ask a question in regard to it, if it's not there at least to some extent
as an image.
That extent is an extent of an image.
That's why the casino, literal meaning of casino is extent, totality or something, totality
of the extent, or the extent of totality.
You can't be more specific than that, because that's as specific as it is.
Can you ask a question about something?
So you don't know specifically what it is, but there's something you want to ask.
Oh, I can't remember what it was, but I have a question.
There has to be an image there of that extent, that extent of ambiguity, the extent of lack
of clarity.
Oh, my mind is empty now, it's blank, there is no thoughts in it.
That's the thought of the images there.
So you truly conceiving an objective reality free from you is inconceivable, because that's,
you can only even relate to it in a wrong manner, or right manner, in any manner, because
it's there as an image enduring, how can you even talk about it or think it?
And so if you're able to discern the extent of image, like the image of manifestation,
then you discern everything that has a nature to manifest.
Exactly, and if you also recognize the fact that these images have the characteristic
of, I'm subjected to them, I didn't create them.
Yeah, they have a reason to manifest them.
And there is absolutely no reason for ownership.
They endure, they persist while they're changing, they're enduring.
Images.
Oh, I can, I can put this, I can throw it away, I can use it, I can save it, I can do lots
of things, because an image of it is still there for me.
If you had an image of that, it disappears, either through this body being destroyed or
the counterpart that's necessary, whatever, of my senses being destroyed.
Which is also another image, but yeah, at last.
Which is another image, exactly.
You can't even think of the pure world, pure destruction, pure anything, without having
it manifested as an image in your mind.
They're saying you're subjected to images.
So how can you not be subjected?
What do you think?
So, because if you, you know, an image is there for me, so that's, so that's afflicting
me.
Yeah.
In the sense of I'm being subjected to it.
But if I see that image is just there, I want to see that image is just there, but there's
an image of for me.
Yeah.
But that's an image.
So that's secondary to image.
It's not, why is it secondary?
It's an image.
Secondary, only in your assumed relationship between the two images, the content of it.
What is the content of for me?
Well, it's different in content, like this is not the concept of for me.
What is the content of that tape?
What is the content of it?
Colour, the shape.
And does colour have a content?
They're saying, yeah, yeah.
So I'm saying that when you say content, it's an image, not separate from it.
So it's another image that you yet somehow assume to be the material content of my image.
As if that's not an image.
As if that's not an image, which means any sense of materiality or mentality has to be
within an image.
So type of image.
Type of image.
Yeah.
Why would you worry about that?
It's just instead of two images, start thinking about one.
You said, this is for me.
So there's an image of this, there's an image for me, which is more important there.
The image of this or the image for me?
Well, the image for me, because it's an account for me that I feel and suffer.
So you have an image for me, which has the nature of an image.
So if you understand the nature of an image for me, you understood the nature of all images
that are for you, which is literally anything you would be perceiving.
So that's what I mean.
It's not like comparing and figuring out the relationship between the two images.
Why? Because you're failing to understand the common nature of it, which is it's an image.
But if you are thinking about an image that doesn't pertain for me, means now you're thinking
like a second hand sort of, abstractly.
You want to make it relevant, relevant, which means on the fundamental level of the experience,
which is where the appropriation is, where the sense of ownership, sense of atta, everything
is.
So it's like a suffering.
Suffering, suffering.
What is suffering?
It's an image.
Whatever.
What is suffering?
What's present in your mind?
Suffering.
What is suffering?
Pain and discomfort.
The pain and the discomfort stands for the image of suffering.
It's an image of suffering, image of pain.
So what is the image of pain then?
What are the characteristics of the image of pain?
How would you describe it?
Which is the necessary image for the image of suffering?
What's the image of pain?
Well, it's not, it is the image of pain, I don't know.
Well, again, it's easy.
I don't say it's not one thing.
Whatever you say, it's probably going to be more accurate than to try to think about what
it is.
Because when I say the image of pain, it's all like, where is the image of pain?
The fact that you're thinking about something means there is the image of that there, to
that extent.
I'm asking you, tell me the extent of the image of pain when I ask you, what is the
image of pain?
I don't tell you, tell me the right image of pain.
What is the extent of the pain when you hear, what's the image of pain?
Displeasure, the uncomfortable, the not wanted.
Not wanted.
So all these things have in common.
No.
That's in common, that's a common attitude to all these things.
This pleasure, this comfort, no wanting means no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no.
Is no in things or is no in your attitude in regard to things?
In your attitude.
In your attitude in regard to things you are subjected to.
So where is then the suffering, that you said it has a necessity, image, the resisting
of it.
So it's basically then the suffering is not in the image of pain, the suffering is in
you saying no to the image of pain.
But how can you even say no to an image of pain, to an image, without an image?
Because saying no to the image of pain implies you having, well, saying no to there is an
image implies you having, you can move outside of the space that has a reason based on the
base of that image.
Saying no to this means you can replace it with something else from the outside, yet
all that is within this you are saying no to.
So you are responding to an image, by an image, with another image.
So discerning the nature of images will free you from suffering then, because the image
of pain is not the suffering.
The image of discomfort is not the suffering.
So when I say I am afflicted by images, that is an image.
That's an image.
Which I am afflicted by, that's an image.
Because of another image, which is your attitude of these, which you haven't been seen as an
image.
Yeah, I'm separating that.
That's what the necessary reason for the right view is seeing the sign of your mind.
And then within the now established sign of where your mind is, you can start to discern
these images.
The sign of the mind is an image.
It's the most general image of where my mind is, which most people engage with the senses
in the world today, today at the level they don't see it.
That's why it's a necessary condition for becoming Sotipana, sign of the mind.
But now this is even further where we're speaking, where it's basically seeing the presence
of the enduring, resisting images within that mind of me or whatever else.
So not seeing, exactly, not seeing your attitude of, not seeing basically the attitude of resisting
as an image.
You kind of give it, gratuitously give it more validity on a kind of, you assume it
separate from all the images you're resisting to.
Can you be resisting an image if there is no image there to begin with?
If there is no image of pain, can you be resisting it, inconceivable?
Yet, you somehow assume that you resisting it is the first and then just these things
coming up, moving them away and chasing them away and accepting them and rejecting them.
I mean, it's kind of, it's kind of like phenomenology, just recognising the true phenomenon, yeah,
they're taken to the extreme of basically, you know, just recognising that there are
these images there, these phenomena there that had to be there and that, yeah, they
can't not be there and they're so close to you that you normally look through them and
take them for granted.
Yeah, and you will be taking them for granted because by looking through them, you start
seeing further through and that you see further through and that's how the whole sensuality
proliferates as well because you're also not indifferent to these things.
Every image is simultaneously felt pleasantly or pleasantly or neutrally, has to be.
One of those things has to be.
And given that you have attitude in wanting pleasure or avoiding pain, means some images
will be wanted, which means you'll be going for the content, failing to see the nature
of the image and another images will be rejected, means trying to deny the content, failing
to see the nature of the image.
And that's how you're made bound with the image.
But if you were to see that which is wanted, that which is not wanted, as images, as that
sort of common ground.
That's what I mean, like even these ambiguous things, wanting, do you understand what wanting
is?
Wanting, wanting.
How would you describe wanting?
I'll take a particular example.
I want this.
I want to eat.
So what is my wanting in this particular instance?
Yeah.
Okay, so exactly.
So it has to be, it has to be that thing.
So you can do both.
First take that thing.
Did you have any say in the manifestation of an image of that thing?
If that thing is not, because I see, I'm not seeing the food now, yet I know I want food.
How's that possible?
If the food is generally entirely, solely, fully material, how can I even think it?
It's not.
Spiritual and mental are images first, and they always remain images.
Now they're images that are sort of images of the senses, and they're images that are
images of the mind, but they're all images.
And while the senses, the five senses operate, they will be the images of the senses.
While the mind is there, the mind operates, they will also be the image of the mind.
It's not that the images of the senses, and then there are also, you know, the real objects
of the senses.
Again, object of the senses.
Image upon image upon image upon image.
Or an image.
So seeing an image.
Means seeing the mind coming first.
Seeing an image, and always seeing an image.
Well you don't need to, it's really discerning an image.
It's not like I always have to be seeing the image, because you have no choice but to
see anything else.
Yes, discerning that.
But discerning what you're seeing.
So Putujana sees images, that's all he can see.
Arahan sees images, that's all he can see.
The difference is for Putujana, he misconceives images to be there which they're not.
As being separate from his mind.
Yeah.
Whereas...
Well then the whole idea of separation comes from it.
By assuming external, internal, both, neither mind, not mind.
And what we're talking about here is the direction of unification of mind, of Samadhi.
Unification, exactly.
That's it.
Because you discern the unifying contact, the unifying nature.
That's when I ask you first, I say what's in common?
Do you're looking at a tape measure, and you're thinking about not seeing it?
What's in common?
So it's training in regard to the ambiguity of images, not to clarify it into detail,
but to recognize it the extent of its ambiguity.
Because it's only ambiguity of the content, ambiguity of the detail.
Not the ambiguity of the nature of images I'm being subjected to.
That's what I mean.
And not being able to grip with that kind of recognition of that ambiguity, that's why
you don't like wanting, not wanting, all these terms become abstract for most people.
And let alone if you start thinking about emptiness, not self, impermanence, well imagine
how abstract that is.
And abstract means you're not seeing it, that's it.
You're not seeing an image of it.
You're thinking it, which is already a second.
You have a thought, but you aren't seeing that thought as the image that it is.
Exactly.
As an image, and you're misconceiving that thought.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Because there is an image there, whether you see it or not.
So literally any attitude, as a wanting, so wanting requires you.
So let's dwell on the you aspect of wanting.
Me.
What is the image of me?
The image that comes to mind, the most ambiguous, distant, me, me, me, me, shape of a body.
Exactly.
But that's what it stands for.
Yeah, yeah.
You're not thinking about it, and you end up having all this attitude that it's more
than that.
But whenever you think, that's all it is.
Shape of the body, memory of the face that you see in reflection, place, first point
of view, yeah, place, me, this.
So while you have that image of shape of the body as me, which is me, to have any say in
how that shape of the body has been manifested for me, subjective, what came before, after,
can I even approach it on a step outside of it?
Or am I always secondary to that shape of the body?
Or that memory of the face, of my own face, that stands for when I think of me in my own
name?
No.
Because you were basically locked inside of it, or, sorry, locked inside of it more accurately.
Like, if you look left, right, up or down, whatever, you will be in it.
Yeah.
Oh, so how can I then be the owner of this when all of this has been subjected to these
images?
That's all unsubjected, as well.
That's all unsubjected.
There's nothing outside that.
Oh, but there's more, there's an image of more.
Because you're from a big duty of an extent, more.
Ah, but that's an image.
Yeah.
Yeah, I'm subjected to it.
But I don't like the I am subjected to images, saying that because it gives me the impression
that I...
Well, it gives you space to be separate from it.
I am subjected to these images.
But you have to start like that.
Sure, sure, sure.
But about the body, the senses, the mind is subjected to images.
That's what a mind is.
You can't, there can't be a mind without images.
But if I say manifestation is subjected to...
Yeah, that's absolutely fine.
If that becomes a more accurate way of describing it for you, that's fine.
But for most people, in order to start, you have to start like that and then eventually
you come to click, okay, but I'm subjected to this, I'm subjected to that, I'm subjected
to that.
I am.
Hmm.
Well, isn't that another image?
I'm subjected to it.
And then you get to upgrade your own description.
But as I said, the starting point is the point of ignorance, the point of mis-conceiving,
which means you will not be able to cease immediately things like the Arahant does, approximating
how Arahant sees you get to understand what Arahant is.
Which is what makes you become one.
All dhammas are another, not self.
Because not self is an image, or self is an image.
Well, you could say that, yeah, the sense of self, as you say, as we kind of just described,
it kind of becomes a more fundamental image than everything else that comes to your senses.
Like whether I'm seeing, hearing, tasting, touching, as you said yourself, it's for me.
So it's that image is in common to all these senses.
So what if I were to then understand and abandon that image, abandon in the sense of
experiencing dispassion and remove the ownership of it, you have removed the ownership of the
five senses.
You have removed sensuality, sense desires.
By removing the ownership of this image of self.
Yeah.
Exactly.
That all these things come through.
That's what we meant by establishing your mind upon the totality of the extent of solidity,
totality of the extent of erineness or whatever I want to translate it.
Basically by practicing casinas, you establish your mind to a certain level, everything inferior
to that is abandoned, or you know, perceptions of the forest to abandon perceptions of the
village.
They had inferior perceptions in regard to that.
As in either way, which doesn't matter how particular perceptions get, this is what they
have in common and you abandon that common ground.
So whether it's sight, sound, smell, taste, touch, the common ground is image of me, for
me, mine, I am.
You abandon that, you abandon all these inferior images within that image.
And by abandoning means not preventing it from arising because you haven't created its
arising to begin with.
It was never a problem.
Abandoning means removing the gratuitous attitudes of resisting it or craving for it.
You will crave for things for as long as you think you can crave for things.
Full understanding that craving is impossible, the way you assumed it, that's how you stop
assuming.
How can you crave for something that's already there?
Exactly.
As I said, oh, I don't see the food now, but I want to crave the food.
If my craving is in the food, if the food is the craving, I would need to be in contact
with it in order to crave for it.
But you are.
I don't even have food.
But you are in contact with it.
Exactly.
But not the content on the domain that I'm craving for.
No, no, no, with the image.
Exactly.
So you realize, oh, so my craving is then on the level of the image yet, I don't stay
on the level of the image when I crave, I go out and seek food and steal food and attack
and kill and work and earn whatever, rightly or wrongly, I go out and seek these objects
because I crave in regard to the image of food.
And that gets paired then with a discomfort of hunger.
So they're naturally associating then seeking this food that I can put in my belly, alleviates,
my gratuitous attitude of resisting pain or physical nature, discomfort of hunger.
But discomfort of hunger, again, it's an image.
An image that literally you can put anything in your mouth, eat it.
You wouldn't worry about the taste then, because you fully stay with the discomfort of the
hunger as a context.
Okay, I have to deal with this, discomfort, because the body will die.
I don't need to crave for it in order to do it, but most people don't act on that level
or most people act on another whole layer added to it, which is, yeah, I'm hungry, but
I want particular taste.
And that's another image that can never be anything other than an image.
But you assume taste to be in the objects of your senses, which is another image.
But you assume the materiality of it, independent of you, and that's why sensuality is wrong,
because it's a perversion of the right order of things.
If you weren't perverting the order, it wouldn't be unwholesome, it wouldn't be wrong.
So things that don't pervert the order are not wrong, such as hunger, putting something
in your stomachs, you're not hungry.
You don't misconceive what comes first, and the purpose then cannot become corrupted.
That's the whole instruction of the word to mindfully, eat mindfully, as in not to observe
every movement of your tongue, but mindful of the purpose why you're eating it.
Like I will eat for this reason, for this reason, I will not eat for this reason, that's
the mindfulness of eating, not chewing, chewing, slowly, slowly, chugging, chugging, chugging.
Yeah.
No, why am I eating is because hunger is there.
So you have an image of hunger.
Image of hunger disappears, as in non-gets replaced image of non-hunger, you stop eating.
Not even a second, what if this taste, because all that became far removed now.
There was never the purpose of the taste to begin with.
The only reason you were even attracted to tastes is because of the pressure of the hunger.
Yet you completely then, as a result of it, gratuitously assumed taste to being the matter
of things that you can somehow access through your eating, access the external world, that's
another image in your mind.
But you think, that's not an image, that's the world, that's the reality.
And by doing so, you always remain bound to then that extent of assumption.
That's the sensuality, the sensual thirst, wanting the object.
How can you want the object unless there is an image of that you're wanting in your mind?
And then what is the object?
And if I'm consuming, crushing, eating, devouring, enjoying, whatever, object, it's another image.
In escapable, you're fully within that.
And when you fully understand it, you cannot even conceive outside of it.
You stop conceiving outside of it, which is sensual domain, which is the assumption of
sensuality.
So contemplating images, people, images.
Contemplating images, not in an abstract sense, but in a sense that they're already there.
Descerning images.
Contemplating images means discerning images.
Whatever it is, my experience is whole, my body.
Image of the body present here.
I don't need to look at it.
The fact that I can see my body is here, even if I close my eyes, means I haven't even
seen the fact that then I can know what to look at when I say my body is here.
Means I have an image that's there.
How would you even know where to look for it, unless the image already implies the direction
of the space, the space for this position and so on?
Yeah, I mean, I've got my eyes closed, I've got my eyes open, still an image, like there's
nothing.
He's just fundamentally changes that.
Yeah, there is an image of the senses and the image of the mind.
The image is there.
And you have both.
The image is there, while the image of the senses and the image of the mind is there.
But you can't attend to it to the same extent.
Has to be one.
That's where the six senses is.
So the image is there and the six types of images are there.
On account of the six senses being there.
That's the sense basis.
It's like a field at the extent that's already an image within which then the sights come,
which are further images within that extent.
If there is no field where sights are, sights will not be manifested at all.
So understanding the six sense basis means you overcome centrality, not by dealing, managing
or getting rid of the objects of your set's basis, uprooting the framework of the basis,
uprooting and then removing ownership, and misconceiving lack of discernment, not seeing
it as an horizon image, the present in yours.
That's why like suitors that deal with this, they talk about this, often like for people
who deal with this abstract, sounds abstract, sounds.
And then the idea of abstraction from a mind they cannot understand, the nature of abstraction,
and the other, assuming the extension of this already gratuitously external material reality,
and then you think all these meditation experiences get to pertain to the extension of this weirdly
assumed external reality, like infinite space.
It's the infinity of space, either perception or perception.
It becomes immediately like this transcendental universe elsewhere from these senses, magically.
Whereas in fact there are images that actually are present, but need to be discerned in order
to sort of transcend.
Yeah, that's what I said in Majima, one by one, when he's developing all the jhanas and
then all the space of infinite space and so on, he would ask himself, oh he's the mode
in this, as in he's the higher, he's the greater than this, but he wouldn't go around to find
it.
He would just look at the same thing and then see that there is more to it.
He would look at the same log, and he wouldn't go and read a book, and what's the next stage?
Let me find another piece of log that's more liquid than the solid, that no, it's within
the same, there is more, so it's more on the level of the images, not more on the level
of fantasizing about theory of linear connections between things that you already assume to
be.
And in fact isn't each progressive stage more like the sort of negative of what?
It is here, but that negative is also an outside thing.
That's why there is, even in Putujan experience, there is the element of Nibbana present, which
is why some people, some traditions, completely then jump to conclusions saying, ah so we
are already Nibbana, because the Buddha said we all have element of Nibbana, we do.
Element means present absence.
So it's present as an absence, means it's possible to discern it, bring the context
of it, develop the theme of it as the Buddha would say, and that's how you develop it.
But saying that present absence means I'm already in that which is absent, because it's
present as an absence, well that's jumping the gun.
So there is the element of Nibbana in everyone's experience, yet the actual Nibbana, there
is the presence of it in everyone's experience.
And that's another good thing to reflect, because you stop assuming it to be at the
end of the world, or at the end of your meditation, observational technique, it's already here.
Every minute of your life, element of Nibbana is with you.
Understand the theme of that element, understand the characteristics of that absence, there
is Nibbana for you.
I mean absence of greed, absence of aversion, absence of delusion.
And it shares the qualities of all things we've been talking about, this kind of, yeah.
So is there beyond when Saripurta asks, oh is there more than this, means exactly that,
discerning it as a present absence, discerning it as a possibility to develop and develop.
And then later on, as the Buddha says, he would develop it, oh yeah, he verified that
there is more, there was more, now that present absent is not absent anymore, because he fully
discerned the context of that which was absent.
If there was not even present, even a tiny bit, as an absence, you couldn't go in that
direction, how can you discern something that doesn't exist?
Hence the element of Nibbana, you know the all the dhtras of the Buddha lists, it's
not the physical elements scattered in the world that you collect like gems or something.
It's basically the present absences, the absences of all the absence of dispassion, all these
themes are present absences, all possibilities to develop in your practice are elements,
as in the present as absences.
But again, it has to be an image to that extent.
Even if you complete Aha essential Putujana, Nibbana, Nibbana, what is Nibbana?
You have some image, even if it's an image of a word.
And that's what I mean, it closer then represents that ambiguous image, closer represents what
Nibbana is in your experience than when you get to theorize what Nibbana is, because at
least you're looking in the direction of that absence that is present as such.
That's why some monks needed very little detailed instruction, some monks needed more.
With the minimum instruction they would have turned to the right direction of the right
absence.
And then dwell on it and understand the context of it and by doing so develop it.
Even Jna is the same principle, the word we say develop the theme of Jna.
Like Jna is basically so close to the point of view that's why people, that's why it
takes effort to attain it, to develop it.
It's not like Jna is figuring something out at the end of a certain effort.
Jna is basically the way you are seeing regarding things that you then got polluted
with your own ignorance, with your own last aversion and habits.
So it's removal of this pollution to basically recognize that certain imperturbable basis,
unified basis.
Well, whether I think about the sense object, whether I think about joy, grief, an image
has to be there enduring and you become discerning of the enduring image regardless of the content
of whatever points you.
That's already a unified mind and that's already Jna on account of any experience
you can have.
That's all those different ways of entering Jna, the comment that is compiled from the
suttas but like looking at the corpse established Jna, mindfulness of the body established
Jna.
So I'm like this results in Jna.
Jna is an attitude of unification upon certain discernments, discernment of dispassion,
discernment of sensuality, abandoning in that side so it's not the content, it's the
theme, the nature of the image, the characteristics of the unified mind.
So that's always, doesn't matter the experience, whether I'm feeling good, I'm feeling bad,
I'm physical discomfort, physical comfort, whatever it is, doesn't matter how complex
it is, how ambiguous it is, how content kind of inclined it is, image has to be there.
Any idea of direction, any idea of the movement, two, four against both neither, requires an
image to be there enduring, some ambiguous image.
So it's recognizing, learning how to discern an image in its ambiguity, not try to replace
it with content that you deemed a worthy threshold of it.
Because how can you be exercising the threshold of necessary content unless there is an image
that needs to be built up to that level?
I just think it's about being skilled, I think it's about being skilled in images, which
is being skilled in dhamma, being skilled in the mind, seeing the mind quickly.
As soon as it arises, as soon as the image is manifested, he sees it exactly for what
it is.
He doesn't need to catch himself down the line and then, what, you will need that in
the beginning.
It's just like the word for image is dhamma.
Sure, being skilled in dhamma, yeah.
And that's why this teaching is the teaching, the dhamma, the image.
The Buddha was teaching the image, the fundamental image, the universal image in common to any
five aggregates, anywhere in the, any universe or realm, understanding the image.
And that image is understanding the nature of images, the extent of images.
Not the image extent in terms of telling you how many there are, the extent of the nature.
So if he was talking about all these images, it's because it was the context of understanding
the nature.
The nature of images cannot be owned, cannot be appropriated, cannot be yours, cannot be
controlled.
You are the one subjected to them, not the other way around.
You understand that?
You are free from the entire samsara, all of it, absolutely, nothing left, samsara, universe,
rebirth.
Yeah, all these different directions, what they have in common, they are an image.
Not this image, not that, specifically, maybe in biggers, but as such, an image is there.
What else is there when I have these images, oh, it's always me, another image of me is
always there.
So that's kind of more in common to all these other things that you've been dwelling on.
So why don't you dwell on something that's more in common to those particular things,
as opposed to chasing down particular leads?
And that's how inevitably you will end up to self-awareness, responsibility, point of
view, all these things we talk about.
You don't have to go and have refined images, do you have to have refined images?
They wouldn't be refined images.
So even the...
If you're refining your images, it means you're not seeing them as images.
You're basically chasing the content, which is another image that you fail to see, hence
the idea of refinement, of replacing it with another image of a different kind.
Yeah, ambiguous images.
The true refinement of an ambiguous image is to recognize its ambiguity to be an image.
That's how you refine it.
You don't refine it by providing content for it.
That's likeologization, basically.
Yeah, just now we were talking this whole idea of constant, every time you say constant,
everything else?
Meaningless.
Well, if you want to establish your mind upon the unified image, then it's meaningless.
Being distracted becomes inconceivable, meaningless.
As in it's thesis, it's not there anymore.
The mood is an image, has a color to it, has weight to it, that's why the Buddha described
the Sadhipatana for Chitta, elated, expensive, shrunk, depressed, elated, big, small mind.
Because yeah, those are images that mind is.
That is what mind is.
I'm thinking elation, no, it's like you discerning on the kind of mood, an image that's implicit
in it, but you have nothing to do with it, you haven't created it.
You could not have created an image, impossible.
I'm creating an image, is an image that you're subjected to and now you're trying to provide
a secondary content to it that would feel more like yours, so you've begun with an image
of the possibility of creating images.