what is the escape from pain most people think it's hot most people think it is
pleasure pleasure the escape from pain well they don't necessarily think that
I think that's the only escape that I know so the only attitude that a person
without a right view will have only one attitude towards pain which is
covered in pleasure that's the only means of escape that I know either to
try to get rid of the pain because that's more pleasant or to actually finding
some different pleasure to occupy yourself with so you forget about the
pain either way you turn towards pleasure in order to avoid pain because you can't
deal with pain on its own terms so and that that's what the what the sort to
say they put to dinner doesn't know any other escape from pain other than
sensuality essential pleasure that's what I've seen before like the the people
another tractor to sensuality just because it's pleasant and gives you that you
know sweet taste or something they're also dependent on it because that the
only means that their mind has dealing with pain so the prospect of sensuality
it's already something people depend on the possibility of getting placed exactly
at least at least pleasure is is perpetually possible I might be refraining from it
not engaging with sensuality but I'm still using the possibility of pleasure as a
relief from when the pain is there so you still depend on the pleasure I can
deal with this pain now because there is a possibility there is a there is a
promise a prospect of pleasure later on they will be great and so it's worth
enduring this pain now and that's fine everybody like even when you want
hard-hunching to be free from suffering you still have the projected idea of
pleasure through it but the the whole practice revolves around actually not
removing your dependence on sensual pleasure as a mean of dealing with pain
so removing your dependence even on the possibility of sensual pleasure as means
of dealing with pain that's why when people had heard the Buddha described
Nibbana to them the pathogenes in the suttas they were well they were scared
because in their minds it was like oh that's basically complete absence of joy
pleasure the only form of joy and pleasure they're the nanolite of my
nose which is central pleasure so in their minds all this was like this is the
most depressing miserable dreadful thing they will kill me and destroy me if
that's they were they were generally generally shocked afraid by it
good anxiety of fear because mind that depends on pleasure absence of pleasure
means misery but it doesn't absence of pleasure does not mean pain just means
absence of pleasure absence of pain as well so basically what those people were
afraid of was just a pure neutral feeling neither pleasant nor unpleasant but the
mind that depends on pleasure neither pleasant means painful doesn't matter
that it's not unpleasant either the fact that it's not pleasant for the mind
that depends on pleasure is terrifying but it's terrifying not because in
itself it's terrifying it's terrifying because you're refusing to give up your
dependence on pleasure not of fear but that fear feeds your dependence which
then makes you afraid which and feeds the defense it's a vicious circle
centrality or pardana or centrality so this neutral feeling because of your
craving for pleasure it's it's just exactly and that's what the suttas say
when neutral feeling is not known not understood not discerned it will be
felt unpleasantly so that's what meant like you you you nibana is the absence
of joy it's joyless but joylessness does not mean misery
joylessness means equanimity joylessness means no joy and no pain means peace
means evenness but in order to value that the mind needs to train to that
level needs to train for it so in other words you need to discern and
develop wisdom in regard to the neutral feeling and then it will become the
supreme peace of nibana nothing can match that peace but in mind it depends on
pleasure depends on prospect and uses at least the possibility of future
pleasure as a means of relief in regard to the day-to-day pain when that mind
here joylessness that is automatically felt as misery absolute depressing
overwhelming pain it's not pleasant but it's not unpleasant either but you
don't get to value the fact that it's not unpleasant either because you're too
concerned about oh there is no joy so that's the sensory strength needs to be
done before if you have true sensory strength you basically start training
yourself towards joylessness of sensuality and then again the root of
sensuality as the Buddha said so many times is your delight in the joy that
you get on account it's not the beautiful or tasty objects in the world the root
of sensuality is your dependence on that type of pleasure nothing else remove
that dependence on that pleasure and you will find peace so sensory strain is
physically preparing you withdrawing you from that pleasure so then mentally you
can see how gratuitously you depend on it and then choose to withdraw yourself
because oh this is not worth clinging to as the suttas would say but if you're not
physically withdrawn you will never mentally be able to like stop depending
on it so sensory strength means basically emulating nibana pretty much
emulating the non-dependence on on joy that's that's acquired through
senses but you need to start doing it even if you still want to do have it
mentally physically at least you need to be drawn verbally you need to be withdrawn
and then eventually mentally you'll be able to do so as well but yeah once you
start withdrawing yourself on that engaging in pleasures then what will
naturally occur is that experience of mutual freedom well exactly once you
start withdrawing yourself physically from pleasures that's already training
for you to be able to endure the neutral feeling and not freak out in
regard to it so only people that are not withdrawn bodily verbally mentally from
sensuality lose their mind when they recognize what nibana is or that will
kill me that will destroy me if you already have been cultivating sensory
strength say not yourself taming your senses practicing sense control it's not
gonna be as frightening the joylessness of nibana will be something you can
actually get closer to as opposed to lose your mind fall on the ground pull
your hair be the breasts in despair like oh that will kill me as they did when
the Buddha would clearly show what nibana what he's teaching is now that's
what's always said like like those who are free from passion they have no like
fear even in face of death because that's what that is cessation of these
senses upon which what upon which pleasures I depend but those who are
free from passion even when these senses are threatened there is no fear
because there's no passion I there's no dependence on the pleasure of the
senses so the absence of passion means no fear of death means no fear of
nibana means no fear of dispassion doesn't mean speech depression doesn't
mean exactly depression it's only generated from the point of view you
still depends on the pleasure and now you found something that fully like a
crashes that dependence removes it and there is no more future of it and that
is scary because you refuse to give it up or because neutral feeling in itself
is scary so it's joyless but it's also there is but that though that doesn't
mean it's miserable so absence of joy and absence of misery that's the absence of
ambitious and like a thirsty inspiration for achievement and absence of depression
as the other hand in the suit that would say in the terra terra terra terra
gata I delight not in life is actually no delight towards anything in this life
through the senses and I delight not in death right I await my time and that's
the other hand declaration there's no delight and a description of the
fourth John and that's the perfect complete surmounting your equanimity you
know oopak a sati is but it's just a mounting of that pleasure and pain and
joy and grief and the spirit of that pleasure and pain so it's it's
completely steadied mind in a neutral feeling and that's the whole point and
that's what the jana is even the first jana it's it's already from the point of
view of non-jana first jana it's like steadying your mind in the neutral feeling
neutral from that point of view obviously you can go even further and and
refine that neutral feeling up to the point of full jana equanimity but even
the first jana starts by abandoning joy and grief in regard to the world and
unification of the mind that comes on a kind of thinking and pondering and so on
and that in itself it's felt pleasantly in a sense of a neutral peace neutral
feeling when understood it's felt pleasantly that's what the truth is
saying neutral feeling when not understood it is felt unpleasantly to
the understanding your knowledge your discernment of it determines how you're
gonna feel it so joylessness when understood it's pleasant because there's
no disturbance joylessness when not understood it's miserable dreadful
anxious overwhelming so how do you prepare yourself to endure it that which
is overwhelmingly anxious and so on by starting the sensory strength by seeing
the danger in the slightest fault by being watchful mindful careful you're
already practicing strength to be able to endure the neutral feeling which is
initially gonna try to scare you and then you train yourself to that and this
passion is being developed again it comes back to also the other pride
talk with it or non-activity non-engagement fear of boredom that people
have fear of nothing to do so whether they practice Buddhism or not maybe
everything just becomes another thing I do to keep myself occupied because
otherwise I get overwhelmed by the neutrality I mean boredom is truly just
neutral yet it's the more dreadful thing for every mind that's not developed
so there's more understanding you again the more pleasure will become that
neutral feeling that absence of joy
it's not that you know Aravan's feelings is some like mystical dimension
no it's just three types of feelings whether you're protrusion or an
Aravan is just how much influence those three types of feeling have over you and
your decisions and your views and your assumptions or whether you are free
from views and assumptions in regards to these feelings and then in the felt
there's just the felt and the same is just the scene her just the same principle
so the feeling that's felt your neutral in regard to it
there's no pressure so there's no pressure means truly there's really no
feeling there in that sense theogenous feeling are gone in an Aravan but it
doesn't mean that Aravan has no aggregate of feeling and so how can Aravan feel
without feeling seeming contradiction well develop understanding of a neutral
feeling and you see and that's the same like when Sariputta declared oh what a
pleasure what a pleasure and the dying I think in the suit is asking would you
what's pleasure says Nibana it's it's pleasure it's like but didn't you on
another occasion say Nibana there is nothing felt and he says yes and that's
what is pleasant the fact there's nothing felt it's it's pleasant so the
understanding of there's no feeling here it's very agreeable and it's it all boils
down to development in regard to the neutral feeling obviously in order to
begin even any development in regard to neutral feeling and being able to do
it and withstand it you need to stop habitually giving into the pleasant
feeling and feeding the thirst for more pleasure and you have to habitually stop
giving in to the feeling of the unpleasant feeling to try to get rid of
it resisting it you are by doing these two things you are equipping yourself to
endure neutrality that's felt neither pleasantly but not unpleasant the
either clarifying it exactly by by enduring it you as I said you're becoming
more familiar with it so non-activity enduring the initial anxiety of boredom
and finding value and even that's what we would say like the solitude is for
somebody who is developed wisdom to start finding pleasure in solitude otherwise
you won't otherwise it's terrifying without a wisdom solitude mind cannot
bear it and again the Buddha did outline what you need to prepare beforehand so
that you can benefit from solitude which is impeccable virtue seeing the danger
in the slightest fault says sure Janas but you know they've usually come with
solitude since restraint right view all these things you develop beforehand and
then if you go to forest remote dwellings when there's only wild
animals living and so on you your mind will not overwhelm you you will be
benefiting from the neutrality of it well if you're in a position where there's
nothing to do basically do you don't need to be top of the forest it often yeah
top like a remote forest empty or an empty hut empty of activity empty of
activity empty of distraction empty of others turning way as they please so
physically removed but yes apartment will do just fine you do want to have the
environment that will support that but again don't think that that will do the
work for you you will be ready for the solitude if you've already practiced
census strain in regard to the world if you have all already endured joys and
griefs in regard to the world without acting out of it habitually that's how
you surmounting not by running into a solitude or hiding in the forest
because sometimes there are people trying to contrast this yes see the
word I say we should go to the remote dwellings and so on because they don't
deal with their own sensory strength and stuff here now that's like the second
group of herd deer herd from that sutter that we did also recently that
shines the bait and runs on top of mountain yeah but there's no wisdom
developed it so sensory straight in regard to the world in regard to the
central poles in regard to dependence on the drawers and so on needs to be
developed and needs to be endured it's gonna be painful because not because of
the sensory strain but because of your dependence on joys of centrality that's
why you suffer when you first restrain yourself you don't suffer because you
say no to yourself you suffer because you've been saying yes to yeah you've
been saying yes all this time so saying no to yourself just reveals your
addiction your dependence on these gratuitous central joys that you are
responsible that you're fully feeding and maintaining yeah adding to proliferate
so practice towards joylessness
when joylessness is understood it's the utmost peace of gribbility it's nibana
no joy no means joylessness means no delight and it also means no misery and
being unable to be miserable or scared or affected by any type of pain on a
kind of anything including impending death dying you know terminal diagnosis or
whatever else which eventually will have to occur no more prospect of pleasure
well things that are being will be destroyed by death and not things you
depend on anymore why because you removed your dependence on gratuitous joy that
came out of that you removed your delight so joylessness that will die
before you die become joyless and you will be unable to be miserable as well